In this assignment we will write code
to control the movement of the enemy.
The enemy will be driven by the animator,
taking movement from the root motion of
the animation clips that we provided previously.
Animator parameters control which animation
states the animator should play
and therefore how the enemies move.
We will set these parameters using velocities
from the nav mesh agent
and we will modify the values with code
to correct certain behaviours.
When using the nav mesh the system gives
the agent a desired velocity.
This is not the actually velocity that the agent
is moving, but one that it should head towards.
Nav mesh agents such as our enemy
have a waypoint path to a destination,
shown here by a red line.
The agent turns to face the waypoint
whilst travelling towards it, and we say that
the velocity of the agent, shown by the black arrow
is heading towards the desired velocity,
shown with the green arrow.
This desired velocity will be the basis
of the values that we'll send to the enemy's
animator parameters Speed and Angular Speed.
Let's begin by creating the script to
control these parameters.
Add a new script to the Robot Guard called
EnemyAnimation.
Select char_robotGuard and choose
Add Component - New Script
and name it EnemyAnimation.
Launch the script for editing and prepare it.
First let's take a look at the class variables
that we will need. There is only one public variable
that we will need, which is a float
we will call deadZone.
The deadzone, similar to a deadzone in input terms,
is a value range which should be ignored
in the case of enemy navigation
we do not want the enemies to attempt to turn
when the difference between their forward direction
and their desired velocity is very small.
And we define this with the deadzone.
Without this we would see the enemies
oversteering and walking in wavering
lines towards each waypoint.
As shown in this example.
We will need 6 private variables.
The first of which is a reference
to the player's transform.
We will need this to set the direction that the enemy
faces to the player when they are in sight.
Next we will need a reference to the
EnemySight script so that we can change the
animation based on whether the player is in
sight or not.
Then we will need a reference to the nav mesh agent
component which will be guiding the enemies movement.
Next we will need a reference to the animator
component and to help reference it's
parameters we will need a reference to
the HashIDs script.
The last will be an instance of the helper class
that we made during the last assignment,
AnimatorSetup.
Next we will use the Awake function to
setup these references.
In addition to allocating the references
we will also need the awake function to perform
a number of other actions.
Firstly we must make sure that the rotation
of the enemy is set by the animator
and not by the nav mesh agent.
This will reduce the appearance of foot slipping
whilst turning corners.
We will also need to create an instance
of our helper function from the previous
assignment, and in doing so
call it's constructor.
We can parse in the animator component
and the HashIDs script that we already
have a reference to.
We need to set the layer weight of the different
layers of the animator.
The Weight value controls the balance of animation
from the layers on the animator.
We are going to make both the Shooting
and Gun layers have a weight of 1,
meaning that they will totally override the
layers beneath them, such as the base layer.
This means that the animation would be purely
based on those layers.
However we are using a mask for both the
Shooting and Gun layers so that the only
parts of the body that they can override
are the upper body and right hand respectively.
So we use the Set Layer Weight function
and use the integer of the layer.
For example the base layer should be referenced
with a 0, so because we're referencing Shooting and Gun
we will use 1 to represent Shooting
and 2 to represent Gun
and we set both of them to 1f.
The last thing that we need to do in the Awake function
is to convert the deadZone variable
from degrees to radians.
This is because the animator controller we made
earlier measures the parameter in radians.
Luckily the Mathf class has a constant
that we can use for this, deg2rad.
A constant is like a variable,
however once it has been set it cannot be changed.
In order to convert a number from degrees
to radians we simply multiply by this constant.
The majority of this script will be setting
up the animations based on the nav mesh agent.
To do this we will create a function that we
can call in the Update function.
We will call it NavAnimSetup.
The first thing we are going to do in this function
is to create two floats for the Speed
and Angle parameters that we will parse to
the helper class's Setup function.
Now we need to decide if the player is in sight.
If the player is in sight then we
want the enemy to stop, so we will set
the Speed parameter to 0.
Now we need to find the angle between the direction
the enemy should face and the direction
it is actually facing.
Negative to the left and positive to the right.
We will need to make another function in order
to do this for us.
It needs to return a float
and will need 3 vector3s as parameters.
A vector we are measuring from,
a vector we are measuring to,
and another vector to determine which
way is up. We will call this function
FindAngle.
The toVector we are going to parse in to
this is the nav mesh agent's desired velocity.
This will sometimes equal 0.
If this is the case then it might cause an error
so we will need to put in a way to check for this.
If the desired velocity is 0
then we want the direction to be 0.
If this is the case we can simply return
0 from the function, and if this isn't
the case then we will continue with
the rest of the code.
The next step is to find out the absolute
value of the angle.
We can do this very simply with the
vector3.angle function.
Now we need to determine whether this angle is
to the left or to the right of the
forward direction. To do this we can find the
cross product of the two vectors
and check the resultant normal vector.
Using the lefthand rule for the cross product
we know that if the toVector is to the right
of the fromVector their normal
will point upwards.
See the lesson on Vector Maths linked below
if you need reminding of this.
Now we can find the .product of this
Normal and the Up vector that we parsed in.
If the Normal and the Up vector are pointing
in the same direction the result will
be greater than 0, therefore we can multiply
the angle that we've already calculated
by the sign of the .product that we have found.
This will show whether the desired velocity
is to the left or the right of the Forward vector.
Remember that we need this angle to be in radians.
So we need to multiply it by the
Deg2Rad constant that we used earlier.
And finally we can return the angle.
Now that we have a function to find the angle
we can use it in our NavAnim
setup function.
The fromVector is the enemy's forward vector,
the toVector is the vector from the
enemy to the player and we will use the
enemy's upVector as the up vector.
Now we need to account for when the
player is not in sight.
Given that the player is not in sight
we want the speed to be based on the
nav mesh agent's desired velocity.
To achieve this we can use projection
in order to project the desired velocity
vector on to the enemy's forward vector.
Projection allows us to take 2 vectors
and find out how much of the first vector
is in the direction of the other vector.
A projection is found by drawing a line
from the tip of the first vector
towards the second vector.
It must be drawn so that this line is
perpendicular to the direction
of the second vector.
The point of the intersection of this line
defines the end of the projection vector.
Since we are projecting the nav mesh agent's
desired velocity on to the enemy's forward vector
the resultant vector will be small
if the enemy is not facing the same direction
as the desired velocity.
The speed variable will be set to the
magnitude of the projection vector.
Without using this projection the
enemy might have a high speed whilst
facing the wrong direction, and thus running a
wide arch in order to face the correct direction.
Next we need to determine the angle.
Again we will use our findAngle function
but this time the toVector is the
nav mesh agent's desired velocity.
Since we are using damping to set the animator
parameters when they are turning
they won't stop turning as soon as they face
their correct direction. Instead they will
continue to turn very slightly.
They will then need to turn back to compensate.
This will result in a snaking motion
as they finish turning corners.
In order to prevent this we need to put
a check in to our function.
This check will simply be whether the angle
is small, i.e. less than our deadZone variable.
If it is then we avoid using the animator controller
to set the direction that the enemy is facing
To do this we set the angle to 0
and set the enemy's transform to look at
the desired velocity from it's own position.
Now that we have calculated the speed and
angle we can parse them in to
the Setup function of our helper class
animator setup.
They can then have damping applied and be
parsed in to the animator controller.
Now that we have our completed NavAnimSetup function
we can call it in the Update function.
Note that whilst we have inserted this function
above ones that we have already written
this is not necessary.
We are doing this in order to maintain a flowing
structure to the script.
First come the class variables,
then the Awake function is called,
then every frame the Update function is called.
This in turn calls the NavAnimSetup function
which calls the FindAngle function.
The last thing we need to do with this script
is to effect the root motion of the enemy.
Normally we have the choice of either applying
root motion or not on the animator component.
However if we use the OnAnimatorMove
function, which is called after Update every frame,
then we can effect the root motion manually.
There are two things we need to control in this function.
The velocity of the enemy and it's rotation.
To control the velocity we must set the nav
mesh agent's velocity to the delta position
of the animation divided by the delta time.
This is the change in position per frame.
As for the rotation, we have already set the
nav mesh agent so that it does not control rotation.
This is so that we can effect the rotation
directly using the animation's root rotation.
And that's our script complete.
Now that the script is finished,
we can save it and return to the Editor.
Don't forget to tidy the script away by
putting it in to the Enemy folder.
Expand the Scripts folder and drop it from
the root of Assets in to the Enemy folder.
Now let's save the scene and save the project.
In the next assignment we will be making a
script to make the enemy shoot the player.