The text component is used to render text
on the screen as part of your UI layouts.
The primary property of a text component
is it's text.
This is the string that will be shown on screen.
It can be used as a simple label,
or dynamically to show things like scores for example.
One thing to note is that return works within
this text field to create new lines.
So be aware of this, as well as the possibility
of leaving new empty lines.
The Character section of the component defines
how the characters of the string will look.
The Font is the font asset used for this
particular component.
Unity supports TrueType, OpenType and Dafont typefaces.
But remember that unlike most software
because Unity is authoring an external
game or application, your font must be included
in your project's assets in order to be used.
The style can either be normal, bold or italic,
or bold and italic.
And the font size will be the font size
that it's forced to.
If the font size is too large to fit within the rect
then the text will not be displayed
unless overflow settings are used.
Line spacing is also available to aid
legibility within paragraphs of text.
The Rich Text checkbox allows the use
of text markup, which allows you to use tags
in-line to format text
in a similar way to HTML.
For more details on text markup and how to use it
see the documentation links below.
The Paragraph section defines how text
will sit within it's rect.
Text can be aligned left, centre or right,
top, middle or bottom.
Though in this example we cannot see top, middle or bottom
alignment due to the scrollable nature of the box.
Horizontal Overflow controls what will happen
to the text that exceeds beyond it's horizontal limit.
Wrap will move any text beyond the limit to the next line.
Whereas Overflow will allow the text to extend
beyond the horizontal bounds of the rect.
Vertical Overflow is similar, but works vertically.
Truncate means that any text beyond the vertical
bounds of the rect will be cut.
Overflow will allow the text to go beyond the
vertical limits of the rect.
When Best Fit is checked, the text will ignore the
overflow options and instead make text as large
or as small as necessary to fit within
the available rect.
The Min and Max size properties refer to
the limits of the font size.
When a best fit would mean having text that was
beyond either of these font size limits
the text will obey the normal font size provided.
The appearance of characters of text can be
adjusted by using the Color and Material properties.
Generally, a texture of a material will
not effect the appearance of text that it's supplied to.
Let's take a quick look at the text component
in use dynamically.
Very simply, this text element represents the
score in this game.
By default we've written in an example line.
But this is only for design purposes
as it's replaced at runtime by the
string defined within our script
which sets the score dynamically
as the player scores points.
For more information on the text component
and using text dynamically
please see the information linked below.