Most smartphones and tablets have something known
as an accelerometer.
This can be used to find out information
about the physical orientation of the device as we use it.
This information is accessed through a vector3 property
called acceleration, which is a part of the input class.
The axis of the accelerometer are setup
to match the axis in Unity.
Therefore Y is the vertical axis,
X is the horizontal axis,
and Z is the depth axis.
This holds true regardless of whether you are
in portrait or landscape mode.
Unity automatically adjusts the accelerometer input
to match the device's orientation.
Here we have a scene in Unity with a cube in in.
The cube has a script called
Accelerometer Input attached.
Inside the accelerometer input script
we can see that in the update method we are
moving the cube based on the Input.acceleration vector3.
We have mapped the accelerometer's X axis
to the cube's X axis.
And we have mapped the negative of the
accelerometer's Z axis to the cube's Z axis.
The values of the accelerometer's axis
range from -1 to 1 and so we can use it
in the same manner as input.getAxis.
When we build and deploy our project
we can see that by tilting our mobile device
we are able to move the cube around the scene.