As well as supporting input from devices like a mouse and keyboard
Unity also support input from touch screens.
Because of the nature of touch input
it is handled slightly differently.
We still use the input class
as we would for other input devices.
However, since the user may be making
multiple touches at once they are stored as an array.
If we want to retrieve a specific touch
it is efficient to use the Get.Touch function
of the input class.
The Get.Touch function reads in a single integer
and returns a touch from the array at that index.
For example, if we want to access
the first touch in the array
we can create a touch variable and set
it equal to Input.GetTouch parsing in a 0.
A touch variable is an instance of the touch struct.
A struct is very similar to a class.
It is a collection of variables and functions
just the same as a class and for this example
they can be thought of as the same.
The touch struct has a number of properties
that we can use in different ways
depending on how we want the touches to effect our game.
The fingerId property is an identifier
that is unique to that specific touch
for its lifetime.
Using this you can track the actions of a specific touch.
Once the touch is no longer in the array
the touch has finished and other touches can have this ID.
The position property is the position of the touch on the screen.
This is a vector2 measured in screen space.
Screen space is measured in pixels
from the bottom left corner.
That means the axis are between 0 in the lower left corner
and the screen's width in pixels on the right
and screen's height in pixels at the top.
The delta position property is a vector2
that is the difference between the touches
position last frame to it's position this frame.
This is very useful for any system
where you need to know the movement direction of a touch.
In addition to the delta position
the touch struct also has a delta time property.
This is the time since there was an update of the touch.
Generally touches are detected in the update loop.
Under these circumstances the delta time
property would be the same as the time.deltaTime.
Each touch has a tapCount property.
This is a measure of how many taps are
made in quick succession.
When a tap is recorded the fingerId is maintained.
However if you have multiple fingers tapping at once
then this will be treated as the same finger
jumping around the screen.
The last property is the touches phase.
This is an enumeration called TouchPhase.
The possible values for the phase are
Began, Cancelled, Ended, Moved and Stationary.
The phase Began will be returned on the
first frame of the touch.
Stationary is when the touch isn't moving.
And Moved is when the touch has changed position on the screen.
Ended is returned on the last frame of the touch.
The touch will have a phase of Cancelled when the
device can't handle the input of the screen.
This might be where there are more touches
than the device supports
or a large surface presses on the screen.
We can also retrieve the entire array
by creating an array of touch objects
and setting it equal to the touches property
of the input class.
Now that we have our touch array
generally it is a good idea to iterate through them.
By doing so we can treat each touch individually
based on it's properties.
To do this we will us a For Loop.
In order to loop the correct number of times
we could use the length property of the touches array.
However it is again more efficient
to use the touchCount property of the input class.
From here we can treat touch individually
However, this might not be the way you want
to treat touches in every circumstance.
For example, there are times where you might want to write code
that requires a specific number of touches
for complex gestures.
For more examples of touch based input
see the assignments linked below.