When you have a model highlighted
in the project panel you can define how
Unity interprets the mesh, animation,
and other properties using the Inspector.
These properties come in 3 parts
Model, Rig and Animations.
In this lesson we'll be looking at the
Animations section.
The first option under Animations
is whether or not to import animations.
This must be check to use any of the animations
stored within the model file.
Bake Animations is used when an animation
has been created in a separate modelling
or animation program using inverse kinematics,
or IK for short.
And it has no yet been converted to forward kinematics
You can also choose what sort of
compression you'd like for your animations.
By default there is no compression
but you can choose Keyframe Reduction,
or Optimal.
If you choose to compress the animations
you need to decide what error you wish to
allow for position, rotation and scale.
The smaller the values, the higher the
precision, the less compression you get.
Below the compression options
there's a list of clips that are available
from the model.
These can be added to or deleted
using the + and - icon.
Next to each of the names are the
start and end frames for the clip.
This is what makes each clip in the take different.
When one of these clips is selected
all of the options are available for that
specific animation clip.
The first option is the name of the clip.
Also, if the file has multiple takes
you will see what take that clip is from.
Next is the timeline of the animation.
Using the handles in the timeline
or the Start and End fields
you can edit on which frame
the clip begins and ends.
Below the start and end controls
is the loop controls.
Loop Time, when checked,
means that when the animation is finished
playing it will start again.
If Loop Pose is checked Unity will
try and match up the start and end pose
so that the looping clip looks smooth.
The Cycle Offset is for adjusting
when the clip starts and ends.
Use this for mirroring animations.
For example, if you want a run clip
to be mirrored then you might set the offset
to 0.5 so that the other foot is on the floor.
The Root Transform Rotation
affects how the rotation of an animation
affects the avatar.
If the root transform rotation is baked
in to the pose then the avatar will not
rotate with any turning in the animation.
Use this option for animations
such as running in a straight line
so that any slight deviation from a straight
line will not affect it.
The root transform rotation can either be
based on body orientation at the start
of the animation or the original source file
of the animation.
If Body Orientation is chosen
then the upper body will point forward.
You can use the offset to fine tune
the direction of the animation.
The next options refer to the root
transform position in the Y axis.
As with root transform rotation if you check
Bake Into Pose the avatar will not
move up or down during the animation.
There are a few options of what the
position can be based on.
Original takes the Y position
from the source fail.
Otherwise it can be based on the avatar's
centre of mass or the position of it's feet.
Again the offset can be used to
fine tune the movement in the Y axis.
Root transform position XZ
works similarly to the Y axis option
except that it affects the horizontal
movement of the avatar.
Baking in to the pose will restrict movement
on the XZ plane.
This can be based on either the original file
or the centre of mass.
When you use the handles on the timeline
to adjust the animation you will see a graph
for each of the properties below it
representing how well it will match
when the clip is looped.
Based on this matching each option
has a traffic light indicating how well
it matches.
Green for a good loop match,
yellow for an okay match
and red for a not good match.
Depending on what sort of animation clip
you are trimming you may or may not
want these to loop nicely.
For example, with a walking animation
you would want the pose to loop nicely
but you probably wouldn't want the transform
position XZ to loop.
If the Mirror box is checked
then the animation will be flipped left to right.
For information on the avatar mask
and animation curves and events options
see the lessons linked below.