In this lesson we will be addressing
some of the more common uses of the animator class.
For complete documentation on the animator class
see the documentation linked below.
In order to affect transitions between the states
of an animator controller we need to set the
animator parameters to appropriate values.
To do this we need to use some of the
functions of the animator class.
Here we have a scene with a model Ethan in it.
Ethan has an animator component
and a script called Ethan Script attached.
The animator component is using a
controller named EthanController.
If we open EthanController
we can see that there are 4 states.
Idle, Walk, Run and Jump.
Additionally there are 2 parameters.
A float named Speed and a
trigger named Jump.
the controller is setup in such a way
that Ethan will transition from Idle to Walk
to Run based on the Speed parameter.
Furthermore, if the Jump parameter is triggered
while Ethan is running Ethan will enter
a Jump state.
All of the animations of the Ethan model
are controlled by these 2 parameters,
which we will now learn to control
with our Ethan script.
Inside the Ethan Script we first need to create
an animator variable named anim
to contain our animator object.
We get a reference to this animator object
in the start method by typing
anim = GetComponent
For further details on the GetComponent function
see the lesson linked below.
Are animator controller is setup
so that the Speed parameter will dictate
which moving animation is being played.
We can use the player's input to
control that behaviour.
The first thing we will need to do is create
a float variable which we will call Move
in the update method.
Then we will set the Move variable
equal to the vertical input axis
by typing Input.GetAxis
and in parenthesis we will parse the string Vertical.
Next we will want to parse the
value of the Move variable to the
Speed attribute of the animator controller.
This is done with the SetFloat function
of the animator class.
We are using SetFloat because Speed
is a float parameter.
If it had been a Boolean parameter
we would use SetBool.
If had been a trigger parameter we would use
SetTrigger and so on.
For each of these functions there are
multiple ways that they can be called.
The most common way is to first parse
in the name of the parameter you are setting
as a string.
Then the next item is the value
you wish to set that parameter to.
In this instance we will call the SetFloat
method of our animator variable by typing
anim.SetFloat
and then in parenthesis the string Speed
and our variable Move.
Back in Unity we can run our scene.
We can see that if we press the W key
or the up arrow our model now moves.
The Speed parameter and the movement
animation played is now controlled by the player.
Parsing in a string name for the
parameter we wish to set can be inefficient
because it means that the animator needs to
evaluate the string every time it is called.
A faster way of setting parameter values
is by using hashIDs.
Each string that an animator can use is
given a hashID.
This is an integer value that is unique
for every different string.
We can store this value and then set
parameters using this ID instead.
To do this, first we will need
to store the value.
Let's create an integer variable named jumpHash
to store the hashID in.
We get the value for our hash variable by
calling the static method of the animator class
string to hash.
Since this method is static we access it
by typing Animator.StringToHash.
In the parenthesis we parse in the string
we wish to know the hashID value of.
In order to make our model jump
we will need to set the Jump trigger parameter
in the animator controller.
In our case we want to make the model jump
whenever we press the space bar.
So we will start by typing
if Input.GetKeyDown and then in the parenthesis
we will use KeyCode.Space.
Inside our if statement we will set
the Jump trigger parameter using the
anim.SetTrigger method.
Inside the parenthesis we will
parse our jumpHash variable.
Remember that this variable contains
the hasID of our Jump parameter.
Note that since Jump is a trigger
we do not need to also parse in a value.
Back in Unity we can run our scene.
Notice that while we are running we can also
press the spacebar to jump.
We have now utilised both our
float parameter Speed and our
trigger parameter Jump to make our model
more dynamic.
Occasionally, when writing the logic
behind animation we may want to
find out what state the controller is in.
Let's say for example we want to be able to
set the Jump trigger only when the model
is in the Run state.
The animator has some functions that we can call
to find out what state the controller
is currently in.
We can do this by creating an
animator state info variable
which we will call StateInfo.
The animator state info class
stores the name, name hash,
and various other pieces of information
about a state.
We will set our state info variable equal
to the anim.GetCurrentAnimatorStateInfo function.
Inside the parenthesis we will parse the index
of the layer we want to know more about.
Since we are dealing with the base layer
we will parse in a 0.
Again we could compare the current
animation states name with a string
but since it is more efficient to compare
hashIDs let's do that instead.
We will start by creating an integer named
runStateHash and setting it equal to our
Animator.StringToHash function.
We will parse in to the parenthesis
the string Base Layer.Run
We have to include the base layer. part
because we can have states of the same name
on different layers.
Now we can modify our if statement
to also only allow our model to jump
if stateInfo.nameHash
equals our runStateHash variable.