The state machines of animator controllers
can be split up in to layers.
These are generally used to handle
animating different body parts.
For example you might use the base layer
to handle the overall movement of a character
while also allowing the character to wave.
You could handle the separate waving animation
on another layer so that the character
could move and wave simultaneously.
By default an animator controller will
have one layer called Base Layer.
The only adjustable properties for this layer
are it's name and whether or not it does
an IK Pass.
IK is short for Inverse Kinematics.
When a layer does an IK pass
it means that the onAnimatorIK function
will be called for that layer with the
appropriate layer index.
The base layer has a layer index of 0.
Any additional layers have indices
starting at 1 and counting upwards.
For more information on IK and the
onAnimatorIK function
please see the documentation linked below.
Subsequent layers have additional options
to do with how they react to previous layers.
We can create a new layer by clicking the
+ icon next to the word Layers.
All layers have a name and that is set with
the Name property.
The Weight represents how much the layer
effects the final animation.
A weight of 0 means the layer will not
effect animation at all.
Inversely a weight of 1
will completely change the animation.
Layers of higher weights have priority
over lower ones.
The slider sets the default value of the weight
but it can still be set in code at runtime
using the setLayerWeight function
of the animator class.
The Mask property of a layer defines which,
if any, avatar mask the layer will use
to isolate body parts for animation.
For more information about avatar masks
see the lesson linked below.
The blending of a layer can either be
Override or Additive.
If the blending mode is override
then the resultant animation will override
the animation of the lower layer
as defined by the weight.
Additive blending will result in the
animations on the additive layer being added to
or combined with the animations
of lower layers.
An example of this might be using a layer
to represent a character breathing heavily
as they become tired.
In this example the heavy breathing
animation would be added to an animation
defined on the lower layers.
The weight could be used to measure how
tired the character was.
As the weight of the layer increased
the heavy breathing animation would be
more apparent.
The last option for a layer is Sync.
Where you check the Sync box
you are given an option of which layer
you wish to sync with.
This will create an identical state machine
to the one on the selected layer
but with no motions.
This means that the animator will always
be in the same state in both layers.
This can be used for things such as
a wounded behaviour.
If you have a set of animations for when
the character is healthy and a set for
when the character is wounded these can be
blended between as the character looses health.
The Timing checkbox allows the animator
to adjust how long each animation
in synced layers takes determined by the weight.