Sometimes when animating an avatar
we want to isolate areas of the body
that are actually effected by the animation.
For example we might have a wave animation
but we want to be able to wave while running,
walking, jumping, etcetera.
In order to achieve this effect
we can use an avatar mask.
In this way we can restrict the effect
of this animation to be purely based
on the arm of the avatar.
Avatar masks can be created and used
in 2 distinct ways, but the overall effect
of the mask is the same.
Avatar masks can first be created on a
per-animation basis.
For this method go to the Animations tab
of the Model Importer by selecting a model
in the Project Panel and clicking on the
Animations tab.
When you select an animations clip
there are a number of properties that appear
below the clip name.
One of these is a drop-down called Mask.
Here you can create a mask that is unique
to the specific animation you are editing.
The other method for creating an avatar mask
is to create it as an asset in your Project Panel
by right-clicking and selecting Create - Avatar Mask.
Once it is created it can then be applied
to the layers of an animator controller
using the Animator window.
Creating and applying a mask this way will
effect all animations on an animator layer.
For more information on animator layers
see the lesson linked below.
An avatar mask has 2 parts,
Humanoid and Transform.
The Humanoid drop-down has a diagram
of a humanoid facing you from the screen.
This means that the diagram's left hand
is on the right side.
By clicking on each section you can toggle
it's colour between red and green.
You can also click outside the diagram
to toggle between all red and all green.
The colour indicates which parts of a humanoid
avatar will be animated when using this mask.
Green indicates that the body part will be used
and red indicates that it will not be used.
For our wave animation we have all but the
right arm deselected.
This means that only the right arm
will be effected by the animation.
The second part is the Transform Mask.
Transform masks are used for generically
rigged models and humanoid rigged models
with extra bones.
For example, if you had a 4 legged robot
or a humanoid with wings.
Here you need to select the avatar
to base the mask on.
This is done using the circle select button.
When an avatar has been selected
and imported a full list of all of the transforms
for that avatar appear.
From this you can select or deselect
which transforms should be effected
by the animation.
If a transform is checked then it will be
part of the mask and will move when animated.
For example, imagine we have a
humanoid avatar with a tail.
In the base layer of the animator state machine
the character has it's locomotion managed.
On subsequent layers other animations
such as attacking are handled.
It might be a good idea for these subsequent
layers to have a transform mask where
the tail bones are unchecked.
This means that the tail is not effected
by animations on those layers
and will still be moved by animations playing
on the base layer.