In this assignment we'll create the laser grids
that also trigger the alarm if the player
crosses them.
First we can see that in the last assignment
We created some scripts using the
Add Component button,
which are left in the root of our assets.
So let's tidy these up by dropping them
in to the Scripts folder.
Now let's start making the laser grids.
We're going to add a model to the scene,
add some components, write some scripts
and then turn this in to a prefab so that
we can make several laser gates.
In the Models folder, locate
FX - Laser Fence - Lasers.
Drag and drop this in to the scene
somewhere like this.
Press F to focus on it.
We'll start by changing the rotation by
ninety degrees in the Y axis.
This will rotate it to face the two gate
points on either side of the corridor.
Then we'll change the scale to (1, 1, 3.62).
We'll set the position to (-8, 1.21, 5.62)
This should place your first laser gat in to
the exact position that we have on scene.
To make it easier to keep track of these
lasers we're going to add a number
as a post-fix to the name.
So rename this '_001' at the end
The laser grid needs to be able to detect
when the player passes through it
and so it needs a trigger collider.
For efficiency we're going to use a box collider.
The collider will automatically resize to
the laser grid when we add it.
We just need to make sure that the
Is Trigger box is checked.
So click Add Component
choose Physics - Box Collider
and then check Is Trigger.
You'll be able to see a faint green outline
that shows the bounding area
of the box collider.
We're also going to add an audio source
component so that the player can hear
a faint laser hum when he's near them.
Click Add Component and choose
Audio - Audio Source.
In the Audio folder drag and drop
the Laser Hum clip on to the audio clip
in the Audio Source component.
You should see that this is a 3D sound.
which means the proximity of the listener
will define how loud it is to the player.
We want to make sure that the player can
hear the hum from a reasonable distance
so underneath 3d Sound Settings
set the minimum distance to 1.8.
You'll see that the spherical representation
of this expands in the Scene View.
We also want to make sure that this clip
loops throughout the game so check the
Loop checkbox on the audio source component.
We also want the lasers to have a slight
red glow. To do this we're going
to have a point light attached to them.
Collapse your components to make room
and click Add Component - Rendering - Light.
Now we'll change the colour to red
to match the laser grid.
Click the Colour Picker and copy
these colour settings
(255, 40, 0).
We need to tweak the settings slightly
for the lights.
Change the range to 5
and the intensity to 0.6.
We also want to make sure that when we
re-bake the light map these lights
are not included, because otherwise
when the laser grids are switched off
the light from them would remain
on the surface of the environment.
To correct this make sure that these are
realtime only lights.
Set Light Mapping to Realtime Only.
Now we need two scripts for the laser grid.
The first script will make the lasers
blink on and off, we will call it
Laser Blinking.
Click the Add Component button and choose
New Script and name it LaserBlinking
Double click the icon to launch for editing.
Begin by clearing the script as usual.
We only need a few class variables for
this script, two public floats for the
amount of time the lasers are on and off,
and a float for a timer to know when to
switch between on and off.
To make the laser blink we're going to
disable and enable the laser's
renderer component and it's light component.
Thus we need to check if the renderer is enabled
and the timer is greater than or equal
to the amount of time that the laser is
supposed to be on.
We will do this inside the update function.
So add one now.
First we'll increment the timer.
Then we'll check if the renderer is enabled
and that the timer is more than or
equal to onTime.
If these conditions are satisfied then
we need to switch whether the beam is
on or not and reset the timer.
We will do this in a short separate function.
First we will reset the timer
and then we simply set the enabled status
of the renderer and the lights
to the opposite of themselves.
With that short function finished we can
now put a call to it inside our update function
inside the brackets of the If statement.
To finish the script we also need the
opposite check for if the renderer is
already disabled.
The script is now complete, so save it
and return to the editor.
Now we need another script to
manage player detection.
We'll call this script Laser PlayerDetection.
Click Add Component and choose New Script,
naming it LaserPlayerDetection.
Double click the icon to open it for editing.
Clear the script as usual.
This script doesn't need to be referenced elsewhere,
nor does it have anything that needs
tweaking publicly. As such we don't need
any public class variables.
It does however need a couple of private
variables to store references.
The first is to the Player game object.
The other is a reference to the last
LastPlayerSighting script.
We will use the Awake function to setup
these references using FindGameObjectWithTag
as we have done before.
The only other function we need in this script
is OnTriggerStay.
We need to know if the renderer is enabled first
since the lasers should only be detecting
when they are on.
Given that the lasers are on we need
to check if the colliding game object is
indeed the player.
If it is the player then we need to update
the position of the last sighting of the player
to the colliding game object's current position.
And that's this script finished, and the
end of our work on the laser grid.
So save your script and return to the Editor.
Then drag the FXLaserFence
on to the Prefabs folder to save it
as a prefab.
We can now duplicate the lasers and place
at other locations around the level.
Place the first duplicate just past the door
in the same corridor.
We also want to change it's name to show
that it's a different laser grid.
Change the number to '002'.
So first we will duplicate,
then we'll change the name to 2
and we'll use the Transform tool to move
this up the corridor.
To get the exact position set the location to
(-8, 1.21, 9.23).
Now let's duplicate again. Rename the new
duplicate '003' then move this grid to the
doorway of the security room
facing the battle bus. We can do this
by positioning it at
(-17.93, 1.21, 24.08).
Select it in the hierarchy and press F
with your cursor over the Scene view
to focus on it.
It should look like this.
Now let's duplicate again
and rename '004'.
Position this at (-23.92, 1.21, 26.1).
Then remove the rotation in the Y axis
so that it reads 0.
Focus again in the Scene view.
Now reselect laser grid number 3
as it has the correct rotation
for the other two laser grids.
Duplicate it and rename it '005'.
Now reposition this at (-8.95, 1.21, 25.99).
Finally duplicate to make number 6.
Rename it.
And set the position to (-8.95, 1.21, 29.96).
Then refocus on these in the Scene view.
You will notice that they don't reach
the edges of the corridor, so select
5 and 6 and set the scale
to (1, 1, 5.6).
The last thing we need to do with these two
larger laser grids is to set the
On and Off times of the LaserBlinking scripts.
With them both still selected set
their On times to 1.5.
Now select laser fence number 5
and set it's Off time to 1.5.
Now select number 6
and set the Off time to 1.55.
This means that they will flash asynchronously.
With that done what we need is a way to
turn off some of the lasers.
To do this we have switches.
We'll start by dragging the model in to the scene.
In the Models folder you will find a prop
called prop_switchUnit.
It should look like this.
Move your Scene view so that you can see
the second room at the bottom of the map.
You will see that there's a poster on the wall
with the word 'terminal' written on it.
This is where we want to place the first switch.
Drag and drop the switch unit
somewhere like this. For the exact position
we'll place it at (-11.5, 0, 11.3).
Then we'll rotate it by 180 in the Y axis.
When all of the switches are placed in to the scene
we'll want to re-bake the light map
for higher quality.
So that these are included in the bake
make sure to switch the game object to
Static by checking the box at the top
of the inspector. Choose Yes to changing
the child objects of this.
We will need a couple of colliders.
First we will use a box collider so that
the player cannot run through the switch.
Click Add Component - Physics - Box Collider.
The box collider will naturally try and fit
the entire model, which in this case
includes the wiring on the floor.
We don't need it to do that so we will
adjust the collider slightly.
Set the centre of the collider to (0.3, 0.8, -0.15).
Set the size of the collider to (1.3, 1.6, 0.81).
Now we need a sphere trigger collider.
This will be how we can tell the player is
close enough to use the switch.
Unity asks us if we mean to have
two colliders on one game object
and we do so we will choose to add
rather than replace.
Go to Add Component - Physics - Sphere Collider
and choose Add.
We will set the centre to (0, 1, 1).
We will set the radius to 1.5
and we'll check the Is Trigger checkbox.
We want the switch to make a noise when
the laser has been deactivated.
As such we will add an audio source component
to the switch.
Click Add Component - Audio - Audio Source.
We will uncheck Play On Awake so that the
sound does not happen when the game begins.
And from the Audio folder in the Project Panel
we will drag and drop the clip switch_deactivation
on to the audio clip property.
Now we need a script to deactivate the laser.
We will name this script LaserSwitchDeactivation.
Double click the icon to launch for editing.
Prepare the script for writing.
The first thing we're going to need in this script
is a reference to the Laser game object
we're going to turn off. We need this to be
public so that we can drag on the appropriate
laser once we're finished.
We also need a public material so that
we can change what the screen looks like
when the laser has been unlocked.
The only other class variable we will need
for this script is a reference for the player
game object, which can be private.
Next we need to setup the reference to the player
as we have done in the awake function before.
Next we need to check if the player is within
the trigger zone, so we will use the
OnTriggerStay function as we did with
the cameras.
Given that the player is within the trigger zone
the next thing to check is whether the switch
button is being pressed.
At this point we want to deactivate the laser.
We will make a function in order to do this.
We will call it LaserDeactivation.
The first thing to do in this function is to
disable the Laser game object. We do this
using the SetActive function.
Next we need a reference to the renderer
component of the switch's screen.
The screen is a child game object of
of the switch so we can reference that
using transform.Find
Having found the child we can
access the renderer component.
With that reference we can set the material
to the unlocked material which we will
assign in the Inspector later.
We can also play the deactivating sound
from the audio source.
Now we can add a call to this function
in our OnTriggerStay function.
With the script complete we can save and
return to the editor.
Now we need to assign our public references.
Let's start by dropping the unlocked material
on to the UnlockedMat public variable.
In the Materials folder in the Project panel
you will find something called
prop_switchUnit_screenUnlocked
Drag and drop this on to the UnlockedMat variable.
We are now ready to make a prefab of our laser switch.
We haven't yet applied the laser which we
will be deactivating with our switch
but since that will be different with each instance
we don't want to store it in the prefabs
so we will make it now.
Drag and drop prop_switchUnit on to
the Prefabs folder in the Project panel.
We're going to have four switches around the scene.
So let's name them using the same numbering
convention we used for the laser grids.
Add '001' to the name of the first switch.
Now we can duplicate the switch and place
it around the level.
The first duplicate will be on the far wall
of the lower right room. So duplicate,
rename '002',
place this at (-1.6, 0, 11.3).
It should look like this.
Now duplicate once more.
Rename it '003'
and place this one at (-17.7, 0, 33.3).
This should be on the far wall of the security room.
It should look like this.
The last one will go in the small alcove
on the upper left of the level.
So duplicate, rename '004'
and place it at position (-30, 0, 33.3).
It should look like this.
Now we are ready to assign laser to the
switches so that they switch off the
correct laser grids.
The first switch will deactivate laser number 1.
So select the first switch
and in the LaserSwitchDeactivation script
drag and drop laser fence 01
Next we can apply laser2 to switch2
laser3 to switch3 and laser4 to switch4 as shown.
Now all of our laser grids are setup
with appropriate switches and will function
correctly. You can check the sounds
on these by enabling the Audio Preview button
at the top of the Scene view.
Now we're nearly ready to do a high quality bake
of our light map, but before we do that
we're going to tidy up our scripts folder.
Select the Assets folder in the Project panel
and drag in the three scripts we've made
in this assignment.
Now you can see our Scripts folder is
beginning to get bloated and has a variety
of different scripts involved.
In the Scripts folder we'll make folders to
store these to keep them neatly.
First of all create a folder called AlarmSystems.
In to this folder we will place AlarmLight,
CCTVPlayerDetection, LaserBlinking,
LaserPlayerDetection and LaserSwitchDeactivation.
Leaving the last three scripts in the folder.
Now we will make another folder called GameController.
In to this we will place the LastPlayerSighting script.
Now we will make a folder for our screen fader.
And finally we will make a folder for our unapplied scripts.
So remember that Tags is simply a library
of different constants that we can reference
in other scripts, it's not applied to a game object.
This is why we place it in a folder called Unapplied.
Now with our scripts tidied up we will
do a high quality bake of our light map.
Select the light mapping tab, or if you've
close it go to Window - Light Mapping.
Go to the Bake tab and set Quality from Low to High.
Also set the Padding to a value of 3.
Now we're ready to do our bake so simply click
Bake Scene at the bottom.
Becasue this is high quality this will take
a longer time than our low bake took earlier.
This high quality bake will give you a much
better looking environment and a
much more accurate representation
of the lighting involved.
So when it's done have a look around the environment
and check out the changes that we've made.
So take this opportunity to have a break from the computer.
This is also the end of the first chapter.
In the next chapter we will focus on
creating the player.
Once the bake is complete remember to
save your scene and save your project from the File menu.