The Sprite Type.
When importing image assets as sprites
the texture type should be set to Sprite.
If the project has been set as a 2D project
the texture importer will use the
Sprite Type by default on any new image
assets being imported.
For more information on setting up a project
as 2D please see the information linked below.
If any image asset has been imported
and the type has not been set to sprite
the sprite type can be set manually in the importer.
To select the sprite type in the importer
use the Texture Type pull-down and select Sprite.
Sprite Mode has 2 options
Single and Multiple.
Single should be chosen when the entire image asset
is 1 element and will be used as a single sprite.
Multiple should be chosen when the image
asset contains multiple elements in the same file,
such as an atlas of sprite elements
or an animated sprite sheet.
There is an optional Packing Tag.
This is the name of the optional sprite
atlas in to which this texture could be packed.
For more information on texture packing and the texture packer
please see the information linked below.
Pixels To Units defines the scale
of the imported sprite.
Pixels To Units defines the number of
pixels from the sprite that will correspond
to 1 unit in world space.
At the default scale of 100 pixels per unit
a 256 by 64 pixel image
will be applied to a game object that is
2.56 by 0.64 Unity units.
With Sprite Mode Single selected
Pivot sets the pivot point of the sprite.
The default is centre.
The drop-down menu allows this to be changed
to any of the corners or sides.
Custom reveals X and Y value fields
to set a custom pivot.
Custom pivots use values between 0 and 1.
Starting from the lower left, 0 is the start or minimum value,
and 1 is the end or maximum value on each axis.
(0.5, 0.5) is directly in the middle of the rectangle.
With Sprite Mode Multiple selected
the option to set the pivot point is
unavailable in the importer.
The pivot point is set per sprite in the sprite editor.
The sprite editor button will open this
image asset in the sprite editor.
For more information on the sprite editor
please see the information linked below.
The Filter Mode and Per Platform Overrides
are unchanged by the texture type Sprite.
For more information on Filter Mode, or the Per Platform Overrides
please see the lessons on textures linked below.
It is worth noting that an atlas, or sprite sheet,
maybe larger than the default max
size of 1024 for an image texture.
If the image to be imported is larger
than the max size value
the asset will be resized to this
value during the import process.
To prevent the resizing of large images on import
the max size value may need to be adjusted.
When an image asset is successfully imported as a sprite
the asset will update in the project window
and a new sprite, or group of sprites,
can be seen as a child, or children,
of the original image asset.
For more information on these sprite children
please see the information on the Sprite Editor linked below.