Our game is taking shape.
The game play is pretty much finished.
Now it's time to polish our game
and get it ready to build.
Next we're going to be adding audio,
sound effects and music.
There are 3 main audio components in Unity.
There are audio clips, audio sources
and the audio listener.
We will concentrate on audio clips
and audio sources.
For more details on these 3 audio components
please see the information linked below.
Audio clips hold our audio data
or sound files.
Audio sources play our audio clips in the scene.
Let's find our audio clips.
In Assets we have an Audio folder.
Here we can see a selection of sound
effects and a music track.
If we select any 1 of the audio clips
we will see that clip's import settings
in the Inspector.
The Preview window will display additional
information about that clip.
If the Preview window has been closed
we can drag the Preview window's header
bar up to reopen it.
In the Preview window we can see
the audio clip's waveform,
we can play,
or loop the audio clip's audio file,
and we get additional information about
that audio clip printed at the bottom.
We won't cover the details of the audio importer.
For more information on the audio importer
please see the links below.
We do want to note one important import
setting here however, and that is 3D Sound.
For our game we want to make sure
all of our audio clips have 3D sound deselected.
This should already be set properly on the
assets provided with this project.
When an audio clip is imported as a 3D sound
Unity will compare the location
of the audio source playing the audio clip
and compare it with the scene's
1 active audio listener
and use the relative positions
to affect the clip's volume and panning.
We don't want any of this working in our
simple arcade-style game.
So we want to make sure 3D Sound
has been deselected.
The audio files that we have in this project
are 3 styles of explosions,
Asteroid, Enemy and Player.
A backgound music track.
And 2 weapons effects.
In this portion of the Space Shooter project
we will be ignoring the Enemy sounds,
they are for later optional assignments.
We need to associate an audio clip with
our explosion prefabs and our player ship.
The explosions need to play their audio clip
when they are first instantiated in to the scene.
The player ship on the other hand needs
to play it's audio clip when the player
fires their weapons.
We associate an audio clip with a
game object by using an audio source component.
The audio source plays an audio clip.
We can add an audio source component
to our game objects and then reference an audio
clip for that source to play.
But there is an easier way to do this.
If we drag an audio clip on to
a game object Unity will create
a new audio source on the game object
and automatically reference the dragged audio clip.
Let's see this in action.
We can drag assets easily from our
Project view on to game objects in our Hierarchy.
To drag an asset like our audio clip
on to a prefab asset
which both are in our project
we can either open 2 Project view windows
or we can change our existing Project view
from using the 2 column layout
to using a single column layout.
This will allow us to drag objects
from one part of our Project view to another
without losing focus on our target asset.
Our first target asset will be the
asteroid explosion prefab.
Our asteroid hazards have a reference
to this prefab.
When we destroy the asteroid
the asteroid will spawn this prefab.
At that point we want it to go bang.
With the explosion_steroid prefab selected
drag the explosion_asteroid audio clip
on to the game object on the Inspector and drop it.
We can see that Unity has added an
audio source to the prefab asset
and that audio source has a reference
to the audio clip that we dragged and dropped on it.
The bulk of the component is dedicated
to 3D Sound settings,
which we can safely ignore.
The only important setting that we need to
worry about for our game here
is Play On Awake.
Play On Awake should be on by default.
For our explosions to work properly in our game
we need to make sure that it is set on.
This way the audio will play automatically
when we spawn our explosion.
We can also drag an audio clip on to a
prefab asset without having it
visable in the Inspector.
Select the explosion_player audio clip
and drag it on to the explosion_player prefab asset.
As we are using the defaults as they are
with Play On Awake automatically set
we don't need to make any changes to this at all.
Now the player's weapon sound is almost as simple.
Select the weapon_player audio clip
and drag it in to the Scene view
and drop it on to the player game object.
Again we can see that Unity has added
an audio source to the player game object
and the audio clip reference is set to
weapon_player.
The player however has just a few more
items to consider.
First we definately do not want Play On Awake set.
Otherwise we would get our weapon sound playing
on the very first frame of the game.
Deselect Play On Awake.
Now if we won't be playing this sound automatically
how will we play it?
We must do this from our PlayerController script.
So select the player controller script
and open it for editing.
Looking at our PlayerController script
where do we want to write our code?
In our Update function where we fire our shot.
As all of the logic will be
executed within the same frame
practically it doesn't make a difference
where in the block we write our new line
as long as it is inside the if statement.
controlling when we fire our weapons.
We will add this line of code to the
end of this block.
Write audio.Play with a capital P
followed by parenthesis.
Audio is the shorthand reference
that this script will use to talk
to the audio source attached to it.
And Play is a function on the audio source
that will play the current clip
and as a function needs to be called
with the parenthesis.
It is worth noting that we can change the
clips to be played and other
additional functionality all in code
but we won't be covering that here.
For more information on the audio source
or any of the other audio components
please see the details linked below.
Now when we fire our weapon we instantiate
our shot clone and play our weapon sound.
Save this script, return to Unity,
save the scene and enter Play mode.
And we have sound effects.
Exit Play mode.
Along with our sound effects we also have a
background music track.
we can find this in our audio folder
as music_background.
Let's put this background music
on our game controller.
This audio track will be self sufficient
and won't need to interact with a
game controller at all.
It could go on it's own game object.
But the game controller's game object
is a tidy place to keep a component
that is related to the game in general.
Drag music_background in to our
Scene view and drop it on Game Controller.
This will add a new audio source
to Game Controller with music_background
as the referenced clip.
We want this music to start right away
and play during the entire game.
For this we want to make sure that
Play On Awake is selected
so it will begin playing on the first frame
and select Loop as well.
So the audio runs continuously.x
The audio clip is designed as a seamless loop
so there will be no audible gap when the
music continuously restarts.
Save the scene and enter Play mode.
Now we have sound effects and music.
Exit Play mode.
The last step we need to take is
balancing the audio.
All of the clips are currently being played back
at full volume, and they don't mix well.
Let's bring some of these effects down in volume.
Select the player game object and
bring up the audio source component.
Change the Volume property to 0.5.
This will reduce the strength of the
player's weapon sound.
Next select the Game Controller game object
and again on the audio component
reduce the volume property to 0.5.
Save the scene and enter Play mode.
Now the explosions are still bright and snappy
but the player's weapons and the background
music are not so overwhelming.
Excellent.
In the next assignment we will see how to
display a score.