We have developed a simple but playable game.
Now we need to find a way to break out
of our infinite loop spawning our waves
of hazards, end the game when the player is destroyed
and give our players the chance to
restart a new game if they want to.
As we prepare to end the game
we need to create 2 new labels.
1 to display Game Over
and the other to indicate when it's
okay to restart the game.
In an effort to keep our Hierarchy organised
let's create an empty parent game object
to hold our current Score Text
and the 2 new labels we are about to create.
Rename the game object DisplayText
and reset the game object's transform.
Add Score Text to DisplayText
making Score Text a child of DisplayText.
Next create a new GUI text game object.
Rename it Restart Text
and change the text property to
Restart Text.
Change the transform position to
(1, 1) on the X and Y.
This should place the restart text
up in to the upper right corner.
But we can't see it.
By adjusting the transform's position
on the X axis we can drag Restart Text
back in to the game screen.
But again using the transform component
for adjusting this fine detail on the GUI
text label is not ideal.
Let's leave the transform position X at 1.
There are 2 adjustments that we can make
in the GUI text component to better display
our Restart Text label.
The first is our anchor and alignment.
Currently these are set at default
or upper left and left.
This is why we cannot see our label.
The label is starting at the upper right
of our screen and is drawn to the right
from the left.
So the label draws off the screen.
Change the anchor and alignment properties
to upper right
and right.
We can see our Restart Text label
now draws to the left from the right
starting in the upper right corner.
The second adjustment is to the pixel offset.
Let's match the pixel offset
on Restart Text to that of Score Text.
We can have the same 10 pixel pad
by setting the pixel offset to
-10 and -10.
Add Restart Text to DisplayText
to keep our Hierarchy neat and tidy.
Create another GUI text object.
And rename this one Game Over Text.
Change the text property to Game Over Text.
Change the anchor and alignment to
middle centre
and centre.
And change the transform's position Y
to 0.6
so it is in the middle of our screen but up a bit.
Now add Game Over Text
to our Display Text parent game object.
This sets up the basic GUI text objects
that we will need to end our game.
Next we need to update our code
on our GameController script.
Open our GameController script for editing.
We need to create references to our new
GUI text components.
Write public GUIText restartText
and public GUIText gameOverText.
We will feed information to these labels
as the game progresses.
To control what we sent to these 2 labels
and when we send it we will need
2 related control flags,
or 2 boolean variables.
Let's write private bool for boolean gameOver
and private bool restart.
These true-false boolean flags will help
us track when the game is over and
when it is okay to restart the game.
We need to set the value for these at the
start of the game.
So in Start write
gameOver = false and restart = false.
We also need to set the starting text
on our new labels so let's write
restartText.text = ""
The same for gameOverText.text.
Set this to 2 empty quotes as well.
This means at the start of the game
these 2 GUI text labels
will display nothing.
These labels are effectively turned off.
We need to change the state of our game
and the content of these labels when
our game is over.
Much like adding our score we need
to expose a function here
on our game controller for another object
to call when the game is over.
Let's create a new public function we can
call from outside this script.
Write public void GameOver.
Our function will need no parameters.
It simply gets called to end the game.
Our GameOver function is very simple.
First we set our gameOverText.text to
Game Over!
And then we set our GameOver flag to true.
Now we will use our Game Over flag
to break out of the infinite loop
that spawns our hazards.
The spawn loop is a while loop.
The while loop will continue cycling
through the code it holds until the
statement in the parenthesis is false.
We have set this literally to true
so without help this loop will never end.
At the end of the loop, after we have waited
for our wave to clear, but before we loop back
to the top of our block of code
add if gameOver.
And when written this way we are saying the
same thing as if gameOver is
the same as true
restartText.text equals
Press R for restart.
And again, within a string of text
enclosed by double quotes
note that the R is enclosed by single quotes.
This sets our restart label.
Next set our restart boolean flag to true.
And lastly write break.
This will break us out of our while loop.
And as there is no more code to execute
in spawnWaves after the break
it will end the spawnWaves coroutine.
In our Restart Text label
we have informed our player that they
can restart the game by pressing
the R key.
We will now write the code that allows
the player to do this.
To easily capture a key press
let's poll for it in update.
Write void update
and in the update function write
if restart
so if restart is true we look for our
key press with if Input.GetKeyDown KeyCode.R
Now if restart is true and we get
the key press on the R key
we reload this scene by using
Application.LoadLevel.
Application.LoadLevel loads the level
or scene file specified in the parenthesis.
Instead of writing a string name
or using an index number for that scene
we will simply use the currently loaded level
by using Application.LoadedLevel
That's it for this script.
Save this script and return to Unity.
We need to set up our new references
that we have written on GameController.
With GameController selected
drag the RestartText game object
on to the Restart Text slot
on the GameController component.
Next drag the GameOver text
game object on to the Game Over text
slot on the GameController component.
We are now done with our game controller.
To end the game we need to call Game Over
on Game Controller when the player
is destroyed.
We could try to detect this on the
player game object,
but we have already written this code somewhere else.
Our AsteroidHazards already detect
collisions with our player.
and that collision destroys the player game object.
Open the DestroyByContact script for editing.
In our DestroyByContact code
we detect if other.tag is the same as Player.
Then before we destroy the player game object
we instantiate the player explosion.
After the line where we spawn the player
explosion write gameController,
which is the variable holding the reference
to our game controller instance,
and with the dot call the GameOver function
on GameController.
Now when we destroy the player game object
our game controller is told that the
game is over.
Save this script and return to Unity.
Save the scene and enter Play mode.
When the player is destroyed we see the
Game Over label.
When the current wave clears the screen
we can restart by pressing the R key.
And we're playing again.
Note that the game doesn't instantly restart.
Nor can we restart the level for a few moments
while we wait for the screen to clear.
This gives the player a clear sense that
the game is over before restarting the level.
Make sure that we have exited Play mode.
The last step in this assignment is to add
a little more style to our GUI text labels.
We will be using multi-object editing.
Select both Restart Text and Score Text.
These are the labels in the upper corners
and change their font size to 20.
Next select the Game Over text
and set it's font size to 25.
This will make these labels easier to read.
Save the scene and enter Play mode.
Fantastic.
Our game is complete.
In the last assignment we will build the
game as a web player and deploy it
to the web to play.