We have a player ship, weapons
and hazard objects.
We need to bring them together in to a
simple but playable game.
To do this we need to create a
game controller to run our game,
to spawn our hazards,
keep track of and display our score
and when our player is destroyed end our game.
First create a new game object
to hold our game controller logic.
Rename this game object Game Controller.
And then reset the transform.
For this game object this step isn't
absolutely necessary as this game object
will not have a physical presence in our game.
It won't have a collider and it won't be rendered.
That being said it is always best
to keep everything in our project neat and tidy
and there is no good reason not to put
the game controller cleanly at origin.
Using the Tag drop-down menu in the header
of the Game Controller game object select the
pre-made tag GameController.
With our game object setup
let's write our logic.
With the Game Controller selected
use the Add Component button
to create a new script
named GameController.
Accept the changes to add this new script
to GameController.
Select Assets and file the GameController script
in the Scripts folder.
Open the Scripts folder
and open the GameController script for editing.
Our game controller will perform
several different tasks.
The primary task however will be
spawning the hazards in our game.
So the first thing we will need in this script
is a public GameObject reference to our hazard.
Next we need to do something
with these hazards.
We need to spawn them, preferably in waves
for our player to fight through.
Let's write a new function to spawn
our waves of hazards.
Write void SpawnWaves.
Now we need to call this function.
There are some functions that are called
automatically by Unity
but most of the functions that we write
we will need to call ourselves
or they won't be executed.
We want our SpawnWaves function to
work for most of the duration of our game.
So let's call SpawnWaves from start.
So let's write void Start.
Unity will call Start on the very first frame
that this game object is enabled
and then Start will call SpawnWaves.
What do we want SpawnWaves to do?
We want SpawnWaves to instantiate our hazards.
We want to instantiate our hazards
at a spawnPosition
with a spawnRotation applied.
We have 3 parameters for instantiate
and we need a value for each of them.
Let's look at each of these parameters
1 parameter at a time.
Our object Hazard has already been defined
as a public variable.
Our spawnPosition is a vector3 value
so let's create a vector3 variable called
spawnPosition, which we will set to
a new vector3.
Our spawnRotation is a quaternion value.
So let's create a quaternion variable
called spawnRotation
which we will set to a new quaternion.
Both of these will change before we're done.
Let's look at how we can assign
working values to these.
Hazard is a public variable.
We can set this directly in the Inspector.
Save this script and return to Unity.
We can see the hazard property
on the GameController component.
In the Prefabs folder we can find our
Asteroid prefab.
Drag the Asteroid prefab on to the
Game Controller component and drop it
on to the Hazard slot to create the reference.
We want to be able to set our spawn position
in the Editor as well.
Return to our GameController script.
For our spawnPosition
let's define a public vector3
variable called spawnValues.
Why can't we just use spawnPosition here?
We will see why in just a moment.
Patience.
Save this script and let's set
spawnValue in Unity.
To help visualise this let's drag and asteroid
prefab in to the scene temporarily.
So on what position along the Y axis
do we want to spawn our hazards?
On the X/Z plane or the game plane?
So 0 on the Y axis.
What about the position on the X/Z plane?
This could be better seen
through the Game View camera.
What position on the Z axis?
Up, out of the game area.
That looks like about 16.
So let's set the spawnValue Z to 16.
Now what about the X axis
Well we can't really use a single value here.
If we did we will define a
single point for our spawnPosition,
and for that we could have used a simple
game object's transform, like we did for
the shotSpawn on the player ship.
What we really want here is a random
point in the X axis.
One that is a new random value for
each new hazard we spawn.
This is why we couldn't use spawnPosition directly.
Let's return to our script
We will use our spawnValues to set
a random spawnPosition.
Our spawnPosition is made up of
X, Y and Z values.
Working from back to front
our spawnPosition Z will be our
spawnValues Z, or outside the
top of the game area.
Our spawnPosition Y will be
our spawnValue Y
or 0 on the game plane.
Our spawnPosition X is the one
that's more tricky.
We can't use a single value here.
We will use our spawnValue X
to control a random value.
Let's search the documentation for random again
so we can look at the Random class.
In this case we want to look at
Random.Range.
We give Random.Range a min and a max value
and randomRange will return
a random value between those 2 values.
This means we can feed Random.Range
with the values of the edges of our game area
and it will return a random value between them.
Copy Random.Range and return to our script.
Paste Random.Range in to our code
and let's feed Random.Range with
- spawnValues.x
and spawnValues.x.
Save this script and return to Unity.
Where are the edges of our game?
Let's move our asteroid along the X axis.
And it looks like about -6 and 6.
So spawnValues.x is 6.
Lastly we need to set our spawnRotation.
Back to our GameController script
let's find out more about
quaternion in the documentation.
Quaternions are complex.
We almost never access or modify
a quaternion directly.
There are many quaternion functions for us
for us to use.
We won't be using any of the quaternion
functions exactly, but we will be looking at
a quaternion property called Identity.
Quaternion.Identity corresponds with
no rotation of the quaternion.
We will instantiate our hazards with
no rotation at all.
Copy Quaternion.Identity
and return to our script.
Paste this in to our code so the line reads
Quaternion spawnRotation = Quaternion.Identity.
Save this script and return to Unity to test.
Remove our temporary asteroid.
Save the scene and play.
And we get a tumbling asteroid
from a random point left to right
starting outside of the game area
and moving along the game plane.
Let's enter and exit Play mode a few times.
We can see that our spawn points are random
and each new asteroid is spawned
at a new random location.
In the next assignment we will instantiate
waves of hazards to challenge our player with.