Now that we have our environment fully setup
let's get the player ship moving under our control.
To do this we need to write some very simply code.
We will be writing in C#, which is one of the
3 scripting languages supported by Unity.
To stay organised we need somewhere in our
project to store our new scripts.
Let's add a new folder to the root level
of our Assets folder.
It's worth noting that this folder could be placed
anywhere within our Assets folder to work
but for clarity it would seem that the root
level is the best location for such
an important folder.
Select Assets to make sure that we
build this folder on the root level
otherwise we will have to move it after
we have created it.
Use the Create menu in the Project view
and select Folder.
This will create a new folder in Assets.
This new folder will automatically make
itself ready to edit.
Let's change the name to Scripts,
and hit Enter or Return to accept
the change of the name.
Now let's create and add a new script
to our player ship.
I'm going to quickly reduce the view of these
referenced materials shown at the bottom of
the player game object by clicking on
the header bars.
This will make it easier to view and access
the Add Component button without scrolling.
Next let's click on Add Component
and select New Script.
This will allow us to create and add a new script
directly on to our player game object.
Now let's set the name of the script to
PlayerController.
I feel it's best that we follow the convention of
capitalisation shown here, with a capital
P and a capital C.
Script names should start with a capital letter
and the capitalisation of the name with the
capital C makes the name easier to read.
Once we have chosen a name we can click on
Create and Add, or we can simply hit Return
or Enter to create and add this script.
When we create a script in this manner the script
will be created on the root level of our project.
We need to drag and drop it on to the Scripts folder
to file it away properly.
Now open the scripts folder to view the script.
Let's open the script for editing.
We can do this in a number of ways.
1 way is to select the script
and in the Inspector choose Open.
This will open the script in MonoDevelop.
MonoDevelop is a companion application
that is bundled with Unity.
This is the default script editor that comes
with Unity, but you can use different
script editors if you choose.
For more information please see the details on
using Unity with other editors linked below.
Before we start I'm going to remove the sample code.
We will be moving our player ship using physics.
So we will need to use the FixedUpdate function.
For more information on both Update and
FixedUpdate and how to use them
see the information linked below.
So now let's write some code.
Write void FixedUpdate
FixedUpdate will be called automatically
by Unity just before each fixed physics step.
All the code we put inside the fixedUpdate
function will be executed once per physics step
so write
float moveHorizontal = input.GetAxis ("Horizontal")
and
float moveVertical = input.GetAxis ("Vertical")
This code grabs the input from the player.
The axis horizontal and vertical are default
axis that are preset in the input manager.
Next we need to apply that input
to the player game object.
We are going to move the player game object
using physics, and we are going to do this
by affecting the velocity of the game object directly.
Now this will result in non-realistic
physics behaviour, by hey, that's alright,
we are making an arcade game.
If we want to make a game that works properly
with Newtonian physics we would have
approached this code differently.
The rigidbody component which we attached
when we set up the player game object
is how we work with the built in physics engine.
The rigidbody includes properties
like UseGravity, Mass and  Drag
that we can pole, affect and manipulate.
So if we want to change the physics velocity
of the player game object we do this
by addressing the rigidbody component.
So let's write rigidbody.velocity
Now rigidbody.velocity uses a Vector3 value.
This gives us the direction we are travelling,
and how fast we are travelling
as a vector and it's magnitude.
For more information on the Vector3 class
and vector maths please see the
details linked below.
So our rigidbody velocity will be equal
some vector3 value.
But what?
Well, as we know, a vector3 is made out of
3 float numbers, an X, a Y and a Z value.
Well, what do we put in these 3 float values?
We want to use our player input.
Let's walk through this one step at a time.
How much do we want to move on the Y axis?
Or up and down?
Well, none.
So Y equals 0.0f
and if we write it this way, 0.0,
we need the f to indicate to Unity that
this decimal value is a floating point number.
How much do we want to move left to right?
Well, that's our moveHorizontal.
Copy moveHorizontal and paste
it over the X value.
And forward and back?
That's the value from moveVertical.
Copy and paste moveVertical
So how can we use this vector3
now that we've made it?
One way is to create a vector3 variable,
let's call it Movement,
and movement is equal to a
new vector3 moveHorizontal, 0.0f, moveVertical.
In C# we must remember to use
the keyword here.
and our rigidbody velocity is equal to movement.
Now let's save this script and return to Unity.
The first thing we check is the console,
to make sure that there are no errors
and that everything we wrote has compiled properly.
If there were an error we would also see
this error in the footer, as our most recent error
or message will always be shown in the footer.
Let's test our code.
Save the scene and enter Play mode.
We can move our ship,
but it's moving very very slowly.
This is because inputGetAxis only returns
a number between 0 and 1.
So our ship's movement with this code
will never be more than 1 unit per second.
Let's exit Play mode and return to our
PlayerController script.
We need control over our speed.
So let's create a new public
float variable called Speed.
This variable will hold a value we can
use to multiply our input with
as our input will only be a value of 0 to 1.
By multiplying our input by Speed
we will be able to move our ship from
0 up to a maximum of our Speed value.
Now, multiply our movement value by Speed.
Let's return to Unity.
We did not assign a value to Speed in our script.
Because we made Speed a public variable
we can see it, we can set it and
we can change it value in Unity.
Let's look at our player controller component.
We can now see an editable property called Speed.
Let's change it's value to 10.
Now we save and play,
and now we can move much faster around the game area.
10 times faster as a matter of fact,
but we have a problem,
and that problem is our player ship
can leave the game area.
We have no idea where the ship has gone,
and it would be very easy to completely
loose track of where our ship is.
We need to constrain the ship
within the game area.
So leave Play mode and return
to our PlayerController script.
We are moving our ship by setting
the rigidbody's velocity.
We can constrain the ship
by setting the value of the rigidbody's position.
Again, this won't give us realistic
physics behaviour, but in our
case it's not necessary.
Unity executes our code within a given
function 1 line at a time from top to bottom.
The code we have written moves our player ship.
We will write code that will come after
the code that moves our ship
and if we have moved outside of the game
the code will set the player's position
back to the edge of the game area.
Because Unity will read and execute
all of the code in our relevant function
before updating the frame
the ship itself will never leave the game area.
So let's write
rigidbody.position
and this is the property we want to set,
and then write
new vector3 (X,Y, Z)
and this is the value we want to set it to.
The code we are going to write next
will make 1 very long line.
So I'm going to break this code over
several lines vertically.
This will all be the same instruction to the compiler.
I'm going to follow the same indenting and
bracket conventions that we are already using
for organisation and readability.
Let's think about how much we want
to limit our movement.
How much margin do we want up and down?
None.
Our player game object should never leave
the plane of the game.
The Y value, let's set this to 0.
But what about left/right and forward/back?
The ship is moving along the X/Z plane
and we want to clamp it within the game area.
The ship starts at origin, or (0, 0, 0)
so we want to set limits on all 4 directions
along the X/Z plane.
Let's return to our script.,
So write Mathf.
What is Mathf?
Well let's look this up in the documentation.
And remember the shortcut to Unity's
scripting reference in the documentation is
command+' on the mac
and control+' on windows.
Mathf is well worth remembering.
It is a collection of really useful
easy to use math functions.
These include variables like Epsilon
Infinity and Pi,
and functions like Sine, Cosine, Tangent,
Square Root, Power, PingPong, Repeat,
and even Perlin Noise Generation.
What we are looking for is a function called Clamp.
Clamp will clamp any given value
between a minimum and a maximum value.
We will use this to clamp the position of
our player's ship in to our game area.
Returning to our script let's write
Clamp (rigibody.position.x, xMin, xMax)
and for Z let's write
Mathf.Clamp (rigidbody.position.z, xMin xMax)
This will effectively clamp our position
between the values we set for our min
and our max on the X and Z axis.
Now we need to declare our min and max values.
At the top of our script write
public float xMin, xMax, ZMin, zMax
and using this format we can define
all 4 float variables on 1 line of code.
Save the script and return to Unity.
Let's look at our player controller component
on the player game object.
We can see these new properties
but to me they seem to take up a large
amount of space in the Inspector.
Moreover, these properties can
only be used by this script.
There is a way that we can both clean up
this code and make it reusable.
That is to put these in to a separate
class of their own.
Let's return to our script
and let's move these in to their own class.
We start by defining a new class with
public class
and then we will name our class Boundary.
We will follow these with brackets to hold our code.
It's worth noting that this class
will not inherit from anything
like our PlayerController class does.
The : MonoBehaviour that comes after the class name
in our PlayerController class indicates that
this class is inheriting from MonoBehaviour.
For more information on classes
inheritance and monobehaviour
please see the information linked below.
Next, let's move our variable definitions from
PlayerController to Boundary.
So how do we use this new Boundary class?
First we need to make an instance of it
in our PlayerController.
So write public Boundary boundary;
and note the capitalisation.
Boundary with a capital B is our type
as defined by the class name.
Boundary with a lowercase b is
the name for our reference in the same way
that Speed is the name for our float variable.
Next we need to update our Clamp code
to reflect the changes that we have just made.
xMin is now part of our Boundary class,
which we access through the reference
that we made to our instance
by using Boundary.xMin.
This is true for xMax,
zMin,
and zMax as well.
Let's make our code neat and tidy
by aligning our indents.
Save the script, switch back to Unity
and let's look at the updated component.
Hmm, now we can't see our new updated
properties at all.
This is because the new class
that we have created is unknown to
and is therefore not serialised.
Serialising is a way of storing
and transferring information
Serialisation is a complicated issue.
At this point, just understanding
that Unity needs to have properties
serialised to view them in the Inspector
So let's switch back to our script.
To serialise our new class we need to use
[system.serializable]
in square brackets on the line before
we declare our class to make sure
that the class is serialised
and therefore visible in the Inspector.
Save the script and return to Unity.
Now if we look back at our Player Controller
we can see Boundary.
Turn down the gizmo and we can now see our
properties in an easy to use
but very tidy container.
We can also use this class in
other places in our game.
Now that we have our properties available to us
let's set their values.
Make sure that we have the player ship selected.
So what values do we need to set
for xMin and xMax?
Simply drag the ship to the edge of the game area
and note the values on the X axis.
These seem to be about -6 and 6.
So let's set these values to a good round
-6 and 6.
Doing the same thing along the Z axis,
that's about -4 along the bottom
but along the top edge we don't really
want to give our player access to the
entire upper game area.
We will need to give the hazards in our game
some room to be able to enter the game area.
So let's back off a little bit
say about 7 or 8.
Let's make zMin and zMax -4 and 8.
This will give us a square playable area
in our game and reserve
a little room for hazards at the top.
Now let's reset the player's transform
and let's test.
Enter Play mode,
and we can see that we are now clamped
inside the game area.
Exit Play mode.
Now we are essentially done with our
player game object, but I think it's worth
adding 1 bit of fun to it before we move on.
Let's add some bank, or tilt to the
player ship when we move from side
to side along the X axis.
Switch to our script and let's create
a new variable to hold our tilt value.
Next, after the code we have written
but still in FixedUpdate write
rigidbody.rotation = Quaternion.Euler.
And yes, it is pronounced oiler,
which is also an X, Y and Z value.
For more information on Quaternions and
Quaternion.Euler see the links below.
We only want to tilt, or bank,
along the Z axis
so X and Y are set to 0.
And Z?
We want the tilt along the Z axis to
be related to how fast we are moving
left to right, so our rotation on the Z axis
is equal to our rigidbody.velocity X
which is our velocity from left to right
multiplied by our tilt factor.
So we can control the maximum amount of bank.
The only correction we need to make this code is
to multiply by negative tilt.
Otherwise our ship will tilt in the opposite
direction to what we want.
Save the script and return to Unity
and let's set the tilt value.
Let's try 3.
If we feel it needs to tilt more
we can simply adjust the tilt property
with a higher value.
Let's try 4.
4 feels good.
Incidentally, when the ship is banked over
it picks up a good combination
of our fill and rim lights on the left side.
That completes the code for moving our player ship.
In the next assignment we will continue with
our game play by creating shots
for our player to shoot.