So we can now spawn 1 asteroid hazard.
But that's far too easy to be a challenge.
Let's spawn wave after wave of them.
To get started open the game controller script.
The code that we've written works fine
for spawning just one asteroid.
How do we get several of them?
Well, we could try to simply duplicate
the code we wrote by copying and
pasting it several times in our script.
If we save this script, switch to Unity
and enter Play mode
it kind of works.
We spawn several hazards,
though if they collide with each other
they do blow themselves up.
But this is less to do with our code
than the fact that we are spawning several
hazards at the same time at random spawn positions.
Is this the correct way to do things?
Well, frankly, no.
Let's return to our script.
Whenever we write the same code twice
or more we are almost always doing something wrong.
This code is terribly ugly.
We need to delete it as soon as possible,
and good riddance.
But how do we execute this code multiple
times without simply duplicating it?
What we do is we put our block of code
in to a loop and we execute that code
each time we cycle through that loop.
First let's create a public int called hazardCount.
To hold the number of times we cycle
through our loop.
We will be able to set this value in the
Inspector in Unity.
Next let's put our instantiate code in to our loop.
Indent the code we have written
and write for followed by a set of
parenthesis containing 2 semicolons
Surround our code block with brackets
We have now put our code in to a for loop.
We are not finished yet, but I wanted to
show you the 2 semicolons here.
When we are done writing our for loop
it will look very much like a function
with parameters.
Parameters in a function are separated by commas.
In a for loop they are statements
and they are separated by semicolons.
In the declaration of the for loop
we need to initialise a counter,
show the condition, or state how long
you want to stay in the loop
and then increment our counter.
In the initialise step create a new int
variable called i which is set to 0.
Our condition will be to stay in the loop
as long as I is less than hazardCount.
Lastly, every time we cycle through the loop
we increment i by 1 using i++.
Now when we execute SpawnWaves
we will loop through this code as many
times as we have set in hazardCount.
and then continue on with the function
after the loop, which in our case is nothing.
So the function will end.
Save this script and switch back to Unity to test.
Select GameController
and change the hazard count to 10.
Now let's enter and exit Play mode
a few times to see what happens.
Very much like when we duplicated the code
we are spawning a number of asteroid
hazards all at once.
Many are destroying each other on the first
frame when they overlap and collide.
Better, but not much of an improvement.
We have simplified our code
and we have easy control over the number of
hazards that we spawn.
But we don't have waves of enemies.
What we want our code to do is wait
after spawning each asteroid hazard
before spawning the next.
So we have a steady barrage of hazards
challenging our player.
Return to the GameController script.
We need a public float variable called
spawnWait to hold our wait time value.
Logically where we want to place our
wait code is at the end of the spawn code
in the for loop before the code loops back
and spawns the next asteroid hazard.
After instantiate write
wait for seconds spawnWait.
This is the correct logical place
in the code for us to wait
but this syntax does not work in C#.
To have a function that can pause
without pausing our entire game
we need to make this function a coroutine.
And coroutines have some very
specific considerations.
For more information on coroutines
please see the lessons and information linked below.
For this function to become a coroutine
we cannot return void.
We must return IEnumberator.
And our WaitForSeconds line
must be written as
yield return new WaitForSeconds.
Lastly we cannot call a coroutine
like we call a function.
We must explicitly use StartCoroutine.
With either the coroutine's name
or the signature in the parenthesis.
To be polite to our players let's create a new
public float variable called startWait.
And let's use this as the first line
in our new coroutine.
Copy the spawnWait line
and paste it as the first line of the block.
And change spawnWait to startWait.
When we set this value in the Inspector
it will be a short pause after the game
starts for the player to get ready,
get their hands on the controls and
prepare for action.
Save this script and return to Unity.
With GameController selected
let's set Spawn Wait to 0.5.
So we will spawn 2 asteroids every second.
And let's set the Start Wait to 1,
giving our players 1 second to get ready.
Save the scene and enter Play mode to test.
Now we have a steady stream of hazards.
Let's try that again.
Very nice.
But when the first 10 asteroids have
cleared the scene there is nothing
more for the player to do.
We could increase our hazard count
to 50, 100, 1000,
but that could get monotonous,
and if our player is good they could
eventually run out of hazards to shoot or avoid.
Return to the PlayerController script.
We want to create continuous waves of hazards
until our player is destroyed and the game is over.
We can do this by wrapping our instantiate
loop in another loop.
Grab the for loop code that we have written
and indent that code.
Write while followed by parenthesis.
Wrap the code block in brackets.
This is a while loop.
With a while loop we will continue to
cycle through that loop while the
statement in the parenthesis is true.
Let's say as long as A is greater than B
or whatever statement our code needs.
In this case we will say while true
and of course true will always be true
so this becomes an infinite loop.
We will discuss how to break out of this
infinite loop in another assignment.
The way this works is in our while loop
we execute our for loop
and we instantiate our wave of hazards
based on our hazard count.
When we're done spawning our wave
the while loop brings us back to the top
of the block and we execute the for loop again.
To create a gap between our waves we need
to wait, this time at the end of the while loop.
Write yield return new WaitForSeconds.
Write public float waveWait.
And the amount of time we wait between waves
will be represented by waveWait.
Save this script and return to Unity.
We can see our GameController component
now has a Wave Wait property.
Let's set this to 4.
Save the scene and enter Play mode to test.
There's our first wave of 10 asteroids.
We have a pause between waves as we wait
in our while loop.
and there is another wave as we
execute our for loop again.
Another pause.
And wave 3, and this will continue
until we exit Play mode.
This is starting to look like a real game.
There is one last step we need to do
before we sign off on this segment however.
Look in to our Hierarchy while we're playing the game,
it's full of used explosion clones.
Every time we destroy an asteroid
the asteroid spawns an explosion
and there it stays.
Currently we have only 2 ways of destroying
things in our game.
When they leave the boundary trigger box
and by contact.
Neither will work in this case.
We will need to write another way of
destroying things by time.
Exit Play mode.
Select the Scripts folder
and use the Create menu in the Project view.
Choose C# Script.
Unity creates new assets where we are
focused in the Editor.
By selecting the Scripts folder before we
created our new script Unity created it
inside the Scripts folder,
so there is no need to file it away.
Rename this script DestroyByTime.
And with the script selected open it for editing.
This script will be very simple.
After removing the sample code write
void Start Destroy gameObject.
Now this seems a bit crazy,
destroying our game object the same frame
it's instantiated, no?
Well, Destroy is very useful.
For more information on Destroy see the
lessons and information linked below.
One of the parameters in Destroy is Time.
We can specify a wait time before
Destroy takes effect.
Let's write public float lifetime.
And let's copy lifetime.
After gameObject add a comma
and paste lifetime.
Now when our game object is instantiated
like a ticking time bomb
the object will set it's lifetime and
destroy itself when the time is up.
Save this script and return to Unity.
Select the Explosions folder in Prefabs VFX.
In the Explosions folder are our
explosion prefabs.
Select the Astroid explosion and using the
Add Component button select Scripts
and choose DestroyByTime.
Set the value of lifetime to 2.
We can also add a script this way to multiple items.
Let's update all of our explosion prefabs.
Select the other 2 explosion prefabs
and using multi-object editing
use the Add Component button and select Scripts
and again choose DestroyByTime.
And set the lifetime value to 2 as well.
This adds the script and sets the
lifetime value on both prefabs
at the same time.
Save the scene.
Enter Play mode and test.
We can see the explosion clones are no longer
accumulating in our scene,
not even the player's explosion.
We almost have a complete game!
In the next assignment we will add
audio to our scene.
Including explosion sounds
and laser guns blasting.