In this assignment we are going to make
a script to manage the enemy's player detection.
Select the robot guard in the hierarchy
and click Add Component.
Choose New Script and name the script
EnemySight.
Double click the icon to launch it for editing
and prepare the script as usual.
We will need three public variables.
The first is a float we will call fieldOfViewAngle
This is the number of degrees, centred on
the forward direction that the enemy can see through.
If the player is outside of this field of view
the enemy will not react.
We want this to be public so we can tweak it
in the Inspector, but we will give it a default
of 110 degrees.
The next is a Boolean we will call playerInSight.
This will be true when the enemy can see the
player and false otherwise.
We need this to be public so that it can be
accessed by the decision making script Enemy AI
The last public variable we will need is
a vector3 that we will call personalLastSighting.
This is the last sighting of the player
unique to an individual enemy.
When the player is spotted by an alarm system
or another enemy this variable
will be set to the global sighting position
that all the enemies converge upon.
However, when the enemy hears the player without
seeing him this will store the player's location
without setting the global value to alert
the other enemies.
Next we need to setup a series of private
references to other components.
The first one we will need is a reference to
the nav mesh agent.
This is because we are going to use the length
of the path to the player as a measure of
how far away the enemy can hear.
We will be comparing it to the radius of the
sphere collider, so we will need a reference
to that too.
The animator controller has a playerInSight
Boolean parameter which we will
need in order to set this script's
playerInSight Boolean.
Therefore we will need a reference to the animator.
The global last known location of the player
is in our LastPlayerSighting script
as such we will need a reference to that.
We will be using some of the onTriggerEnter
functions in this script to detect the player
entering the sphere collider
and as such we will need a reference to the player.
Since the enemy can hear the player when he's
running or shouting we will need a reference
to the player's animator, in order to tell
which state he is currently in.
When the player is dead we want our enemy
to ignore him, so we will need a reference
to the PlayerHealth script.
Since we will be comparing animator controller
states in this script, we will need a reference
to the HashIDs script we wrote earlier
that stores them.
The last private variable that we will need
is not a reference but a variable
for storing the personalLastSighting
from the previous frame.
This way we can know if the position of the
player has changed.
Now that we have all of the variables ready to
store our references we need to actually
assign them. We will do this inside the Awake function.
Also in the awake function we need to
make sure that the personalLastSighting
and the previousSighting both have the
default reset value from lastPlayerSighting
so that when the game begins the enemies are
not chasing the player.
There are a couple of things that we need to do
in the Update function.
Firstly we need to check if the globalSighting
of the player has changed, and if it has
update the personalSighting of the player.
After this check we need to change the previous
position to be this frame's position.
The other thing that we need to do in the update
function is to set the playerInSight
animator parameter, however we only want to update
this whilst the player is alive.
If the player is not alive we want the
playerInSight parameter to be false.
The majority of the code for this script is
going to be in an OnTriggerStay function
For playerInSight to be true the player
being in view must satisfy three conditions.
One, that he is within the trigger zone.
Two, that he is in front of the enemy
to the extent of the enemy's field of view
and three, that nothing is blocking
the enemy's view of the player.
The first condition is satisfied
if the colliding game object is the player.
At this point we also need to set the
playerInSight variable to be false.
That way if the player is in the trigger zone
but the other conditions are not satisfied
then playerInSight will default to false.
To determine whether the player is within
the field of view we are going to use a
function of the vector3 class called Angle.
This takes in two vector3s and
returns the angle between them.
We will parse in a vector from the enemy
to the player and then enemy's forward vector.
If this angle is less than half the field
of view angle then the player
is within the field of view.
Now we can have the condition to check
whether our angle is less than half
of the field of view angle variable.
Given that the player is within the field of view
we now need to know that there is no obstruction
between the enemy and the player
To find this out we will use a ray cast
from the enemy to the player.
And if something is hit we will determine
whether it is the player or not.
For this we will need to create a ray cast hit
variable which we will call hit.
Now remember that the root of the enemy FPX
is at it's feet. This means that if we
ray cast from it's position, it's feet,
we might hit the floor.
Instead we can use transform.position
plus transform.up as our starting position
for the ray cast.
As the model is approximately 2 units tall
and transform.up is 1 up in the Y axis
this is around the centre of the model.
The direction of the ray cast is the direction
vector we created earlier for measuring the angle.
The direction vector of a ray cast is
always normalised, we we'll always
have a magnitude of 1.
The next parameter is the rayCastHit
variable we have created.
And finally the distance.
For this there is no point in the ray cast being
any longer than the radius of the collider,
for that is where we want to check for the player.
Next we need to check that if we hit
something it is the player.
At this point we know that the player is in sight,
so we can get the playerInSight variable to true
and update the global sighting of the player
to alert the other enemies.
At this point we need to deal with the player being heard
rather than seen. The conditions for this are that
the player is running or shouting.
Both of these are animator states that the
player can be in, so we need to check for them.
We will start by storing the name hash
of the player's states on both layers.
Now we can compare these variables to the hashIDs.
When the enemy hears the player it may not be
a straight line to the target.
If the player was just around the corner then
the enemy should be able to hear him.
But if they are in a completely different room
then the enemy shouldn't be able to hear
through the walls.
What we need is a way of telling how far the sound
would have to travel, and we can do this
by calculating routes using the nav mesh.
We will keep these calculations in a separate function.
We will make the function return the length
of the path we are calculating it will
need to take in a vector3 as the
target position. The first step in this function
is to create a new empty nav mesh path.
Now we are going to use a function of the nav mesh
agent called calculatePath.
This takes in a target destination
and the path variable that we've just created.
The NavMeshPath type is a class,
which means it's a reference type,
one that can be assigned to within a function.
This means that our path variable will be
effected by the CalculatePath function,
since we are parsing in a reference to the variable
We will first ensure that the nav mesh agent
is enabled and then calculate the path.
Part of the NavMeshPath class
is an array of vector3s called Corners.
These are all of the corners on the route of the path.
If we added the position of the enemy
and the player to this array then we will
have an array of all of the way points on the path.
We can then add together all of the distances
between the way points to get the path length
and therefore the distance that the sound would
have to travel to be heard by the enemy.
Let's call our array allWayPoints
and declare it's length as the length
of the corners array plus 2 more.
to allow for the enemy and player positions.
Now the first point of this array should
be the enemy's position.
And the last point of the array is the target
position, that of the player.
All the points in between will be those
from the corners array. We can assign these using
a For loop which performs an assignment
for each of the corners.
Since we don't want to assign the first item
in the allWayPoints array the index that we will
assign to will be i+1.
Now we need to create a float to store
our path length.
We need to initialise it to be 0
since it won't be able to increment
if it has not been initialised.
We will need another loop.
This will iterate over each of the lengths
between the waypoints.
Therefore it will need to loop the number
of times that is one less than the number
of waypoints in the array.
An array of 3 waypoints will have
2 lengths that join them.
An array of 4 waypoints will have 3 lengths
and so on. Then, in each loop we need to
add the distance between one waypoint and
the next to the pathLength variable.
Finally we just need to return the path length.
With the function finished we can put a
call to it in our OnTriggerEnter function.
Since the furthest distance the enemies can
hear is the sphere collider's radius
we need to make sure that the length of the path
returned from our function is less
than or equal to this radius.
And if this is the case we set the
personalLastSighting to the player's position.
The final part of this script is to make sure
that playerInSight is set to false
when the player leaves the trigger zone.
This is done very simply with an
OnTriggerExit function.
Now we can save our script and return to the Editor.
We need to create a new subfolder in our
Scripts folder to hold this script
and others for the enemy.
Select the Scripts folder
and go to Create - Folder
and call this folder Enemy.
Then reselect Assets
and expand Scripts and drag and drop
EnemySight in to the Enemy folder.
Now we can save our scene and project
and in the next assignment we will be making
a script to handle parsing the parameters
for the movement from the nav mesh system
to the animator controller.