In this beginner assignment we are going
to make a very simple but playable game to
use many of the basic concepts from the
beginner tutorial modules.
We will be making a roll-a-ball game where
we will collect special game objects.
We will see how to create new game objects,
add components to these game objects,
set the values on their properties and position
these game objects in the scene to create a game.
In our game the player will control a ball
rolling around the game board.
We will move the ball using physics and forces.
We will look at the input from the player
through the keyboard and we'll use those
inputs to apply forces to the ball, making it
move in our scene.
We will see how to detect contact between
the player's ball and the pick-up game objects,
and use these events to collect these
pick-up game objects.
When we are done we will have made a simple
roll-a-ball game where the player controls
the ball with the keyboard, picks up and
counts special collectable objects,
displays the current count and ends the game
when all of the game objects
have been picked up.
We won't need to import any assets for this project.
We won't be using models, textures,
sounds or animations for this assignment.
We will simply use the primitive shapes
like cubes, spheres and planes
provided by Unity.
To begin, start with assignment 1 where we
setup our game and starting game objects.