Detecting a collision in Unity requires
one of the two colliding objects
to contain a script with an
OnCollisionEnter function in.
The basic syntax takes a single argument
of type Collision.
From this you can query the collision
to find out information about the object
that has been collided with.
In this example our samoflange ball is
bouncing around with a bouncy physic material
and hitting power cubes.
The script attached to the ball looks like this.
Currently we have nothing inside the function.
We can make use of the collision argument to
check for when it has hit a power cube.
We simply use an IF statement and check
'col', our variable, for the data
it contains. One example of which
is the game object that it's collided with
and as a result, the name. We would say
if(col.gameobject.name) is equal to
the hierarchical name of the power cube
which is 'prop_powercube'
and now this IF statement will only activate
when our ball collides with our power cube.
If it does collide, we'll make use of the
Destroy command. You can check what
types of data you can retrieve
from the collision by typing the name of the
variable and then typing a dot (period) in the script editor.
You'll then see a list of the various
different data you can retrieve from the collision.
Also remember to check the script reference
page linked below on the collision
class to see other data that you can retrieve.
For now we'll simply destroy the game object.
And when we save our script
you'll see that whenever a collision occurs
our ball destroys a power cube.