When working with code
you will inevitably need to work with
many types of variables.
Ultimately all variables have
what is called a Datatype.
The 2 primary data types
are value types and reference types.
Variables like integers, floats,
doubles, booleans and characters
are all value types.
Additionally there are complex
variables types known as structs
Structs are value data types
that simply contain one or more other variables.
The two most common structs in Unity
are vector3 and quaternion.
The list of reference types is much simpler.
Basically any variable that is an
object of a class is a reference type.
The two most common classes
and thus the two most common reference types in Unity
are transform and game object.
You might be wondering what the difference is
between value and reference types.
Simply put, value type variables
actually contain some value.
All reference type variables contain a
memory address where the value is stored.
The result if that if a value type changes
only that specific variables is affected.
If a reference type changes however
all variables that contain that memory
address will also be affected.
As an analogy consider this;
Charles has a nice blue house full of his favourite things.
Quentin sees Charles' house online and is jealous
and so makes an exact copy and wills
it with duplicates of everything that Charles owns
Creepy, right?
This is like a sign made for value types.
You make a copy of the variable.
Quentin doesn't own Charles' house
and nothing he changes in his house will affect the original.
Not even painting it red.
If Quentin had Charles' address
he wouldn't need to copy the house.
He could simply visit any time he likes
and see it's content instead.
This is like assignment for reference types.
You make a note of the memory address of the value you need
and return to that address when you need to know
the value of the variable.
Let's take a look at this in action
We have here a scene with a sphere in it.
The sphere has a script named
DatatypeScript attached to it.
Inside the DatatypeScript we first
create a vector3 variable named pos
and assign to it the value of the transform's position.
We then set pos equal to a new vector3
with a value of (0, 2, 0).
Since we know that pos is a vector3 struct
and that structs are value types
we know that only pos is affected by this line of code.
The transform's position is unaffected.
If we go back in to Unity we can run our scene
and confirm that the sphere does not move.
Value types contain their own copy of data
and changing them only affects
that specific variable.
Back in the DatatypeScript, let's try another approach.
Let's start by creating a transform variable named tran,
and setting it equal to the object's transform.
Then let's set tran's position to a new vector3
with a value of (0, 2, 0).
Since transform is a class
we know that tran is a reference type.
Furthermore, since we assign the object's transform to
the variable tran using the assignment operator
we know that they point at the same memory address.
The result is that changing one changes the other.
Back in Unity we can run out scene.
We should notice immediately that the sphere
has moved upwards, even though we never directly
changed the value of the sphere's transform.
We were able to indirectly change it
by using a reference variable.