When scripting in Unity sometimes we want a
variable that is one of a set of constants.
Consider the points of a compass.
We could describe these using an integer
where 0 was north, 1 was east,
2 was south and 3 was west.
This wouldn't be very easy to read write in code
since it would mean remembering what each number referred to.
Instead we can create something called
an enumeration.
Enumerations, which are often referred to as Enums,
are a special data type that has a specific
subset of possible values.
Here we have a script named EnumScript.
Let's create an enumeration to represent
the different directions of a compass.
We can create the enumeration either inside
or outside of the class.
We would place an enumeration in the class
if only that class needed access to it.
We would place the enumeration outside the class
if other classes also needed access to it.
For this example we will be creating
it inside the class.
The syntax when declaring an enumeration
is to start with the enum keyword.
Next we give it a name.
For our example we'll call the enumeration Direction.
Note that we're using a capital letter for Direction.
That's because we are effectively declaring a type
and not a variable.
Then we need to list the various
constants of the enumeration separated by
commas in braces.
First we want north, then east, south
and finally west.
Unlike when you normally close braces,
this is the end of a statement and so
needs a semi-colon.
Each of the constants declared in this enumeration
has a value which by default
is an integer starting at 0.
This is incremented through the set
so north has a value of 0,
east has a value of 1,
south has a value of 2
and west has a value of 3.
Both the type of value and the
values themselves can be overridden if required.
If we were to declare the Enum
with north = 1
then east would have a value of 2,
south a value of 3
and west a value of 4.
Alternatively we could declare a value
for each of the constants, such as north = 10,
east = 11, south = 15
and west equals 27.
We can also change the type of the constants
in an enumeration.
The constants can be changed to
any integral type.
For more information on integral types
see the link below
We change the type by putting a colon
after the name of our enumeration and
putting the type afterwards.
For example we could have direction:short.
This would mean that the type of the enumeration
was short instead of int.
One of the main reasons for changing the type of
an enum is optimisation.
But we generally won't worry about it.
Once we have our enum declared we
then make variables of the enum's type.
Let's make a direction variable called myDirection.
We now can treat this just like any other variable
but whereas an integer might have a value of 5
or a float might have a value of 97.3
our myDirection variable
can have values of direction.north,
direction.east, direction.south or direction.west.
Let's set myDirection to a Direction.North in the start function.
Our enum can also be parsed in
to and returned from functions.
We simply use the name of the enumeration,
in our case Direction
where we would use a type.
To illustrate this let's make a small
small function to reverse a given direction.
Given north it should return southern so on.
The return type for our function is Direction
and we'll call the function ReverseDirection.
We'll give the function a direction parameter
which we'll call dir, and return the opposite
Now all we need to do it
compare dir to our various direction constants
We only need to check for north, east,
south and west because those are the only possible values.