The scope of a variable is the area in
code which the variable can be used in.
A variable is said to be local to the
place in code that it can be used.
Code blocks are generally what defines a
variable's scope, and these are denoted
by braces.
So for example, everything within the
class in this example can be said to
be local to that class.
The variables pens, crayons, and answer
are all local to the example function
and cannot be used outside of that.
You would say that the variables
alpha, beta and gamma are in scope
within the scope and access modifiers class.
And you would say that the pens, crayons
and answer variables are in scope
within the example function.
Public and Private Access Modifiers.
Variables defined in the class as
opposed to those declared within a function
have an access modifier attributed
to them. An access modifier is a keyword
placed before a data type when declaring the variable
and it's purpose is to define where the
variable or function can be seen from.
As a general rule if other scripts need
access to a variable or function then it
should be public, otherwise is should be private.
Declaring a variable as public means that
it can be accessed from outside the class.
It also means that the variable is shown
and editable on the component in the inspector.
In this example my scope and
access modifiers script
is applied to our prop samoflange object
and you can see that the public variable
alpha is included as a property that I
can edit. This allows the user to edit
the variable whilst they test the game.
Imagine for example the value
controls the speed of a car. It would be nice
to be able to tweak that variable whilst
testing it without having to stop, edit
the script and play again. As such
it makes sense to have this be a public
variable. Note that if a variable is
initialised in the class to a
a default value, for example if we had put
alpha equals 5
then it will still be overridden by the value
that's written in the inspector.
However if these values are set in functions
such as Start and Awake these
occur after the variable has been set
in the inspector and will not be overridden.
So for example, if my script had a
default value of 5 but was being
overridden by the inspector then setting
it manually with a Start function
will override the value in the inspector.
Now given that the game is at runtime
if I tweak the value again
that's now overriding the script again.
So bear in mind that even though the
public variable is tweakable on the
component it doesn't mean that you can't
go back and edit it via a script during
during runtime.
Private variables can only be edited from
within the class. In C# private is the
default access modifier for any
variable that doesn't have it specified.
So although I've written private on
beta and gamma, if I hadn't they would be
private regardless. It's good practice
to make all member variables, those that belong
to a class rather than a function,
private, unless they need to be public
for a specific reason.
Setting variables and functions to public
can also mean that you can access them from
other scripts. So for example I have
another class here which has 2 functions in,
a public function called FruitMachine
and a private called OfficeSort.
And I have some public variables and
some private variables. Back in my original
script I can call only the public
members of that script.
For example, if I were to create
an instance of the class
AnotherClass, and you can see that when I
try and access this the
apples and banana variables as well as
FruitMachine are available,
and you can see that in telesense in MonoDevelop
is telling me that I can use these.
So when I choose FruitMachine and open the
the bracket it's then telling me what
arguments need to be fed in to that.
And I can feed in any of the variables
that are in scope of this script, or
that are in scope of AnotherClass
because they are public.
So I could use any of the variables
from my scope and access modifiers class
and I can access the instance of another
class and make use of a public variable
from there, such as apples for example.
Note that because the OfficeSort
and stapler and sellotape are all
private I can't access them by creating
an instance of another class.
They're for use only within the class itself.
(翻訳:gamesonytablet)