When making decisions in code
it is common to use an If statement
or a series of If Else statements.
An alternative to this can be the Switch statement.
A switch statement is a more streamlined conditional
that is used when you want to compare a single variable
to a series of constants.
A common use of switches is to make
decisions based on enumerations.
For more details on enumerations
see the lesson on enumerations linked below.
Consider a game where a character's conversation
options were based on their intelligence.
You could set these options using a series of
If Else statements, but that could get cumbersome.
Instead we can use a switch statement
to more easily implement our solution.
Here we have a script called ConversationScript.
In this script we will implement a function
that will allow a character to give a greeting
based on their intelligence.
First we will create an integer
for our character's intelligence.
We will set this variable equal to 5.
For the purpose of this example
let's say that intelligence ranges from 5 being the highest
to 1 being the lowest.
Next we will create a function called Greet,
which will use a switch statement to output
a greeting based on the character's intelligence.
The syntax for a switch statement
starts with the keyword switch followed by
the variable which it will be comparing in parenthesis.
In this case we will be comparing
our intelligence variable.
We follow that with some open and closed braces.
Inside the braces we need to define
a series of cases.
These cases are the constants that we are
comparing our variable against.
To create a case we use the keyword case
followed by our constant and a colon.
As you can see we are starting by
defining what the character will say
if they have an intelligence of 5.
Let's print out a greeting that someone of
high intelligence might give.
As I am not of particularly high intelligence myself
I'm going to guess.
That seems about right.
After the instructions for each case
we need to include something called a Jump statement.
The most commonly used jump statement for
switches is Brake.
This is a keyword that jumps the code
execution out of the switch
so that none of the subsequent cases are executed.
Think of brake working like the return keyword.
But whereas return most commonly is used
in functions, brake is used in switches and loops.
After encountering a brake,
code will continue execution after the
block of code it is in.
In our situation, since the brake
is inside of a switch
after it encountered
execution will continue just after the switch.
Let's put in a couple more cases
with phrases of decreasing intelligence.
For our final case we want to catch
everything that doesn't have a case of it's own.
To do this, instead of using case,
we use another keyword, default.
Since this should be for any case that hasn't
already been covered it doesn't need a value.
Other than that we treat it as we would
any other case.
Think of default as the Else
in an If Else statement.
Just like else, default covered
any situation not caught by a preceding conditional.