In Unity scripts are made up of 1 or more classes.
C# scripts have the class declarations
shown. In Javascript however, the declaration
is hidden, meaning that what you write
into the script is automatically
inside the class. It is the equivalent of
writing here in the C# script.
A variable declaration in C#
starts with the type of variable you are
declaring. You then name the variable.
You then have the option to give it a default value.
In Javascript a variable declaration
starts by using the keyword var.
We then name the variable.
After that we have the option to say what
type of variable it is we are declaring,
by using a colon.
It is good practice to decide on a variable
type when declaring it.
We can then optionally give it a default value.
The line #pragma strict at the top
forces us to select a type.
A function declaration in C#
starts with a type of variable that will
return from the function.
Or the word void if we're not returning
anything from the function.
We then name the function.
We then have the parameter list,
also known as the arguments.
The contents of the function go here.
In Javascript a function declaration
starts with the keyword function.
We then need to name the function.
Then comes the parameter list.
Similarly to setting a variable type
we can use a colon
to set a return type for our function.
Another key difference between C# and
Javascript is the default access modifiers.
In C# the default is private.
Whereas in Javascript the default is public.
See the lesson on variable scope and access
modifiers for more information.