The Destroy function can be used to remove
gameobjects or components from
gameobjects at runtime.
This can also be done with a time delay
by using it's second argument, a float number.
To destroy a gameobject, for example,
we could simply refer to the gameobject
that the script is attached to.
In this example our prop samoflange object
has the script attached to it, and when the
spacebar is pressed the gameobject
will be destroyed.
Now a problem could be that you may be using
this script for various purposes
so it doesn't make sense to destroy the object
as the script component will be removed
too, as it's attached to the object.
So instead you'd likely use a reference
to another object. Here we've setup a public
variable called Other to refer
to another object. Then in the inspector
we'll drag on another object to use,
for example our physics door.
Now when we press play
and press space
our door gets removed from the scene.
You can also use the Destroy command to remove
components, rather than entire game objects.
For this we use the GetComponent function
inside the destroy parenthesis
to refer to a component.
In this example I'll destroy the mesh
renderer component so that the object
is no longer visibly rendered.
Here you can see that the object is still
in the game and has all of it's other
components, except for the mesh renderer
that we removed. All of these examples can
include a number as the second argument
in order to create a timed delay.
For example, if I add 3 as a floating
point number, as my second argument,
save the script.
Once I've pressed the spacebar
there will be a 3 second delay
and then my object will be removed.
This works the same for destroying components.