To enable or disable a component in Unity
simply use the Enabled flag.
In this example we have a reference
to a light, called myLight
and in Start we're setting this variable
using the GetComponent function
to the light component attached to our object.
In update I'm waiting for the key press space
and then I'm setting the Enabled flag
on myLight to false.
Let's see it in action.
I could also set this to true, but it
would be even more efficient to make
it a toggle. So I'll set it to
the inverse of myLight.enabled.
So by using the exclamation mark
not keyword I'm effectively saying
set this to whatever it's not at the moment.
So I'll save my script.
And now you can see that when I press play
the spacebar acts as a toggle
switching the light component on and off
signified by the checking and unchecking
of the checkbox next to the name of
the component in the inspector.
Keep in mind that because scripts are also
components you can use the dot enabled
flag to disable those too.