The ternary operator is a condensed
form for an if else statement.
In it's most basic form the ternary operator
is used for deciding between two values
based on some boolean expression.
The syntax has the format
boolean ? true expression : false expression.
The first parameter is the boolean, or a condition which
evaluates to a boolean that you wish to test.
The end of this parameter is marked with a question mark
The next parameter is the value that the ternary operator
would evaluate to if the condition is true.
This is followed by a colon.
Then the final parameter is the value that the
ternary operator would evaluate to if the condition is false.
Here we use a simple ternary operator to determine
if a player is alive or dead.
Ternary operators can be nested within one another
but if used for long expressions
this can make code cumbersome and difficult to read.
A general rule for when to use a ternary operator
instead of an If statement is if your code needs
a simple If Else structure with a single
short expression in each case.