Let's begin by creating a new project.
We can create a new project from File - New Project.
This will bring up the new project window.
The first thing we need to do is set the
destination or path to our new project.
I'm going to put this new project on my desktop.
I'm going to call the new project Roll-a-ball.
And then I will click on Create Project
to make a new project.
We now have our new project with a new empty scene.
Before creating anything in the new scene
we need to save our scene.
We can save our scene by going to File - Save Scene
or by using the keyboard shortcut.
I'm going to save this scene in the Assets directory
in a new folder called _scenes.
The underscore is optional, I use it to sort this
folder to the top of my project window.
Now I'm going to call the scene MiniGame.
We can now see in our Scenes folder
the scene called MiniGame.
Let's create our game board, or play field.
To do this we will use a stock Unity plane.
We can create this plane from either
Game Object - Create Other - Plane.
Or from inside the Hierarchy view using the Create menu.
Rename this game object Ground.
We can do this by either selecting the game object
and using the enter or return keys
to allow editing, or by clicking on the
game object twice, slowly.
Type in the new name or hit enter or return
to confirm this change.
Reset the transform component using the context
sensitive gear menu in the upper right.
This will place the game object at the location of
(0, 0, 0) in our scene.
This point is known as the origin point
of the world and this is where all of the
coordinates in the scene are calculated from.
Now with the game object selected and the
cursor over the Scene view type the F key, or choose
Frame Selected from the Edit menu
to see the entire game object in the Scene view.
We need to change the scale of the ground plane.
We can do this in a number of ways..
We can use the Scale tool,
simply grab the axis handle you want to change
and drag the handle rescaling the plane.
We can click and drag on the title of
the fields we want to change.
Or we can type a number directly in to the
field we want to change.
You can tab between fields and hit enter or return
to confirm your choice.
Now remember a plane has no volume
and scale does not work on the Y axis.
There will be no change unless you go in to negative numbers.
In this case the plane, which is a single
sided object will simply face the other direction.
If you place a plane in the scene and you can't see it
check your orientation between the plane and camera
and make sure that you have the correct values
for the Y axis of scale.
This is usually the value of 1.
Let's create our player object.
In this assignment our player object
will be a Unity sphere.
From the Hierarchy - Create menu select Sphere.
Rename the sphere Player.
Reset the transform to make sure it's a origin.
Select Edit - Frame Selected
or use the F key while the cursor is
over the Scene view to focus our Scene view
camera on our game object.
See how the sphere is buried in the plane?
This is because both game objects
are in the exact same location in the scene,
the origin point, or (0, 0, 0)
on the X, Y and Z axis.
We need to move the player's sphere up
until it rests on the plane.
All Unity primitive objects, cubes, spheres, capsules,
have a standard size, they are either
1 by 1 by 1 or 1 by 2 by 1 Unity units.
As such we simply lift the player object up
by half a unit in the Y axis
and we know it is laying perfectly on top of plane.
If we look in the Game view we can see it's very dark.
There are no lights in the scene.
Add a new directional light from the Hierarchy - Create menu.
Rename this Main Light.
Reset the game object's transform to Origin.
Set the X axis and the transform's rotation to 30
so it shines down on the game board.
Now this light does not give shape to the player's sphere
so set the transform's Y axis to 60
so the light comes in from 1 side.
This gives a better shape to the ball.
The player's position over the plane is some what ambiguous.
It's hard to tell the player's exact position over the plane.
Shadows will help with this.
Set the shadow type on the main light to soft shadows
and set the resolution to very high resolution.
Now it's hard to see the separation between
the ball and it's shadow.
To help with this let's add what is
called a fill light.
Duplicate the main light.
Rename Main Light to Fill Light.
Reverse the transform rotation values to -30
and -60.
so the light shines up from below but still from the front.
Change the colour value for the light
to give a hint of blue.
And lower the intensity to 0.1.
Finally, turn off shadows.
This will now act as a gentle fill light on the
ball separating it from it's shadow.
Let's look at the organisation of our hierarchy.
Even with only 5 game objects
the hierarchy is already getting confusing
and is disorganised.
Organisation in our projects and in our hierarchy
are very important.
We need to understand the organisation at a glance.
We organise our projects using folders or directories
created by our operating system.
We add these to our project using the
Project Views - Create menu.
We organise our hierarchies by using game objects.
In our scene game objects can hold other game objects.
Don't be afraid to use an empty game object
as a directory or folder in the hierarchy.
To do this, first create a new empty game object.
Rename it Lighting.
Reset the transform to origin,
and this step is important, we want the transforms of
all of our container game objects to be at
origin before we use them.
Add the Fill Light and the Main Light
to the lighting parent game object.
Now see how these lights are in the middle of the game board?
They are some what in the way.
Remember directional lights light all of the game
objects in the scene based on their rotation
not their position.
We can simply move their parent game object
up 100 units above the game board.
There they are, out of the way.
Next we will find a way to move the player game
object using player input.