In this assignment we will be going through
making some standard pinch zooms
style touch controls.
Our controls will be made by using a script
that we'll attach to the camera.
Select the main camera in the scene.
Next we will add a C# script
to our camera by clicking Add Component - New Script.
We will call our script PinchZoom.
Once that is done click Create and Add.
Now we can double click on the script
to open it for editing.
Let's remove the body of the class
so we have a nice clean place to start.
The principle of a pinch zoom works as follows.
We need to first make sure we have
exactly two touches on the device.
Then we need to know the distance between
those touches on both the current
frame and the previous frame.
If the distance between the touches
has gotten smaller the touches have moved
closer together and we should zoom out.
Similarly if the distance between the
touches has increased then we should zoom in.
The first thing we need to do in this script
is to make a couple of public float variables.
These will be used to adjust the speed
at which the zoom happens.
We need two variables so that we can
separately adjust speeds to both perspective
and orthographic cameras.
We will call these variables
perspectiveZoomSpeed
and orthoZoomSpeed respectively.
We will also give them a default value of 0.5.
Since touch input is detected in time
with the update loop it is usually best to
deal with that input in the update function.
However we only want to do anything
if there are exactly two touches on the device.
We can check this using the Input.touchCount property.
Now that we are sure that there are exactly
two touches we can store those touches
in our own touch variables.
This way we don't have to keep accessing
the properties of the input class.
We access the touches using the GetTouch function
of the input class.
Since there are only two touches present.
these will be indices 0 and 1 in the touches array/
We can therefore parse 0 and 1
to the GetTouch function to get a copy of these touches.
Now that we have the touches
we need to find out what their positions were
in the previous frame.
We do this by taking their current position
and subtracting their delta position.
We want to find the distance between the touches
in each frame and use that knowledge to determine
whether we need to zoom in or out.
To find the distance between the touches in either frame
we subtract one touches position
from the other to get a vector between them.
Then from that vector we simply find it's magnitude.
We can do this in one step by
enclosing our vector subtraction in parenthesis
and using the . operator.
We are using the term delta
because it refers to a change between two pieces of data.
Having calculated the distance between
touches in each frame we can now
find out the differences between those distances.
This time the order in which we subtract is important.
We will subtract the current frame's distance
between touches from the previous frames distance.
This will result in a negative value
if the distance in the current frame is greater
than that of the previous frame.
This means that the fingers are moving apart.
If the fingers are moving apart
then we expect to zoom in
reducing the field of view
or orthographic size of the camera.
Since we want to reduce either the field of view
or orthographic size under these conditions
this is the correct way to subtract the two values.
Before we can go about changing the
properties of the camera though,
we need to know if the camera is in orthographic mode
or perspective.
If it is orthographic then we can adjust the camera's
orthographic size by the change in the distance
multiplied by the orthographic zoom speed.
We are also going to make sure our camera's orthographic size
does not drop below 0.
If it does the image will invert.
To prevent this we are going to use
the Max function of the Mathf class.
This will return which ever is the largest
of the parameters it is given.
We will give it the camera's orthographic size
and a value of .1.
That way if the size drops below .1
we cam instead set it to .1.
Now, if the camera isn't in orthographic mode
then we know it's in perspective mode
and we should instead change the field of view.
We can adjust the field of view by the same amount
but using the perspective zoom speed instead.
We again want to limit the field of view.
However, since the field of view represents an angle
we need to clamp it between 0 and 180.
We do this using the Clamp function of the Mathf class.
This takes 3 values.
First, the value you wish to clamp,
then the minimum value it's allowed to be,
and then the maximum value it's allowed to be.
Our value is the camera's field of view
and we want it to be between .1
and 179.9.
When making your own pinch zoom system
you may want to pick more appropriate limits
for your field of view and orthographic size.
We are using the limits shown in the script
because they are the extremes of what
produces a reasonable result.
That is the end of our script, so now it is time to test it.
We are assuming at this point that you have a device
ready and setup to test.
For instructions on how to do this
consult the device's documentation.
We are now going to build this project
by going to File - Build Settings.
We need to add the current scene to the build.
You may be prompted to save the scene
if you haven't already.
We will then click Build And Run.
As you can see, when we move our fingers together
the camera zooms out.
And when we move them apart we zoom in.