The distance joint 2D component
allows for 2 sprite objects
controlled by 2D rigidbody physics
to be attached together and kept at a certain distance apart.
The distance joint 2D applies a hard limit
rather than a gradual force to maintain
this desired distance.
The connected rigidbody is a reference
to the rigidbody 2D component
on the connected sprite.
If this is left empty, this sprite will be connected
to a point in world space in the scene.
To define the exact position of the pivot point
the properties of Anchor and Connected Anchor need to be set.
These two properties are needed to define
this single pivot point.
The first property, anchor, is the point the sprite
rotates around, relative to the sprite
in local space.
This point does not need to be within the bounds of the sprite.
The second property, connected anchor,
is the point in the scene our sprite is
maintaining a distance from.
And this point is relative to the connected item.
When connected to the world in the scene
these values are in world space.
When connected to another 2D rigidbody
these values are in the connected body's local space.
When rotating around another sprite it is
important to note the collide connected checkbox.
When collide connected unselected
the sprite will ignore collisions with a connected sprite.
To collide with the other sprite make sure that
collide connected is selected.
Distance is the distance between the 2 sprites
being maintained by the joint.
Max distance only will only enforce
a maximum distance.
If deselected the distance between the
objects will be fixed.
It is worth noting the gizmo in the scene view.
A line connects the 2 anchor points.
Perpendicular to this line is a marker
indicating the distance value in the scene.
This is the distance the joint will maintain
between the two sprite objects along this
line between the 2 anchors.
It is possible to have situations where the 2 sprites
are moved in a way that the joint
cannot maintain a fixed distance.
In these situations the 2D physics engine will
apply forces on the sprites until they
reach their fixed distance.