In order to animate the properties of
game objects in Unity we use the
Animator Component.
Animator components have a number of properties
which may differ depending on what you are animating.
For example, a 3D humanoid character
will require different settings than a 2D sprite.
Here we have a scene with a model in it.
The model has an animator component attached.
The first property of the animator component
stores a reference to an animator controller asset.
Animator controllers are Unity generated
assets that contain one or more state machines
which determine which animation is being played
while the scene is running.
These state machines can be on multiple layers
and use parameters of various types.
To affect when they transition between states
and blend.
For example
you can set the parameters of an
animator controller from your scripts to tell it
if the character is running, jumping
or shooting a gun.
It will then play and blend the animation
automatically.
The avatar is an asset that Unity creates
when importing a 3D humanoid.
It contains a definition of the
skeletal rig the character has.
When adding a character of this type to
your scene the avatar field will
automatically be filled in with an asset
created for that character.
Try to think of the avatar as the glue
that binds the model to be animated
to the animator.
For generic objects without skeletal
rigging an avatar is not required.
The Apply Root Motion field
determines whether the animation can affect
the transform of the game object
and is generally used with 3D humanoids.
Root Motion is the core movement
within an animation clip.
For example
imagine the difference between an animation
of a character running on the spot
verses one that is animated running a few
paces forward.
In the latter example
we can use the motion of the character moving
forward to drive the character
around in our game.
Looping that clip to give us realistic
continuous motion.
However, if you simply have
animations that run on the spot
you would uncheck Apply Root Motion
and instead move the character via script.
It is also possible to override this
property entirely.
This is done by creating a script with a
call to the onAnimatorMove function
and attaching it to your game object.
See the documentation link below
for more information on this.
Animate Physics can be either checked
or unchecked.
When it is checked it means that the
animations will be executed in time
with the physics engine.
Generally this is advised
if what ever you are animating
has a rigidbody.
The Culling Mode of an animator effects
whether or not the animations are being played
while they're not being rendered.
Always Animate means that the
animations will play even while not
being rendered.
Based On Renderers means that the
animation will only play while being rendered.
Meaning that when the character is
obscured from view animation will cease
to save performance.
With either option the root motion
is applied as it would normally.
That is if a character was being made
to walk with root motion applied
then they would continue to move even while
not being rendered so that the character
would end up in the correct place
when they became visible again.