The last component that we need for the enemy
is the EnemyAI script.
This class will act as the enemy's brain
and will make decisions based on the information
given to it by other scripts.
Add a new script component to the enemy
called EnemyAI.
Open it for editing as usual and prepare it.
Let's start as usual with the public
variables of the class.
Our enemies are going to have 3 states,
patrolling, chasing and shooting.
They will be stationary whilst shooting
but we will need to allocate a speed
for patrolling and chasing.
2 and 5 should be appropriate defaults for these.
When reaching the last sighting of the player
or the waypoints of their patrol route
enemies will wait for a brief moment.
We need to store the amount of time they wait
when patrolling and when chasing.
The last public variable we will need is
an array of transforms to act as
waypoints for the patrol route of each enemy.
We need several private class variables.
Firstly we need a reference to the
EnemySight script.
Next we need a reference to the nav mesh agent component.
We will also need to know the player's position
so we will need a reference to his transform.
We will need a reference to the PlayerHealth script.
And lastly we will need a reference to the
LastPlayerSighting script.
We need a few more private class variables.
Firstly we need timers for the chase and
patrol wait times.
Finally we need an index to keep track
of which of the array of waypoints is
the enemy's current destination.
Now we will use the Awake function to
setup our references.
Now we will create all the empty functions
we will need so that we can write
calls to them as we proceed.
We will start with Update as that is where
all of our functions will be called.
Next we will have functions to represent
the states of the enemy.
The first is Shooting.
This is the highest priority state
and though it doesn't matter which order
the functions are listed in, it makes more sense
to have the highest priority ones first.
The next highest priority state is Chasing.
Finally our last state is Patrolling.
Now that we have our empty functions let's
return to populate them.
In Update we want to have the conditions
for each of our states and then a call
to the appropriate function.
The highest priority state is Shooting
and we want this to occur if the player
is in sight and is alive.
So the player's health must be greater than 0.
If the enemy is not Shooting then the next
highest priority is Chasing.
We want the enemy to do this if the last
personal sighting of the player is not
the reset position, and if the
player is also alive.
If the enemy is not in either of these
states then the enemy should be Patrolling.
Now that we have the state logic finished
we can populate our State function.
The only thing we want to do when shooting
is to stop the enemy from moving.
We do this using the Stop function of the nav mesh agent.
The rest is handled by the EnemyShooting script.
Next we can move on to the Chasing function.
The first thing we want to do is set a new
destination of the last personal sighting of the player.
However, we only want to do so if the
distance between the enemy and the player
is greater than some small margin.
So first we create a vector from the enemy
to the last personal sighting position.
An appropriate margin is 2
so we will compare the square magnitude
of this vector to a value of 4.
If it is not some small distance away
we will set the nav mesh agents destination.
We want to make sure that the enemy is running
so the nav mesh agent's speed should be
set to the value of chase speed.
Now we need to check if the enemy has
reached it's destination.
To do so we will see if the nav mesh agent's
remaining distance is less
than it's stopping distance.
Once the enemy reaches the last sighting
we want him to wait, so we should start
incrementing the chase timer.
We then need to check if the enemy has
been waiting long enough
and if he has then the enemy will start
his patrol route again to look for the player
To make this happen we need to reset the
global last sighting of the player, as well as
the enemy's personal last sighting of the player.
And since we've stopped waiting we will also
reset the chase timer.
One other thing that we need to do in this function
is state that if we're not near the last
sighting of the player the chase timer should be 0.
This is because the player may be spotted elsewhere
whilst the guard is already in persuite,
meaning that we need to reset to 0.
The patrolling function follows a similar
pattern to chasing. First we need to
get the nav mesh agent's speed appropriately
Now we need to check whether the waypoint
index needs incrementing.
We need to check if the enemy is either near
the destination or has no destination.
The enemy has no destination if
they have just lost track of the player,
signified by last player sighting
being set to the reset position.
Now, similar to the Chasing function,
we need to increment the timer.
As before we check if the enemy has
finished waiting.
This time we need to increment the waypoint
index so that we can set a new destination.
First we check whether we are already at the end
of the array of waypoints and set the
index to 0 if we are.
If we aren't then we increment the index.
And at this point we need to reset the
timer just as in the Chasing function.
Also as before, if we are not near the destination
or the destination is not the reset position
then we need to reset the timer.
Since the rest of the function may have changed
the destintation we can now update it.
That concludes the script, and we've almost
finished making the enemy.
Save it now and return to the Editor.
First let's tidy our script in to the
Scripts - Enemy folder by dragging
it from the Assets folder
in to the Scripts - Enemy folder.
Next let's make a prefab out of our
robot guard so that we can make more guards.
Drag the char_robotGuard from the hierarchy
in to the Prefabs folder in the Project panel.
Now we need to make instances of the
enemy prefab and place them around the scene.
Now that it is a prefab, duplicating
the existing one in the scene will
make another instance.
So let's used command-D on mac or
control-D on PC to create a duplicate
and place it at (-19, 0, 37).
Then find your guard in the scene.
Next duplicate again and place the
new one at (-29, 0, 43.5).
So that there's less confusion we will
rename the robot guards now.
Reselect the first guard near the bottom of the map
and add _001 to the end.
Select the second guard,
and rename him with _002 on the end.
And finally add 3 to the last guard.
The last stage of making the Stealth game
is to create waypoints for the enemies to patrol.
To make it easier we are going to organise
the waypoints under a parent game object.
Create an empty game object and call it wayPoints.
Go to Game Object - Create Empty and rename your object.
Set the position to (0, 0, 0)
so that each of the waypoint's local position
is also the global position.
Duplicate the wayPoints object and rename it
wayPoint_001.
Now make it a child of wayPoints.
Because our waypoints will be made up of
empty game objects we won't be able to see
where they are in the scene view without selecting
them one by one.
To solve this we can use 2D gizmos.
Gizmos are simply icons that represent
where an object is in a scene view.
And you can set these by clicking on the icon
to the left of the name at the top of the Inspector.
With wayPoint_001 selected
click on the game object icon and then choose Other.
Then search for wayPoint
and you'll see an asset in the Project
panel called wayPoint.
This flag icon should be applied to your waypoint.
You can then collapse this menu.
It should look like this flag in the Scene view.
Now we need the rest of the waypoints.
Duplicate wayPoint_001 10 more times
and rename so that each of them has an
individual number. You should end up with
wayPoint_001 to wayPoint_011.
Now that we have all the waypoints we can position
them around the level as we wish.
The first four we are going to use for the
patrol route of robot guard number 1.
The positions for waypoints 001 to 004 are
(-26.75, 0, 7)
(-25.4, 0, 14.5)
(-18.8, 0, 14)
and (-18.5, 0, 7).
Centring on the building on the left hand side
of the map you should see that there are 4
waypoint flags now setup.
Now we need to reposition the final 7 waypoints.
These make up the two patrol routes of the
robot guards near the end of the level.
The next four waypoints have the following positions.
Select wayPoint_005 and position at (-10, 0, 36.4)
wayPoint_006 is at (-10, 0, 44.8)
wayPoint_007 is at (-17.9, 0, 44.8)
wayPoint_008 is at (-17.8, 0, 36.4)
And the last three waypoints have these positions.
wayPoint_009 is at (-27, 0, 35.4)
wayPoint_010 is at (-17.9, 0, 43)
and finally wayPoint_011 is at (-28.2, 0, 43).
Looking at the end of the level you should now
see that our flags are setup as shown.
All that remains is to apply the waypoints
to the appropriate enemies.
First select char_robotGuard_001
and scroll down to the EnemyAI script.
From the hierarchy drag wayPoints 1 to 4
in order on to the Patrol Way Points field
of the EnemyAI script.
They should now appear in order as shown.
Now select guard_002
and drag on waypoints 5 to 8.
And finally guard_003 will need waypoints
9, 8, 10 and 11.
This unusual order is because we
are using one of the same waypoints as guard_002,
so be sure to drag them on in this order.
And don't forget to save your scene
and save your project.
Now that we're finally ready to test our game
we can check for any errors and any
thing that we've forgotten to assign within the project.
Let's press play and test our game.
Remember that our controls for sneak,
using switches and attracting attention
are left-shift, Z and X respectively.
The first thing to notice here is that
as we've died Unity has shown
us an error at the bottom of the screen
An unassigned reference exception,
the variable deathClip of PlayerHealth
has not been assigned.
So what we need to do is fix this before
we continue testing.
So I'll stop play, reselect the player
char_Ethan
and we can see here that deathClip
in the PlayerHeath script has not been assigned.
This is a very common problem when writing
scripts with public variables.
Often you will forget to assign references
and Unity will prompt you to do these are
they are called by a script.
So simply select the Audio folder
and drag the endgame audio clip on to the Death Clip.
Now let's play test again.
And we'll deliberately allow ourselves
to be shot by the guards.
And now we can see that our game
plays back the end clip and resets the level.
Let's continue to play test.
And not that we've reached the end of the game
we've verified that our game works properly.
Congratulations, you've now finished the Stealth project.
If you want, try out the stretch goals
that we've set out in the next assignment.
And we very much hope you've enjoyed this project.
Thanks for watching.