The next stage in creating our enemy
is to create the EnemyShooting script
to control all the aspects of the enemies
firing their guns.
Before we make the script we need to give the
robot a gun. The model we need is
in the Models folder
and is called prop_sciFiGun_low.
Drill down in to the hierarchy of the robot guard
until you find his right hand.
Then zoom with the Scene view until you can see it.
Now drag the gun model from the Project panel
and drop it on to the hand as a child object.
We need to position this gun so that it is in
the right position for when the enemy is
walking and shooting.
We are using a position of (0.1, 0.021, -0.02)
and a rotation of (332, 101.4, 263.8).
These settings will compensate for the position
of the enemies hand when animated normally.
Next we need to make some effects for when the
gun is fired. Create a new game object
and call it fx_laserShot,
and then make it a child of the gun.
Now we can tweak the position of this game object
so that it's at the end of the gun.
We will start by resetting it
and then move the position to (0, 0.05, 0.2).
Now we are going to add a point light
and a line renderer.
These will be triggered when the gun is fired.
To add the light click Add Component
Rendering - Light.
The default type is a point light, which is what we want.
To add the line renderer click Add Component
FX - Line Renderer
A line renderer creates a simple flat
mesh that connects 2 or more points
with a material drawn on to it.
It is ideal for drawing effects like lasers
as we will be. You might notice that by adding
a line renderer we now have a pink
square at the origin. This is because the
line renderer currently has no material.
To fix this search for the material called
fx_laserShot in the Project panel and then drag it on.
Also, in order to give our laser a bit of a
tapered effect we are going to change
the width to 0.05 at the start
and 0.025 at the end.
You can find these settings under the parameter
section of the component.
The point light will mostly be controlled by code
but we will turn the intensity down to 0
to start so that it doesn't interfer with
the lighting in the scene.
We now want to write a script for controlling
all the aspects of the enemy shooting.
Close the enemy's hierarchy and select
the parent object now.
Add a script called EnemyShooting.
Then open it and prepare it as usual.
We are going to make the damage done to the player
scale with proximity.
The closer the enemy is the more damage
it does when shooting the player.
With that in mind there are a few public
class variables that we need to setup.
Firstly we need 2 floats representing the
maximum and minimum damage per shot.
The player has 100 health to start with
and if close enough a single shot should kill the player.
That said, the player should not have to be
right next to the enemy in order to
die from a single shot.
So we will give the maximum damage a
default of 120.
The minimum damage of each shot should still be
significant since we want to encourage
stealth in this game.
Let's give it a default of 45.
Next we will need an audio clip to be
played with each shot.
We are using a point light to help simulate the shot.
We need an intensity for the light as the gun
fires and a speed at which the flash
should diminish.
In addition to those we have a few private
class variables that we will need.
We will need a reference to the animator component.
Since we are referencing the animator we will
need a reference to the HashIDs script.
We have a line renderer and a light
for effects that we will need references to.
To give the enemy a distance range for firing
we will use the radius of the sphere collider
so we will need a reference to that as well.
We need to know the player's position so
we will need a reference to it's transform.
The last reference we need is to the
PlayerHealth script, so that we can call
the TakeDamage function.
Aside from these references we will also need
a Boolean variable to determine whether
or not the enemy is currently shooting.
And finally we are going to use a float
to store the amount of damaged that is scaled.
This will be the difference between the maximum
and minimum damage, this is not essential
but it is slightly neater and makes the
code earier to read.
Now that that's done let's assign our references
in the Awake function as normal.
To find the line renderer we are using a
function called GetComponentInChildren.
This returns a component of the given type,
but looks on a game object and all of it's
child game objects to find it.
It is worth noting that since the laser shot light
and laser shot line are on the same game object
and we already have a reference to the line
we can use the game object it's attached to
to get the reference to the light.
We use a similar principle to find player health
once we have the player transform.
The next commands that we need to add to awake
are to make sure that by default
the laser shot line is disabled
and the laser shot light's intensity is 0.
Lastly we will need to set scaled damage
to the difference between the maximum damage
and the minimum damage.
Next we will look at the Update function.
In Update we need to check the current value
of the shot curve that we used in the enemy's
animator controller, so we will store it
as a float here.
Remember that the EnemyShoot animation
features a curve which begins at 0,
peaks in value when the weapon is fired
and then quickly returns to 0.
We can use the value from this to time our effects.
Now that we have stored the value of this curve
we need to check if it is peaking.
If it is above 0.5
then we can assume that it's peaking.
However we only want to shoot once
so we make sure that it's not already shooting
when we first detect that the curve is peaking.
Next we are going to create our empty Shoot function
so that we can put a call to it here.
The Shoot function should be called once per shot.
We will come back to complete this function shortly.
Next we need to check if the curve is not peaking
and if it is not then we know the enemy
is not shooting.
We should also turn off the line renderer
so that it's not displayed when the enemy
is not shooting.
The last thing we need to do in our update is to
fade out the flash of light when the enemy shoots.
To do that we will use a lerp to fade the
intensity of our laser shot light between itself and 0.
Now we can move on to the Shoot function.
The first thing we need to do in this function is
to say that we are shooting.
The maximum distance at which the enemy
can shoot the player is the radius of his
sphere collider, this is because when the player
is beyond this distance he is no longer in sight.
With this in mind, the next thing we
need to do is to calculate the distance
of the player from the enemy as a fraction of
the sphere collider's radius.
This should be a number that equals 1 when
the distance from the enemy to the player is 0
and when the player is at the edge of the collider,
the maximum range, the number should equal 0.
This is calculated by finding the difference
between the collider's radius and
the distance from the enemy to the player
and dividing by the collider's radius.
Next we need to calculate the damage that the
player will take, that is, the amount
of damage to be scaled multiplied by the
fractional distance plus the minimum damage.
Now we can call the TakeDamage function from
the PlayerHealth script and parse in the
amount of damage we have calculated.
Finally we will need to display the visual
effects of the shot, but instead of
putting that here we will put it in to a separate
function called ShotEffects and call it here.
First we need to set the start position of
the line renderer to be at the end of the gun,
which is already the position of our
fx_laserShot game object
and we need to set the end position to
be where the player is.
We do this using the SetPosition function.
The first parameter is an integer representing
the point of the line, 0 being the first point,
1 being the second, etsetera.
The second parameter is a vector3
representing the position in world space
of where the point should be.
Instead of using only the player's position here
we are adding the value of Vector3.up times 1.5.
This is because the player's position is at
the model's feet so we need to add some height
so that the enemy shoots at his abdomen instead.
Next we need to turn the laser shot line
on by enabling the component.
We need to set the intensity of the laser shot light
to the flash intensity.
Finally we need to play the Shot clip
at the position of the laser shot.
Now we can put a call to the ShotEffects function
inside our Shoot function.
Before we are finished with this script we need
to make the enemy point the gun at the player
when he's shooting. We are going to do this
by using inverse kinematics,
which is deal with in the OnAnimatorIK function.
We will define it just below the Update function.
The first thing we want to do in this function
is to store the value of the Aim Weight curve that is
on the Raise, Shoot and Lower weapon animations.
Next we want to set the IK positions
using the SetIKPosition function of the animator.
The first parameter of this function is
an enumeration called AvatarIKGoal.
An enumeration is a collection of named constants
and the one we will be using will be the right hand.
The second parameter is the position
that the right hand should be aiming at.
We will be using the player's position
plus 1.5 units up
Again this is because the player's transform
is at his feet so in order to hit him around
the centre we need to aim up slightly.
Lastly we need to set the weight for the IK.
We do this using SetIKPositionWeight.
Again the first parameter is an
AvatarIKGoal to say where we are applying the weight.
So we will use the right hand enumeration again.
The second parameter is the weight, which we
stored earlier as the AimWeight.
That's the end of our script so we can save
it now and return to the Editor.
We will reselect the char_robotGuard
and on the Shot clip open the Audio folder
and drag on weapon_sciFiGun_fire.
Also remember that because we created this
script directly on the object it will
currently be in the root of Assets.
So drag and drop this in to our Scripts - Enemy folder.
Then you can save the scene and save the project.
In the next and final assignment we will
be going through making the EnemyAI script,
the brain of the robot guards.