Here's a quick Unity tip.
When you're working in Unity and you want to find a game object in the Hierarchy
With a specific component or script attached
You can type the Full Case Sensitive Name in the Hierarchy search
Notice that the object will not appear until the full name has been completed
Here we can see that we've found our game object 'Player'
Which has the dummy script 'FindMe' attached
You can also use this technique to find attached Unity components - in this case, the Animator
As we can see, the Player object also has an Animator component attached
Which we have found, by searching in the Hierarchy for it's name