A quick tip for Unity.
If you're working with public variables that are
exposed in the inspector,
such as this Speed variable in our PlayerMovement script,
you may wish to turn them in to a slider
instead of simply a float value that you can type in to.
You can do this very easily.
In your script simply place above the
public variable range declaration
which looks like this;
Open square brackets and type Range,
and then in to normal brackets type in
the two float values that you'd like the slider to go to and from.
So for example with my player's speed
I might want to have a minimum value of  1
and a maximum value of 10.
That way I can limit any kind of
game designer that plays around with this script
from going over the potential maximum value.
I save my script and switch back.
And as soon as the script compiles I now have a slider
to play around with the speed.