Here's a quick tip for Unity.
In Unity, its common to use empty game objects for spawn points, and other invisible objects in our scene
Here we have an empty game object called Spawn Point which currently only has a Transform component
When we have the object highlighted in the Hierarchy, it's easy to see.
but when we deselect it, it becomes completely invisible
to solve this, we can assign our empty game object a custom icon
the icon menu is in the upper left corner of the Inspector
by click on it, we can choose a panel icon
which will show the object's name against a coloured panel
we can choose a small circular icon of various colours
a diamond
or we can click Other to choose a custom icon
Here I will assign the default particle texture as the icon
Now when we deselect the object
we can see that the icon causes it to remain visible
these icons will not be visible in the Game view, unless the 'Gizmos' toggle is turned on