A quick tip for finding assets for your game
is to use the project panel to search the assets store.
So if you're looking through your project thinking
'I don't really have the assets that I need'
for example I might search for 'zombie'
when I've only really got some zombears.
Then we can just simply use the toggle
below the search field.
So you'll see Search, it'll say Assets.
If you flip this to Asset Store
and then search for what you want, for example Zombie.
You'll find all of the results on the store
and you can select them, you can
move your preview, you can have a look around them,
you can import that package, you ca do all that kind of stuff.
So it's a quick way to browse the assets store without
opening the store and looking through the categories there.