Here's a quick tip for moving objects
around by defined increments.
So you can snap objects by holding
command on Mac or control on PC,
and they'll move in defined increments.
For example if I drag this now holding the command key
I can move it around.
You can set these increments by going to Edit
Snap Settings and define how many units you want things to move by
And you can see from this panel that the same goes
for scaling and rotation.
Holding command will move
those defined amount of degrees at a time.
If you want to snap by vertex
you can hold down the V key
and then drag a particular vertex of your model
to a vertex on the environment.
This is more useful when snapping together
modular parts of an environment.