A quick Unity tip.
When you're working in the editor
it's easy to forget that you're in play mode,
and what can happen is that when you're
adjusting values of game objects,
when you leave play mode those settings can be forgotten.
So it's quite useful to be able to remind yourself
of being in play mode, and you can do this using tinting.
So if you go to Unity Preferences on Mac,
or Edit Preferences on PC
you can go to the Colours section
and in there you'll find Playmode tint.
Simply set this to a colour that's kind of
obvious and will stick out
and then the editor will entirely tint
to this colour when you're in play mode
to remind you. It looks like this.