A quick tip for positioning cameras in Unity.
So it can be painful to select cameras
and use the transform controls to
kind of move them around.
It's much easier to actually use the
scene view camera to get the actual
frame that you want with the camera
and then move the camera to that position.
For example I can move my scene view camera around
like this, I could use right-click,
and look around and then use the
cursor keys to kind of move that around,
get the exact shot that I want,
then select the camera
and go to Game Object
Align With View.
That then puts the camera exactly where you want it.
You've also got the ability to jump the scene
view camera back to that position if you've
left it and you want to kind of re-evaluate.
You can go back to Game Object - Align View To Selected.
That will take you back.
So remember, get the scene view camera to where
you want it, command-shift-F or control-shift-F,
to reposition it.
Or if you want to go back and start reevaluating
if you've moved away use Align View To Selected.