We're making a space game and space is, well, black.
But flat black is boring.
So let's add a background to our game.
First, let's begin by deactivating our player
game object, it will simply be in the way for now.
Next create a quad to hold our
background image by selecting Create - Quad
from the Hierarchy's Create menu.
Rename this Background.
Where is it?
We've created a quad, but we can't see it in our game.
Let's switch to the Scene view to see what's going on.
There it is, it's oriented in a way
that's not facing the main camera.
The main camera can't see it.
To adjust this let's first reset
the game object's transform to make sure
it is at origin
and then let's change the background's
transform rotation along the X axis.
Let's set this value to 90 degrees.
Now the background quad is facing
towards our main camera.
and we can see it now in the game view.
I'm going to switch back to the Scene view.
The stock quad comes with a
component we don't need.
We can safely remove the mesh collider
component as we won't be using it.
Next, let's add a texture to this background.
In Assets there is a directory called Textures.
Inside Textures we will find an image
tile_nebula_green.
Let's select this image.
When we select an image and inspect it
we are looking at that image's importer
We will leave the importer settings as they are.
But if the preview window is open
we can some additional information about this image.
If the preview window is collapsed
we can drag the bar titled Preview upwards
until we see the image clearly.
The information at the bottom of the Preview window
tells us the current resolution of the
image in our project, the current compression method,
if any, and the total size of the imported image.
What is important for us to note here is that
this is a very large image.
1024 by 2048.
So this image is more than large enough to stretch
behind our 600 by 900 game view.
This is also telling us that the image is not square
but rectangular.
There are a number of ways that we can get
a texture on to a mesh.
Let's try one of the most simply ways.
Grab the image, drag it,
and drop it on the background quad in the scene.
Done!
Let's get a better view of our background.
Use Frame Selected to focus the
Scene view camera
The image has been applied to the background quad.
It's dark and squashed but it's there.
What just happened?
We can see that the texture has been attached
to a material and the material has been
associated with the quad by a reference
in the mesh renderer.
Our mesh filter holds the mesh data,
in this case the quad.
The mesh renderer renders that mesh using
the materials in the mesh renderer's Materials Array.
The renderer is only able to use a texture
if it's part of a material.
We did not create a material, we simply
dragged the texture on to the quad.
It was Unity that created the material for us.
When we drag a texture on to a mesh,
if Unity cannot find an associated material
with that texture Unity will create
a new material for us.
Then Unity will automatically add that material
to that mesh renderer's Materials Array.
This automatic material will always
with the default diffuse shader.
Let's look at our background.
Is it ready to go? No.
It's small, square, squashed,
a bit dark and a little hard to see.
The first thing we need to do is scale up
our quad to fit our background.
We can do this by changing the
transform's Scale properties.
The quad is a very simple 2 dimensional plane.
We can scale the quad along the X and Y axis,
but not along the Z axis.
Trying to scale the Z axis does nothing.
Let's reset the scale now that we've played with it.
What scale should we use?
Let's first look at the texture itself.
It's 1024 by 2048.
To keep the image undistorted when we scale it up
we should keep an aspect ratio of 1:2.
This means our X scale should always be
half of our Y scale.
Or conversely our Y scale must always
be twice our X.
To see this properly in the game let's
switch back to the Game view.
In the Game view select the background quad
and scale it along the X axis
until it fills the screen.
It's more than filling the screen when we use
a scale value of 12 or more.
We have enough resolution that we can afford
to lose some of the image off the sides.
So let's pick a good round number,
like 15. It's more than big enough.
So that we can maintain our 1:2 aspect ratio
what is 15 times 2? 30.
If we have 15 in our X we need 30 in our Y.
Now the background fills the game view
with no distortion.
Let's look at it in the Scene view.
Use Frame Selected to focus the
Scene view camera to the background's new size.
and we can see that we now have a nice big background.
The background is still a bit too dark
The material is using a simple diffuse shader.
This means that the texture is being treated like
a simple painted surface using matt,
not glossy paint.
The surface of our background is being lit
by the lights in our scene.
These lights have been setup to light our player ship.
1 light, the rim light, is shining up
from below and won't light the surface
of the background at all.
The other 2 have very shallow angles
that only rake the surface of the quad.
So our background isn't receiving very
much light from our lighting rig.
This is great for our player ship
but not so great for our background.
We could add a light shining straight
down to light the background.
But this would add another light to the ship
lighting it in a way that we wouldn't want.
We could put the background and it's new light
on a separate layer so that the background
light did not mix with out existing lights
on the player ship.
But there is a better way.
For more information on layers and how to use them
see the information linked below.
If we think about our background image
we simply want to have it display
behind our game.
It's a flat plane, we do not need specialised
lighting like we need for our ship
and it's a waste to shine a directional light
on a simply quad just to flat light it's contents.
When dealing with a material,
how that material treats the texture
depends upon what shader we choose.
Diffuse treats the texture like matte paint.
The specular shader will treat that texture
like glossy paint, or shiny plastic.
There are many other built-in shaders
that come with Unity.
More can be found on the Asset Store
and we can write our own custom shaders.
For more information on shaders
see the information linked below.
For our purposes we don't need any
specialised lighting on our background.
As a matter of fact we don't need any lighting at all.
For our background, let's change the shader.
Let's choose Unlit - Texture
for the shader on the nebula material.
Now our background is independent
of our lighting system, and it displays
the texture exactly as it looks
in the original image
and it uses no lights at all.
In the game it's nice and bright.
If we change the shader back to diffuse
we can see how much darker it is in the game.
Let's bring back our player and check that
everything looks good in context
now that we have a background in place.
Okay, something's wrong with our ship.
Let's look at it in the Scene view
to see what's going on.
Ah, the player ship is buried
in the middle of the background,
they are both at origin.
The background should be behind the game.
So let's grab the background and adjust it.
along the Y axis.
We can slide it in to a good position by hand
or we can simply set the transform position
on the Y axis to -10.
Now the background is down and out of the way.
When we look back at the game we can't
see any change to the background,
except for the fact that it is no longer
in the middle of our space ship.
This is due to the fact that our camera
is orthographic and has no perspective.
The background can be any distance from the
camera as long as it's within it's clipping plane
and still look exactly the same.
We have now setup our background and our lighting.
Next let's begin to create game play elements
by moving the player ship.