Our game is complete.
Let's build a web player and deploy
that web player on to the web.
Open the Build Settings window.
The Build Settings has two main sections.
The bottom part for setting the build target
and customising details for the build
and the upper part for selecting the
scenes to build in to the game.
We do not need to include every scene in our
project when we build our game.
We only need to select the scenes we want.
We can either drag the scenes we want
from our Project view and drop them
in to the upper window
or we can click the Add Current button
to add the current open scene to the
build window.
As a side note, we can build a game
with no scenes in the Scenes To Build window.
If we do this Unity will temporarily use
the current open scene when building.
Once we have selected the scenes to build
it is always good practice to check our
player settings before we actually build the game.
For more information on player settings
please see the information linked below.
When we are satisfied with our player settings
we can return to the Build Settings window
and choose Build.
Unity will open a dialogue box
prompting us for a name and location
for our new build.
I like to keep the builds associated with
the project, so let's create a new folder
to hold our build.
We will create this folder in the root of our
project along side the assets
library and other default folders.
It is important to note that this new folder
should not be placed inside any of
the default folders.
Create a new folder in our project
and call it Builds.
Save the folder.
With the Builds folder selected
let's name our build Space_Shooter.
We use the underscore here in the name
as we will be deploying to the web
and this name will be part of the web
address or URL for the game.
Spaces are not recommended in
a web address or URL.
So we should use an underscore, dash or
other web friendly character instead of
spaces here when we are creating a web build.
It should be noted that we could,
if we chose to,
change the name of the HTML file to
index.html if appropriate
to shorten the length of the URL.
When we have named our build select Save.
Unity will now build our player.
And when the build is done
Unity will open the target folder,
in this case our Builds folder,
revealing the built game.
We have built a web player.
Open the Space_Shooter folder.
The web player comes in 2 parts.
A Unity 3D file, which contains the data
and an HTML file which describes the page
that will play the game data in a window.
If we look at the size of these 2 files
we can see that the Unity 3D file is the
larger of the 2 as it contains the game data.
If we select and open the HTML file
our operating system will load the HTML file
in to our default browser.
And the game will play in the web page.
We are playing this game locally.
To play this game globally we need to
upload it to a web host of some sort.
As an example I am going to upload this
via an FTP client to an existing website.
Open an FTP client, select a destination
and upload both the HMTL and data files
into the same directory.
In this case, for ease, I'm going to
upload the entire folder containing both files.
When the files are uploaded open a browser
and use the URL to open a new web page.
The data will load from the web
and we're playing the game globally.
Anyone anywhere in the world with access
to the internet can play our game.
Fantastic.
Thank you for taking these assignments,
following along and making this game.
Please check out the Learn section of Unity's
website for more information,
tutorials, assignments and learning materials.