So we have a tumbling asteroid hazard
and we can destroy it with our laser bolts.
But the entire process seems a bit dull.
So let's add some explosions to brighten things up.
Let's open our DestroyByContact script.
The first thing we need to do is add a reference
to our explosion visual effect.
So let's write public GameObject explosion
then after our boundary detection code
write instantiate.
We know instantiate, we've used it in
our Player Controller script.
Let's open our Player Controller script.
And copy the instantiate line.
Paste it in to our DestroyByContact script.
What do we want to instantiate?
Our explosion.
Where do we want to instantiate it?
At our transform position with our
transform rotation applied.
This will instantiate the explosion
at the exact same position as our asteroid.
Save this script and return to Unity.
In the Prefabs folder is VFX Explosions.
Drag the explosion_asteroid on to the
Explosion slot to create a reference to it
on our DestroyByContact script.
Save the scene and enter Play mode.x
Now when we destroy the asteroid we get a
very pretty explosion.
Let's see that again.
Nice.
On the other hand
If we ram the asteroid with our ship
We only get that same explosion.
Now that's a little sad.
Let's improve this script to accommodate
the player as a special case and include
a player explosion as well as
the asteroid explosion.
Return to our DestroyByContact script.
Let's add a public GameObject reference
to our playerExplosion.
Then let's duplicate our instantiate code
and again, what do we want to instantiate?
Our playerExplosion.
And where do we want to instantiate it?
Where our player, as the other collider
is in our scene, or the Other
transform position and the Other
transform rotation.
Leaving the code like this would simply
instantiate 2 explosions with every
OnTriggerEnter event.
Let's test the Other collider again.
Indent the new instantiate code and write
If the other collider's tag is the
same as Player
and add an open bracket.
And after the instantiate line we will
need to complete this with a close bracket.
We will now always instantiate our explosions
but if we collide with an object tagged Player
we will also instantiate a player
explosion as well.
Save this script and return to Unity.
Our player now needs a tag.
Using the Tag drop-down menu select the
pre-made tag Player.
There is no need to create a custom tag in this case.
Select the Asteroid game object
and drag the explosion_player on to the
Player Explosion slot on the
DestroyByContact component.
Save the scene and play.
Wow, that's great.
The last improvement we need to make on the
asteroid is to get it moving towards the player
With the Asteroid selected
open the Scripts folder and drag the
Mover script on to the Asteroid
game object in the Inspector.
The Mover script is the movement
code we created when we were moving the bolt
game object in an earlier assignment.
Then set the speed value to -5.
This negative speed will bring the asteroid
down the screen towards our player.
Save the scene, enter Play mode and test.
And the asteroid tumbles towards our player.
Conveniently the boundary also takes care
of the asteroid when it leaves the boundary's
box by destroying it.
Exit Play mode.
The asteroid hazard is done.
We need to save this as a prefab
So drag the asteroid game object from the
Hierarchy on to the Prefabs folder in Assets.
This creates a new prefab of our
Asteroid game object.
Lastly delete the instance of
the asteroid from our scene.
Our asteroid hazard is setup and ready to go.
In the next assignment we will create
our game controller.