Now that our project is setup and ready
to go let's setup the player game object.
First I'm going to make sure that I'm in the Scene view
for the best view of the scene we are working with.
Next I'm going to add the player's ship model.
We can find the player ship in the Assets
folder in the Models directory.
Drag the vehicle_playerShip
from the Models directory in to the Hierarchy view.
We can also drag this model directly in to the
Scene view if we choose to.
Either way is correct.
Let's get a better view of the model in our scene.
To do this we want to focus, or frame the
selected game object with the Scene view camera.
We can do this by either choosing Edit - Frame Selected
or by using the hot-key F
while the pointer is in the Scene view.
Double clicking on the game object in the Hierarchy view
will also focus the Scene view camera.
There's our player ship.
Now that she's in the scene, let's rename her
in the Hierarchy. Click on the game object in the hierarchy and
type either the Return or Enter key to enable editing.
We can also click on the game object
twice, slowly, to enable editing as well.
Name the game object Player
and then hit Enter or Return to confirm that change.
We want our player ship to be at origin.
Origin is the centre of our 3 dimensional scene
where the X, Y and Z coordinates are (0, 0, 0).
Let's use the context sensitive gear menu
in the upper right of the Transform component
and select Reset.
This will reset the transform's position,
rotation and scale.
Now we have guaranteed that the model is
placed perfectly at origin.
We want this ship to fly around, fight enemies
yet be vulnerable enough that we can be destroyed
if we're not careful as we pilot our ship.
We currently have nothing more than a mesh model
that represents the player in our scene.
The game object that holds our ship
has a number of components that define
what our ship is and where it is in the game.
The game object uses a mesh filter
to hold our mesh model
and a mesh renderer to render the ship
in our scene.
The renderer references 2 materials,
shown here at the bottom for our convenience.
The game object uses the information in
the transform component to know where the
model is in the game, what direction it is facing
and what scale it currently is.
To set up our player game object we will
be adding more components that perform
specialised functions, and we will be creating
our own components using simple scripting.
We will be moving our ship using physics,
though with an arcade style
and we need physics to detect our collisions
between the player and other game objects
in the scene.
To use physics we need to add a rigid body component.
I'm going to quickly reduce the view of these
referenced materials by clicking on
the header bars so that it's easier to
see and access the Add Component
button without scrolling.
Now let's click on Add Component
and select Physics - Rigid Body.
This attaches a rigid body component
to our game object.
By default the rigid body assumes
we want to use gravity, and well, we're in space
and we don't want to fall out of the game
so let's deselect Use Gravity.
With the rigid body attached our game object
now uses the built in physics engine.
To detect collisions the physics engine
through the rigid body, needs to know the
volume of our objects.
We need to know how much space these objects
take up in our game to calculate the collisions.
We give this information to the rigid body by
using a cage that we wrap around our game objects.
This cage defines the volume of that object.
The cage is called a Collider.
Let's use the Add Component button again.
This time select Physics - Capsule Collider.
This puts a simple cage around our player game object.
This looks like a sphere but that's because
a capsule collider is defined by 2 spheres
and the space in between them,
and we are seeing both spheres in the same place.
Let's change the capsule collider's size.
The default orientation for a capsule collider
is up and down or along the Y axis.
This is to fit a humanoid object.
Our ship is longest along the Z axis
so let's change the direction to Z
and reduce the radius and increase the height.
For a better view let's change our orientation.
For a top-down view let's click on the
Scene view gizmo and click on the Y arm.
In this view it's easier to fine tune the shape.
We simply need to choose the values
for radius and height that comfortably fit
the collider to our model.
Now for the purposes of this game,
which is fairly simple, the capsule collider is sufficient.
There are other alternatives however.
Let's click on the Add Component button again
and select Physics.
There is the Box Collider and Sphere Collider as well.
The box collider and sphere colliders are
2 other primitive colliders like the
capsule collider, but there is a more complex
collider called a Mesh Collider
where we can supply the collision mesh ourselves.
For more information see the documentation
on colliders and the lesson on
colliders linked below.
At this point I think it's important to note
that the primitive colliders, the box,
sphere and capsule are far more performant
and should be used whenever possible
over the mesh collider.
For more information please see the
Compound Colliders section of the
Rigid Body documentation linked below.
If however we have a more complex shape that
can't be accommodated by any of the primitive colliders
and for some reason doesn't work by using
a compound collider we can select Mesh Collider.
Let's look at the mesh collider in action.
Select Mesh Collider and yes,
replace the existing component.
This will remove the capsule collider and
use the mesh collider instead.
To have a better look at the mesh collider
let's turn off the mesh renderer.
This reveals the green lines of the mesh collider
that were hidden underneath the rendered mesh.
We can see how complex this cage is.
Unity must check the position of each
triangle in the cage relative to
the other colliders in the scene
to properly detect a collision.
If for whatever reason we use a mesh collider
rather than a primitive collider
it is best that we use a simplified mesh.
The mesh collider holds a reference to the
mesh it's using in the Mesh slot
on the component.
By default Unity will use the mesh
in the mesh filter if one is present.
We can simply swap this out with a new
simplified mesh of our choice.
We have supplied a simplified mesh in the Models directory.
Open the Model file and select the Mesh asset.
Drag the Mesh asset in to the Mesh slot
on the mesh collider.
Now we can see the substantially simplified
mesh being used as the collider.
Let's turn the mesh renderer back on.
For the purposes of this game we could use a
capsule collider, but this game will be
simple enough to absorb the larger cost
of the mesh collider, so let's leave it as it is.
Now that we have a working collider,
we need to adjust the collider's settings.
For this game we don't need to
or want to detect full physics collisions.
We simply need our collisions to trigger an action.
So select Is Trigger,
making this a Trigger Collider.
Lastly, let's add a little sizzle to our ship.
In Prefabs - VFX - Engines
there is an engines_player prefab.
Let's add this to the player ship.
Drag the prefab on to the player ship
in the Hierarchy to add it as a
child game object.
The Engines prefab consists of 2 particle systems.
Now they look funny in the Scene view,
as the particles are billboarding
or facing to the camera at all times.
If however we are in top-down mode
like our game will be they look just fine.
If the gizmos in the scene are too large
we can reduce them by selecting the gizmos
button in the Scene view toolbar
and adjusting the slider.
Now our player ship is setup.
In the next assignment we will setup the
camera and the lights.