In Unity it's possible to control the
volume of one element in your audio mix
based on the volume of another.
This is called ducking and we achieve this
using the Duck Volume effect.
I've got a simple scene setup here with
three musical parts, a kick drum,
bass line and arpeggio, these are all assigned
to game object which have
audio source component which are assigned
to different outputs in our audio mixer.
The kick has it's own group
and the synthesisers, the bass line and
arpeggio are both routed
to the synthesiser group.
What we're going to do is we're going to cause
the volume of the synthesisers to duck
based on the volume of the kick drum when it strikes.
This is also called side chain compression.
To begin I'm going to add a duck volume effect
using the Add drop down menu.
Now that the duck volume effect has been added
I'm going to send some audio signal to it
and I'm going to do this using the Send effect.
I'm going to click Add and choose Send.
Now in the inspector
I'm going to choose the bus
for the send to be routed to.
In this case that's going to be
synthesisers duck volume.
Now that we've setup our routing
we're going to set the send level.
Because the input
on the duck volume effect does not route
it's signal back to the main volume
we can turn up this send without
adding any volume to our mix.
This is a typical behaviour for a side
chain input on a compressor.
With the volume turned all the way up
now the full amplitude of our
kick will reach the duck volume effect when it plays.
Let's listen to the scene first.
Now even though we've configured our scene
we're still not hearing any gain reduction
from the duck volume.
If we click on the duck volume effect
we can configure it's parameters.
The threshold is the volume at which
gain reduction will begin to occur.
So our input signal, in this case
our kick drum, will need to exceed a
threshold of -10 decibels
before we start to apply any gain reduction.
Let's listen to that in action.
We're going to play
turn on Edit In Play Mode so that we can
change the parameters
and we're going to slowly reduce the threshold.
And so you can hear as we reduce the
threshold we start to hear that
pumping breathing effect
because the amplitude of the kick drum
is now causing our duck volume effect
to lower the amplitude
or volume of the synthesiser group.
Now we can move on to our next parameter,
which is called the ratio.
The ratio determines how much gain reduction
will be applied once
the threshold is triggered.
One easy way to think about this is that
it's the amount of gain reduction which is
applied once the threshold is exceeded.
Next we have the attack time and the release time.
The attack time is once the threshold
has been triggered, how quick is the onset
of the gain reduction?
The release time is the opposite.
Once the attack phase is completed,
so in this case after 26 milliseconds,
the release time begins to release
the compression or the gain reduction.
And so in this case after 100 milliseconds
we will no longer be reducing volume
so we'll be back to our original signal strength.
The makeup gain is simply an
additional volume control
that allows us to make back up
some of the gain that we've reduced.
In this case because we want to have a
pronounced ducking effect where we hear the volume
getting quieter we're going to leave the makeup
gain at 0, which means that no change
in volume is going to be applied.
The knee controls the behaviour of the threshold.
At a very low or hard knee
we're going to get a linear transition
from once the threshold is crossed
we're going to begin applying gain.
If we increase the knee value or soften it,
we're going to see that we're going to have a
much more smooth transition
as the gain reduction is applied.
And it's actually possible at high knee values,
as you can see from the graph changing,
to begin reducing gain even before
the threshold has been tripped.
As we approach the threshold at a soft knee value
we're going to begin to see some gain reduction
even before we've exceeded the threshold.
The side chain mix allows us to blend
between the effected
and the unaffected signal.
At 100% we're listening to
only the signal which is being
processed by the duck volume.
At 0 we're going to be listening to
only the original signal.
In addition to being able to adjust the parameters
via the sliders we can also
adjust the parameters by clicking directly
on the graphic.
If we click on the white line here representing
threshold we can actually drag horizontally
to adjust the threshold value.
By dragging vertically we can adjust the knee
and you'll see we have this nice representation
of how the knee is effecting the threshold.
If we drag to the left of the line we can
adjust the makeup gain
and if we drag to the right of the line we can
adjust the ratio.