Welcome to part 2 of
upgrading the Nightmares survival shooter project
from Unity 4 to Unity 5.
If you missed part 1 please check that out
before continuing with this video.
In this version of the Nightmares project
we have a pause menu that's been
created with the new UI system.
The pause menu is called up when you press
escape using a script called
Pause Manager, which is attached to menu canvas.
We'll look at this script in more detail
later in the video.
For more information about creating
this type of UI see the information linked below.
Before moving on to scripting we want
to do one more thing in our mixer.
We want to expose the volume
of the music group and the sound effects group
to script control so that we can set them directly
without using the snapshot system.
We'll click on the music group,
right click on the volume parameter
and choose Expose To Script.
We're also going to do this for the sound effects group.
Now in our exposed parameters list
we're going to name these two parameters.
We're going to call our first exposed parameter
musicVol
and our second
sfxVol.
To rename the parameters double click
on the parameter names.
Now that we've got the audio setup
in our project we're going to move on
to adding some scripting control.
Let's start by editing the pause manager script.
We're going to go to the menu canvas game object
and then double click on the pause manager script
to open it in mono develop.
Let's just quickly review what we have here.
We've added the name space declaration
using UnityEngine.UI
because we're using some of the functions
from the UI system including the canvas
variable type.
We're also checking if we're currently
running in the Unity editor
and if so we're adding the name space declaration
using Unity editor.
We've declared a variable of the canvas type
called Canvas, and this is the UI canvas.
In the start function we're getting a reference
to that using getComponent.
In our update function we're checking
to see if the escape key has been pressed.
If escape has been pressed
we'll flip the canvas from enabled to disabled
or visa versa.
We'll also call the pause function.
In the pause function we're setting
Time.TimeScale
We're doing this by checking if it's currently
set to 0, set it to 1
and otherwise set it to 0.
By setting Time.TimeScale to 0
we can freeze the motion of all of
the objects in our game.
We also have a public function called Quit
in which we're checking if we're using
the Unity editor we're going to do
EditorApplication.isPlaying=false
meaning it's going to stop playing the scene.
Or else we're going to call
Application.Quit
meaning if this was the build of our application
it would actually quit out to the desktop.
What we're going to do is we're going to
add some stuff to this script
to allow it to control
our audio mixer.
The first thing that we're going to add is another
name space declaration
using UnityEngine.Audio.
This is going to allow us to access
members of UnityEngine.Audio including the
audio mixer and the audio mixer snapshot classes.
We're going to add 2 public variables
of the audio mixer snapshot type.
We're going to call these Paused
and Unpaused.
These are going to correspond to the snapshots
that we created in the first video.
We're going to add a new public function under Paused.
We're going to call this function Lowpass.
In low pass we're going to check if
Time.TimeScale is currently equal to 0.
If Time.TimeScale is equal to 0
we're going to call the TransitionTo function
from the Paused snapshot.
We're going to parse in a floating point parameter
time to reach,
in this case 0.01 seconds.
If Time.TimeScale does not equal 0
we're going to call TransitionTo from
the Unpaused snapshot.
With our low pass function declared
we're now going to call it from inside
the pause function.
Let's save our script and return to Unity.
In the editor we'll see that our
pause manager script now has
2 new variables, Paused and Unpaused.
We're going to set those to our audio mixer
snapshots we created earlier using the asset picker.
We'll select the Paused snapshot
and the Unpaused snapshot.
Let's play our scene and give it a try.
Press escape and see that the paused snapshot
has been recalled, and then when we click resume
we can see that Unpaused has been recalled,
and so we can hear that it's working.
In the Paused menu
we have volume controls for the music
and for the sound effects.
We're going to use those to control our audio mixer
using scripting. Let's start by creating a new C# script
which we'll call Mix Levels.
We'll double click it to open it in mono develop.
Again the first thing we're going to start by doing
is adding the name space declaration
using UnityEngine.Audio.
Next we're going to add a public variable
of the audio mixer type called Master Mixer.
Because we won't need either the update
or the start functions we're going to delete those.
We're going to declare a public function called
SetSfxLvl.
We're going to give SetSfxLvl a
parameter of the type float
called sfxLvl.
We're going to use the sfxLvl
parameter to parse a floating point value
to master mixer and use
that to change the volume
of our sound effects level in our audio mixer.
We're going to do this using the SetFloat function.
SetFloat takes two parameters.
A string, which is the name
of the exposed parameter that we want to set.
And a floating point parameter to set the value.
We're going to parse in the string sfxVol
which is the name of the parameter that we
exposed earlier in the inspector.
We're also going to declare a second public function
called SetMusicLvl.
SetMusicLvl is also going to take
a floating point parameter, in this case called
musicLvl.
In SetMusicLvl we're also going to use SetFloat
to set the value of our exposed parameter musicVol.
Let's save our script and return to the editor.
In the editor let's add our
Mix Level script to
our menu canvas game object.
We're also going to select
our audio mixer master mixer
as the master mixer variable.
Next, in the paused panel
we're going to choose our effects
slider game object.
In the slider script you'll see that
previously onValueChanged was
changing the value of the gun barrel end
and the player audio sources directly.
Now we can reconnect those to our audio mixer.
First we're going to drag in our menu canvas.
We're going to choose from our list of functions
found on this game object
our mix level script
and we're going to choose the SetSfxLvl function
from that script.
We can remove the connection to the player audio
source by selecting it and hitting -.
We're going to do the same thing for our music slider.
Drag in our menu canvas game object.
Choose from our list of functions, in this case
mix levels, set music level.
Because we determined that -10
decibels was probably the loudest
we wanted our music to be in the mixer
we're going to set that in the max value in the slider.
We're also going to set the minimum value
to -80, which will be silent.
In the effects slider we're going to do the same thing
except it's going to be between -80
and 0.
With that setup let's play our scene
and give it a try.
We'll hit escape,
adjust the music volume,.
Let's pull down the sound effects volume too.
So there we have it.
For more information about audio mixers,
snapshots, exposed parameters and effects
see the information linked below.