The Standard Shader is a powerful and versatile shader,
This single physically-based shader
can be used to make such a wide variety
of materials it's easily
possible that this one shader can make
every material in a given project.
The standard shader is used to create Unity's default material.
So all mesh renderers using
the default material will be using the standard shader.
All new materials that are created
will use the standard shader as well.
To change the shader used by a material
select the Shader menu on the material.
Select Standard to use the standard shader.
This physically-based material is
still a standard Unity material
and this material is associated
with a renderer in the same way as usual.
There are three sections to the standard shader.
Rendering Mode.
Main Maps
and Secondary Maps.
The standard shader has three rendering modes.
Opaque, Cutout and Transparent.
Most materials are opaque, or solid materials.
Opaque is the default render mode.
For transparent materials, such as glass,
choose Transparent.
In transparent rendering mode
the alpha channel on the diffuse colour property
is used to control the level of transparency.
With rendering mode 'Cutout'
the alpha channel of the diffuse image
is used to mask out parts of the texture.
If the alpha channel has a gradient value to the mask
the alpha cutoff slider can be used
to adjust the shape of the cutout.
based on the strength of the mask in the alpha channel.
The Main Map section defines the look of the material.
Before going in to the details of each property
there are a few subjects that are worth covering first.
Optimisation.
The standard shader is highly optimised.
When the standard shader is built
two important things happen.
All properties that are not being used are discarded.
The build target is checked
and the shader is optimised for that device.
Because of this there is no need to populate every
property with a map or values.
And there is no need to worry about wasted
resources due to unused properties.
Physically-based shading.
Physically-based shading is a different approach to materials
compared to previous versions of Unity.
Physically-based shading tries to define
certain physical aspects of a material's surface.
Including it's diffuse colour,
specular refection and other properties
so the material behaves correctly,
and believably in all lighting environments.
The response of the scene lighting to the material
created with a physically-based shader
mimics light in the real physical world.
This means that even though there is
full control over the values on
all of the properties in the standard shader
there are certain ranges of values that
work best for certain types of materials.
This is particularly true of the specular colour value.
When analysing real-world materials
most materials have a specular range
that is a very dark grey.
Metallic materials are one of the few exceptions,
which have very bright specularity.
As well, no material, even the most dull,
has no specularity at all.
This means to have a phyically-based
material behave correctly
some attention needs to be paid in using
the correct physical values for some key properties,
especially the specular property.
For more information on physically-based shading,
material charts and sample materials
please see the information linked below.
There is no need to panic however.
Items with materials from previous versions of Unity
will work well with Unity 5 out of the box.
Upgrading from a legacy diffuse shader
to the standard shader should display little or no difference.
In the main map section each of these properties
control one aspect of the final material.
Each property can be defined by a texture map.
The diffuse, specular and emission properties
use a texture and a colour property
where the texture is optional.
The diffuse property uses a combination
of an optional texture.
And a colour value to define the base
look of the material.
The colour value will tint the texture.
Where pure white leave the main texture unaffected.
If there is no texture being used
the tint colour will be the base colour for the material.
The specular property can either be a texture
or a colour value
and defines the specular reflectivity
of the material's surface.
The specular value can have some colour in it
but looking at real-world values,
with the exception of some metals,
this is usually a grey and often very dark.
Specular maps are usually a dark grey as well.
When a specular texture map is not being used
the overall surface smoothness
can be set with the slider.
This is easier to see when the
diffuse texture is removed.
The ball looks like polished porcelain.
For a more true mirror push the specular from dark grey,
which makes the ball look like porcelain,
in to the range of metals, and it will now reflect
the sky and surroundings.
The smoother the surface, the more it is mirror-like.
The rougher the surface, the more diffuse,
or scattered the reflections are.
The normal map property is an optional property used
to define the apparent bumpiness of the surface.
When a normal map is applied
the strength of the normal map can be controlled
by adjusting the normal map value.
As well as positive numbers, this value can be
a negative number or 0.
The height map property is an optional property
used to define the apparent height of the surface.
When a height map is applied
the strength of the height map can be controlled
by adjusting the height map value.
The occlusion property used a
texture map to define the amount of
ambient occlusion that is applied to the material.
This is used to help darken
hidden or recessed areas on the texture.
The ambient occlusion map also prevents specular
and reflections in these occluded areas
giving the material a more realistic look
The emission property controls whether or not
the material's surface will emit light.
To emit no light the emission colour should be black
or the emission value should be 0.
The material's emission value can contribute
to the scene's global illumination.
First a colour other than black needs
to be chosen to be able to emit light.
The strength of the emission can be controlled
by the emission value.
The shape of the emission can be controlled
with an emission map.
The map can be a simple black and white map.
But this texture can also be a colour map.
When there is a value for emission
the contribution of the emissive light
can be assigned to either the baked light maps
or to the real-time light maps.
The detail mask property is an optional mask element
to control the secondary maps.
Tiling and offset control the position of the map.
The secondary maps are used to define
additional surface detail.
This additional detail, sometimes referred to
as micro detail, is added on top
of the surface defined by the main maps.
This helps to add extra detail and
variation to a material,
which is overlaid on top of the main maps
defining that material.
Because detail maps can be tiled across meshes
they can add incredibly high levels of surface detail.