The script that moves the enemy will be a script
called Enemy Animation and we'll create that
script in the next assignment.
But to make sure that script is not too cluttered
we're going to make a helper script that we will
call AnimatorSetup.
Our enemies in the game will take their speed
and direction from the nav mesh.
Often when the player is trying to evade
the enemies the direction that the enemy
must face will change suddenly,
which can result in drastic and unrealistic movement.
To smooth these changes in direction and speed
we use damping, a reduction in the amount
of change over time.
This script will be making decisions on what
damping to apply when we set the
various float parameters of the
enemy's animator controller,
such as speed and angular speed.
We will create it in the unapplied subfolder
of the Scripts folder. Open the Scripts folder
and select Unapplied and then choose
Create - C# Script.
Name the script AnimatorSetup,
and double click it to launch it for editing,
and prepare the script.
Instead of applying this script to the enemy
directly we will be creating an instance
of this class within the EnemyAnimation script.
We will also not be using any of the
MonoBehaviour functions, such as Update or Awake.
This means that we won't need the MonoBehaviour
keyword or the colon, so we can remove these now.
This class is going to need 5 class variables.
in total, 3 public float variables
and then private references to the animator
component and the HashIDs script.
We will start out with the floats.
The first two of these are going to represent
damping times for our speed and
angular speed parameters.
The last will be a response time that will
be used to convert an angle
to an angular speed.
The first float we will call speedDampTime.
The next will be called angularSpeedDampTime.
and lastly angleResponseTime.
This script will not be applied to a game object
and as such these variables will not be
visible in the inspector.
These variables are public as a matter of
flexibility of code. At some point later
when designing this game we might
decide that we'd like to be able to affect
these variables whilst the game is running
from another script, perhaps we would want
to tweak their reaction speeds
under certain conditions.
If this were the case we would be able to
because they are public.
By default however we won't need to adjust then
so let's simply give them default values here.
Set these values to 0.1, 0.7 and 0.6 respectively.
Next we have the animator reference
which we will call anim
and the reference to the HashIDs script
which we will call hash.
We need to allocate a reference to each of these
variables but since we are not using
MonoBehaviour we can't use the Awake
function as we normally would.
Instead we will make sure the references are
allocated in the constructor of the class.
Firstly the constructor will need to be called
from another script, so it needs to
be a public constructor.
The constructor will be called when an instance
of this class is created.
As such we can parse in the references to
the animator and HashIDs script
from the EnemyAnimation script,
which is where we are calling the constructor.
Therefore our constructor will need an animator
parameter and a HashIDs parameter.
And we can allocate to the class variables
using these parameters.
The use of this class is to apply damping
and to set the Angular Speed and Speed
animator controller parameters.
We will need a function that we can call
in order to do this.
It needs to be called from another script
so it must be public.
It won't need to return anything
and will need to take in speed and
and angle as float parameters.
This function will setup the animator
controller parameters, so we will just
call it Setup.
The first thing we need to do is create
an Angular Speed float that we can
parse to the animator controller.
This is the angle by which the enemy should turn
divided by the response time.
Now that we have both the Speed and Angular
Speed all that's left to do is to parse them to
the animator controller with damping applied.
The SetFloat function can either have
2 parameters if you are not applying damping
or 4 parameters if you are.
The first argument is the animator parameter
that we want to set.
The second is the value we want to set it to.
The third is any damping we want to apply.
And the last is simply deltaTime
in order to apply damping over the
time between rendered frames.
And that's it for this script.
Remember to save it, and return to the Editor.
In the next assignment we will be making
the EnemyAnimation script, which will
have an instance of this AnimatorSetup
class inside it.