In a different way to how we use key input
to control our player character's animator
the animator controller for enemies
will be based on the velocity of the nav mesh agent.
The internal AI in Unity.
Let's being by making this animator controller.
Select the Animators folder in the Project panel
and click Create - Animator Controller.
We will call it Enemy Animator.
Then ensure that you have the Animator window
visible, go to Window - Animator
if you can't already see it.
For the game's enemies we are going to use
four float parameters.
Click the plus icon to the right of the parameters
field at the bottom of the Animator window
and choose Float.
The first will be called AngularSpeed.
and remember to capitalise as I am doing here.
Next we have Speed.
Shot
and Aim Weight.
And finally one Boolean parameter
PlayerInSight.
AngularSpeed will control how fast
the enemy changes it's facing direction.
Speed will be used to control how fast the
enemy moves. Shot is a parameter that refers
to a curve on the shooting animation.
Let's take a look at these curves briefly.
In our shooting animation we can see a curve
called Shot.
We will use this to determine when the gun is
firing and thus when the effects
and damage should occur.
The curve is set to 0 until the
recoil of the shooting animation,
at which point the curve peaks to 1
and then returns to 0.
We use this value of 1 to define the
point at which the effects and damage should occur.
You can see hear that this animation has another
curve for AimWeight, one of our parameters.
When the enemy is shooting the player we want
the arm to be pointing at the player
so we are going to override the animation
using inverse kinematics.
This will point the hand of the enemy
and therefore his arm at the player.
This float curve will define by how much
we override the animations with IK.
It stays at a constant of 1 for the shooting animation.
It goes from 0 to 1 in the raise animation.
And from 1 to 0 in the lowering animation.
If we did not do this the animation would
always show the character simply raising the
gun and aiming directly forward
even if the player is not directly in front
of the enemy.
Finally our last parameter, PlayerInSight,
will be used to dictate the enemies behaviour
when the enemy can see the player
and this will be set by the EnemySight script
that we will make in the next assignment.
Our enemies movement is going to be
entirely stored within one 2D blend tree.
To start right click in the Animator window
and choose Create State - From New Blend Tree.
Select the state now and name this
Locomotion at the top of the Inspector.
And now double click the state to edit the blend tree.
We are also going to call this blend tree Locomotion
so ensure it's selected and name it
at the top of the Inspector.
We want the type of this blend tree to be
2D Freeform Cartesian
This is the best type to use for dealing with
speed and angular speed.
Next we need to choose the parameters that
we want to represent the two axis of our
2d blend tree. The X axis will be represented
by the angular speed parameter
and the Y axis by speed.
This means that when we have a map of animations
the motions towards the left will be
those that turn left. The ones on the right
will be turning right. The ones at the top
will be running and the ones at the bottom
will be walking or stationary.
The next step is to add all of the motions
that we are going to use.
We will start by adding the Turn On The Spot animations.
Open the Animations - Humanoid folder
and locate humanoid_turnOnSpot
and humanoid_idle.
Within humanoid_turnOnSpot you will find
TurnOnSpotLeftD through to A
and TurnOnSpotRightA through to D.
And in humanoid_idle you will find the idle animation.
That A to D animations represent an
width of turning on the spot
with A being the smallest
and D being the widest turn.
Reselect the Locomotion blend tree
in order to see the motion list once more.
Click the plus icon and select Add Motion Field.
Start by dragging on TurnOnSpotLeftD
through to A as shown.
Creating a new motion field each time.
Next create a motion field and apply idle to it.
Now create motion fields for TurnOnSpotRightA
through to D
With 2D blend trees it doesn't matter
which order the animations are applied.
But it is nice to have a structure that's easy
to understand.
Next we will have the left walks, the straight walk
and the right walks.
Still in the Humanoid folder, open all of the
humanoid_walkForward FPXs
in order to find the animations.
Begin by adding the left walks, add WalkLeftShort,
WalkLeftMedium and WalkLeftWide.
Now add the straight forward walk, simply called Walk.
Now add the right walks, WalkRightShort,
WalkRightMedium and WalkRightWide.
Lastly we will add the running animation.
These can be found under the
humanoid_runForward FPXs.
You should note that there are no short runs
so we'll add medium and wide on the left
then straight and then wide and medium on the right.
Next we need to compute the positions of our
animations on the 2D plane.
From the Compute Positions drop down at the bottom
select Speed and Angular Speed.
This will automatically give our motions
thresholds for Speed and Angular Speed
based on the root motion that Unity detects.
within each animation. Note that calculating
the thresholds in this way is possible
with any animations regardless of which
parameters are present in the controller.
This is a calculation build in to the blend tree
based on root motion. We have chosen to
name two of our parameters Speed and Angular Speed
because they coincide with this measurement of
root motion, not for functional reasons
as this makes it easier to see how they will effect
the enemy's animation.
An important thing to note about this way of
computing positions is that Angular Speed
is calculated in radians rather than
degrees. If you are unfamiliar with radians
they are simply another measure of an angle.
where there are 360 degrees in a
full circle there are two pi radians.
Thus a full turn is little more than
6 radians, and turning 180 degrees
is a little more than 3 radians.
You can see the extreme turn on spot animations
are around 2.5 and this is
almost a 180 degree turn.
Now we can preview how this motion will look
on our character, let's make sure that we can
see the Preview window and let's
preview using our actual character rather
than the default Unity humanoid.
So in the Models folder drag and drop
char_robotGuard on to the Preview window
and press play.
To control the preview of a 2D blend tree like this
drag the red dot around in the display.
This controls the values of Speed and Angular Speed.
whilst our motions are represented by the
blue dots on the display.
And to remind you, Speed is increased
further up the display we go,
whilst Angular Speed is divided
between the left and the right sides.
That concludes the movement part of the enemy's
animator controller. Next we need to
make a new animation layer for shooting.
This layer will mean that the enemy will be able
to shoot whilst turning on the spot
in the base layer of animation.
To start out let's add a new layer
by pressing the plus button.
We will call this layer Shooting.
The next thing we need to add to our layer
is an avatar mask. Create one called
EnemyShootingMask within the Animators folder.
So select it and choose Create - Avatar Mask.
We only need a body mask so expand Body Mask
and we want all of the upper body to be controlled
by the shooting layer, so simply
deselect the legs and the feet.
Now we can apply this to the shooting layer.
Click the circle icon to the right of Mask
and choose EnemyShootingMask.
As we mentioned earlier we want the enemy's
arm to point at the player when it is shooting.
We're going to do this by using IK
so make sure that you check the IK
pass box at the bottom of the layer.
Now we can start making states for our shooting layer.
We're going to make our default state
an empty state. To do this right click
and select Create State - Empty.
We need an Empty state so that what ever is
happening in the base layer is by default
not being overridden.
Next we need our RaisedWeapon state.
Open the Animations - Humanoid folder
and find the animation in the humanoid_weapon_raise FPX.
Drag and drop WeaponRaise in to the Animator.
We want to make sure that the animation happens
nice and quickly so that the enemy can get to
shooting right away, so for this reason
we'll change the speed of the animation to 3.
We need a transition to RaiseWeapons
from our Empty state. The condition for this
is that Player In Sight is true.
Let's make sure that we lay out our states
with enough space so that they all fit on screen.
Then right click on New State
and make a transition to WeaponRaise.
Select the transition.
And make sure that the condition is that
Player In Sight is true.
Once the weapon has been raised we need him
to start shooting, so drag in
the ShootWeapon animation.
You'll find this under humanoid_weapon_shoot.
Drag and drop it in
and align it with our other states.
Now we need a transition from the raising
of the weapon to the shooting of the weapon
and the condition for this should simply be
that the animation has finished.
So we can leave this on the default transition
condition, which is Exit Time
So right click on WeaponRaise
and make a transition to WeaponShoot.
You'll see that if you select the transition
Exit Time is the default.
The last state that we need is lowering the weapon.
So drag that on now. You'll find it naturally
in humanoid_weapon_lower.
The condition that we stop shooting and lower
the weapon is that the player is no longer
in sight, so this should be the condition
for the transition.
Right click on WeaponShoot and make a transition
to WeaponLower.
now select the transition and set the
condition to be the Player In Sight is false.
Finally once we've lowered the weapon we want
to transition back to the empty state.
Right click on WeaponLower
and make a transition to the empty state.
Yet again we simply want the WeaponLowering
to transition back in to nothing
so we will leave the Exit Time as our condition.
The last thing we want to do in the animator
is make sure that the enemy grips his gun.
The animations that we have don't
naturally have a grip posture for the right hand
so we're going to make a layer to handle this for us.
Create another new layer by pressing the
plus icon and call is Gun.
So select the Animators folder in the Project panel
and click Create - Avatar Mask.
Name this one EnemyGunMask
and expand the body mask.
This time we want to deselect everything
apart from the right hand.
You should be aware that the body mask
is represented by a character
that is actually facing you.
So the right hand of the character will actually
be the left hand in the display.
Now we can apply it to the gun layer by
clicking on the small circle to the right
of the mask property.
Select EnemyGunMask and close the window.
The only animation that we want in this layer
is the gripped animation that we have
on the robotGuard FPX.
This is just a single frame of animation
with the hand in a gripped posture.
In the models folder expand
char_robotGuard
and you'll find a Gripped animation.
Drag and drop this in to the Animator.
This is orange, which means it's our default
state, which is what we want.
Also note that the blending of this layer
is set to override and we know that our
EnemyGunMask only has the hand visible.
So we know that at all times the enemy's
hand will grip the gun.
Now that the animator controller is finished
we can drag it on to the Enemy's animator component.
Reselect char_robotGuard in the hierarchy
and then drag and drop EnemyAnimator
on to the Controller property
in the animator component.
Finally save the scene and the project.
Note that at this stage our parameters
don't have any way of receiving information.
So we cannot yet preview how the enemy will
behave in the scene.
In the next assignment we will be making the
first script for the enemy.
The EnemySight script will handle
identifying the player's location.