In this assignment we will begin work
on the lift by creating a set of double doors.
The lift will have inner and outer doors
and the inner doors will track the motion
of the outer doors.
Here we will setup the motion of the
outer doors and write code that will
apply to the lift's inner doors that we
will add in the next assignment.
The double doors of the lift will work in
a similar way to the single doors we
have already made, but with some
subtle differences.
We will start as before by dragging the
model in to the scene.
In the Models folder locate
door_exitOuter and drag it in to
the Scene view.
Position it at (-22, 0, 46).
And rotate it by 270 in the Y axis.
Double click it's name in the hierarchy
to focus the Scene view on it.
You should now see that it's located
inside the lift shaft.
Before we go any further let's enable
light probes on both the left and right door
so that they are affected by the lighting in our scene.
Open the hierarchy and select both
doors then under the Mesh Renderer component
check Use Light Probes.
Next, as with our single door,
we need to add box colliders to each of
the doors and a sphere trigger collider
to the parent object.
Select the parent object and choose
Add Component - Physics - Sphere Collider
and check the Is Trigger box.
Then select both child door objects
and choose Add Component - Physics - Box Collider
We want the proportions and the position
of the trigger collider to be slightly different
to the single doors.
This is because we want the doors to shut
behind the player character when they enter the lift.
Reselect the parent object
and in the Sphere Collider component
set the centre to (-1, 1, 0)
and set the radius to 2.
Now we need to create an animator
controller asset to control the double doors.
It should be exactly the same as the single
door animator controller but with the
animations for the double doors instead.
As such we can duplicate the single
door animator that we made earlier
and rename the duplicate to DoubleDoorAnimator.
Open the Animators folder in the Project panel
and duplicate the SingleDoorAnimator.
You can use the shortcut command-D
or control-D on PC
or go to Edit - Duplicate.
Then rename this DoubleDoorAnimator.
Now all we need to do is edit the animations
that the states represent.
Ensure that you can see your Animator window
and then change the SingleDoorOpen animation
to the DoubleDoorOpen animation
and likewise for the closed.
To do this select the open state
in the Animator window and then in the
Models folder in the project panel
expand the door_exitOuter FPX
so that you can see the open and closed
animations beneath it.
Drop the door_exitOuter_open animation
on to the motion field in the Inspector
for the open state.
Then select the closed state
and drag door_exitOuter_closed
to the motion field for this state.
We can now apply the animator controller
to the animator component.
Reselect door_exitOuter in the hierarchy
and drag the DoubleDoorAnimator
from the Animators folder in the project
to the controller property of the
animator component.
We also need to make sure that Root Motion
is not applied, so uncheck this box.
As with the single doors we need to add
a kinematic rigidbody component
to the moving parts.
Select both the exitOuter_left and right doors
and go to Add Component - Physics - RigidBody.
Uncheck Use Gravity and check Is Kinematic.
Now we can apply the door animation script
that we wrote earlier to the parent object.
Select door_exitOuter
and then in the Scripts folder
under Level Dynamics drag and drop
DoorAnimation either in to the Inspector
beneath the other components or on the
name of the object in the hierarchy.
We need to make sure that the correct
audio clips are applied
so in the Audio folder drag and drop
door_open to Door Swish Clip
and door_accessDenied to Access Denied Clip
and also that this door requires a key.
by checking the Require Key public variable
in the Inspector.
As with the single doors, for these doors
we will need to add an audio source component
and make sure that Play On Awake is unchecked.
Click Add Component and choose
Audio - Audio Source and uncheck Play On Awake.
The doors are now ready to be stored as a prefab.
Do so by dragging the parent object from
the hierarchy in to the Prefabs folder
in the Project panel.
The last thing we will do in this assignment
is to make a script that will make the inner
doors of the lift move with the outer
doors that we have just made.
We will call it LiftDoorsTracking.
However we are not going to apply it to the doors,
instead we will be applying it to the lift
that we will make later.
Select the Scripts folder in the Project panel
and then select Level Dynamics.
Click Create and choose C# script.
Name the script LiftDoorsTracking
Launch the script for editing
and then prepare it as usual.
In this script we are going to make the inner
doors lag just slightly behind the outer doors.
As such we will need a variable that we can tweak
for how fast the inner doors will catch up.
We will set this to a default of 7.
We also need to store the transform
of each of our doors.
The last class variables we will need
are floats, in which we can store the
X component of the position the doors
are in when they are closed.
We will use this to force them to close
when the lift is about to leave.
Next we can use the awake function to
allocate our references.
We are going to use GameObject.Find
rather than tagging each door separately.
At this point it becomes obvious why a strong
naming convention is advised.
We know that our double doors have names like
door_exitOuter_left_001.
Using our naming convention we know that
the inner doors, those attached to the lift
will be named door_exitInner_left_001 for the left
and likewise for the right.
We also need to set the closed X positions.
Since the doors will start off closed
we can setup these variables in the Awake function.
We need a function that will move the doors
based on a target X coordinate.
We will need a float argument for each
of the left and right doors that will
be parsed to this function when it is called.
We will call this function MoveDoors.
Normally when we want to smoothly transition
from one position to another we'd use
Vector3.Lerp and therefore modify the
X, Y and Z coordinates.
But since we want the inner doors to also move
up with the lifts we're only going
to lerp their X coordinate using Mathf.Lerp.
We will then simply parse in the existing
Y and Z coordinates in to the Vector3
for the new position.
We will use this Mathf.Lerp on a
new float variable.
Firstly we will set the left inner door.
We then set the position of the door to a
Vector3 with the newly offset X coordinate.
and the existing Y and Z coordinates.
Next we can reassign this new X variable
for the right inner door's new X coordinate.
And with this we can set the right inner
door's position.
With the function complete we need a couple
of ways of calling it.
Both these functions should be public
since they will be called from the lift
triggering script that we will write later.
We need one function to call the MoveDoors function
with the parameter of the outer door's X
positions so that the inner doors will follow them.
The other function we will need we'll call
MoveDoors with the parameters of the closed
X positions for when the player is
inside the lift, and it must close
to seal them inside.
We will start with the function that makes
the inner doors follow the outer doors.
We will call this DoorFollowing.
All we need to do in this function is
to call MoveDoors with the outer doors
X positions as parameters.
Next we will make the function CloseDoors
which we'll call MoveDoors with the closed
X coordinates.
The script is now finished and in the next
assignment we will attach it to the lift.
For now save your script and
reutrn to the editor.
Remember to save your scene
and save your project.
In the next assignment we will be finishing off
this chapter by creating the lift
through which the player completes the level.