The Sprite Editor is used to take images
containing multiple elements like an atlas or sprite sheet
and slice them in to individual sprites.
It is important that the sprite mode of the image
is set to Multiple.
Images with sprite modes set to single
cannot use the sprite editor window at this time.
For more information on sprites, sprite mode and the sprite type
please see the information link below.
When sprite mode multiple is selected
the sprite editor button will appear on the
texture importer in the inspector.
Click the sprite editor button to open the sprite editor.
The sprite editor can also be opened by selecting
Window  - Sprite Editor.
The sprite editor window is a standard Unity window.
It can be used and docked like any other window.
To create sprites in the sprite editor window
slice the image by clicking and dragging
over the desired elements.
This will create rectangular selections that define each sprite.
The rectangular selection can be adjusted
by clicking and dragging the rectangle.
Click and drag anywhere inside the rectangle to move it.
Click and drag any of the corners or edges to resize it.
Click and drag the pivot point gizmo to move
the pivot point for that sprite.
When a sprite is selected a sprite panel appears
in the lower right of the sprite editor
with details about the selected sprite.
Name is the name of the sprite.
The name is created from the name of the original image
and the order in which it was sliced from that image,
starting with 0.
Position defines where the sprite
is on the image, in pixels.
X and Y define the start point of the sprite.
measured from the lower left corner of the image.
to the lower left corner of the sprite.
W and H define the width and height
of the sprite, from the start point.
The trim button can be used to trim off any
excess space around the element,
creating the tightest fitting rectangle possible.
Pivot sets the pivot point for this sprite.
The pivot drop-down menu includes presets
for each corner and the centre of each edge.
Custom allows for a custom pivot point
to be set numerically under Custom Pivot.
Along the top of the sprite editor are a
number of tools.
The slice menu,
the revert and apply buttons,
the RGB alpha toggle
and the zoom slider.
The slice menu is used to automatically create sprites
by slicing the sprite elements from the image.
The slice type is either automatic or grid.
Automatic is best for slicing individual
uneven elements, like from an atlas.
Elements on the image are automatically
detected based on the empty space around them.
Each sprite will have effectively been trimmed
as a result.
With automatic selected minimum size defines the
minimum size for each individual sprite.
If this value is set too high smaller elements
that are near each other could be combined
in to 1 larger sprite to meet
the minimum size requirements.
Pivot sets the default pivot point that will
be applied to all sprites when they are
spiced from the image.
Just like the sprite panel, the pivot drop-down menu
includes presets for each corner and the centre of each edge.
To set a custom pivot, once the sprites have been sliced
select any sprite and adjust it's pivot point
in the sprite panel,
or adjust it visually in the editor.
Method lets you choose how to deal with existing
sprites in the sprite editor window.
Delete Existing will replace any sprites
that already exist with new sprites.
Smart will attempt to create new sprites
while retaining and adjusting existing ones.
Safe will add new sprites without
changing any sprites already created.
When the settings are correct select the Slice button
to slice the image in to individual sprites.
After slicing, each sprite can be edited individually.
With the sprite sheet, where each element is designed
to be a regular identical size,
if Slice Type Automatic is used
small changes in the individual sprite's shape
and the amount of empty space surrounding it
could cause the sprites to be cut out unevenly.
To evenly slice a sprite sheet made of regular elements
choose Slice Type Grid.
Pixel Size sets the size of the grid in pixels.
Pivot sets the default pivot point that will be applied
to all sprites when they are sliced from the image.
To set a custom pivot, once the sprites have been sliced,
select any sprite and adjust it's pivot point
in the sprite panel, or adjust it visually in the editor.
When the settings are correct use the slice button
to slice the image in to individual sprites.
After slicing each sprite can be edited individually.
When slicing is complete, to save any changes,
select Apply.
Or discard any change by selecting Revert.
The RGB Alpha toggle switches the
display of the sprite editor between the colour image
and it's alpha channel, making it easier to see
fine details when manually adjusting edges.
The zoom slider controls the zoom when viewing the image.
When an image has been successfully edited
and the changes applied
the asset will update in the project window.
And a new sprite, or set of sprites
can be seen as a child or group of children
under the image.
When viewing thumbnails in the project view
click the turn-down arrow to see any children.
Each child represents a useable sprite from that image.
Any of these sprites can be used in the
project independently, or grouped together
to create a character, for example,
or used sequentially as animations.