Attributes allow you to attach information to a
method, variable or class as you declare it.
This is useful for taking existing code
and enhancing it or changing it in some way.
Attributes themselves vary greatly
in their effects and use.
Here we have a Unity scene with an orb in it.
The orb has a Spin Script attached to it.
Notice the speed variable of the script
which is currently set to 0.
In the Spin Script we can see that we
first declare the integer speed variable
and set it to 0.
Then in the update method
we rotate the object about the Y axis
based on the current speed.
In this way we could give the speed variable
any value we wanted and the objects rotating
speed would change as a result.
This works fine, but what if we wanted to
limit the value of the speed variable?
We could write code to detect the current value
of the variable and prevent it from going out of range.
Or we could attach an attribute to it.
Attributes are written either directly above
or directly before the code that they are modifying
and generally don't affect any other parts of the script.
In this case we will be using
the range attribute.
The syntax for all attributes starts with
an open square bracket.
Then for the range attribute
we write the keyword Range followed by parenthesis.
Inside the parenthesis we write our minimum
and maximum values.
We finish the attribute with a closed square bracket.
Note in this case we have put the
attribute above the variable declaration.
We could have easily put it just before as well.
If we go back in to Unity
we can see that we are no longer presented with
the same speed property in the inspector view.
We now have a slider which goes from our minimum
to our maximum values.
Running our scene, we can see that moving the slider
directly changes the speed of the variable,
which in turn changes the rotation of the object.
Another attribute we will look at is the
Execute In Edit Mode attribute.
This attribute causes the script  that it is
attached to to run even when the scene is
not in play mode.
Here we have another scene with an orb in it.
This orb has a script called
Colour Script attached to it.
In the Colour Script we set the colour of the object's
shared material to red.
If we wanted to see this change in Unity
without running our scene we could apply the
Execute In Edit Mode attribute to it.
To do this we open a square bracket either
above or before our class name.
We put it before the class name
because the Execute In Edit Mode attribute
is applied to all of the code in a script,
not just one part.
We then write the keyword ExecuteInEditMode
followed by a closing square bracket.
This attribute does not have any parameters
and therefore does not need any parenthesis.
Back in Unity we can see that our object has turned red.
Our script was executed even though we never ran our scene.
It is worth noting that you need to be careful
with the ExecuteInEditMode attribute.
Normally scripts are run when the scene is run.
When you stop running a scene any changes
made to the game object in a scene are undone.
Scripts that are executed in edit mode however
will be able to modify, create and delete objects in your scene.
Since the changes are not in play mode
they will not revert and will instead be permanent.
For instance, the orb in this scene
has been modified to actually be red permanently.
If we drag another orb in to our scene
if will also be red, since the orb asset was changed.
To fix this we would have to manually
change our colour back.
You could find more information on the ExecuteInEditMode
attribute in the documentation linked below.