Events are specialised delegates
that are useful for when you want to alert
other classes that something has happened.
In practice you will see that events
function very similarly to public multicast delegates.
For more information on delegates
see the lesson on delegates linked below.
An event can be thought of like broadcast system.
Any class that is interested in an event
can subscribe methods to it.
When that specific situation occurs,
like a button click, a power-up or player injury
we invoke our event and that in turn
calls the methods of the subscribed classes.
We have here a scene with 2 orbs in it.
One orb has a script called TeleportScript
while the other has a script called TurnColorScript.
Attached to our camera is an EventManagerScript.
An event can be made for just about any situation.
But in this example we want to invoke an event
whenever the player clicks a button
that we are drawing to the screen.
In our event manager we can see
that we first create a delegate type
which we name ClickAction.
We can see that any method that wishes to subscribe
must take no parameters and have a return type of void.
Next we create our event variable.
We do this with the Event keyword.
Note that this variable is also static
so that we can use it outside of the class
without instantiating an object of this class.
Our event variable, which we have named OnClicked
is of the type of the delegate we created above.
The only other thing this class is responsible for
is calling the event whenever the appropriate
situation arrises.
Like we stated before,
we will call this even whenever the player
clicks our button.
Therefore this script has an OnGUI method.
Inside the OnGUI method
we create a button on our screen.
When the player clicks the button
we use our event variable as if it was a function.
This in effect invokes our event.
Please note that just like delegates
it causes an error if we invoke an event
with no subscribers.
Therefore we should always make sure
that the event does not equal null
before invoking it.
If you recall the 2 orbs in our
scene have 2 different scripts attached to them.
These 2 scripts will act as subscribers
to this event.
Let's take a look at them now.
In the TeleportScript we have
created a method call Teleport.
This is the method that we will be subscribing to
the event that we created in the event manager.
You will notice that the Teleport method takes no parameters
and has a return type of void,
just like our delegate.
The Teleport method is responsible for
positioning the object randomly along the Y axis.
Near the top of our script
we have a method named OnEnable.
This is a built-in method that will be called
whenever the object that this script is
attached to is created or enabled in a scene.
We will use this method to subscribe our
Teleport method to the OnClicked event
of the EventScript.
We can see that we subscribe a method to
an event by using the += operator.
By subscribing a method to an event
we ensure that whenever the event occurs
our method will be called.
Next we have the OnDisable method.
Opposite of the OnEnable method,
the OnDisable method is called whenever
an object is disabled or destroyed in a scene.
Inside the OnDisabled method
we are unsubscribing our method from the event.
We unsubscribe a method from an event
using the -= operator.
Doing so will ensure that our method is no
longer called when an event occurs.
This step is incredibly important
and failure to do so can lead to memory
leaks and errors in your game.
A good rule is that whenever you subscribe
a method to an event you must
also have a corresponding unsubscribe
Our TurnColorScript
is structured very similarly to our TeleportScript.
In this case we have a method called TurnColor
which takes no parameters and has a return
type of void.
The TurnColor method
turns the object's material a random color.
Again, we have the OnEnable
and OnDisable methods.
This time they are subscribing
and unsubscribing our TurnColor method
from the event.
It is worth noting another time
that unsubscribing our method from the event
is paramount to using events correctly
and preventing errors in our code.
Back in Unity we can run our scene.
The first thing to notice is the button that
appears near the top.
Clicking this button will invoke our event
and call the Teleport and TurnColor methods.
We can click the button multiple times
and each time the subscribe to methods will be called.
As we can see, our event manager
only needed to worry about the event itself
and the triggers for the event.
It did not need to know about the TeleportScript,
or the TurnColorScript.
Likewise the TeleportScript and TurnColorScript
didn't need to know about each other.
In this way we are able to create
a very robust and flexible broadcast system.
You might be wondering why we used a static
event variable instead of a public delegate variable
in our event manager?
The truth is you can achieve the exact same
functionality of events with public delegate variables.
In fact as we stated at the beginning of this lesson,
events are just specialised delegates.
The reason we use events over public
delegate variables for situations like this
is that events have inherent security
where delegate variables do not.
With events other classes
can only subscribe and unsubscribe.
If we were to use a public delegate variable instead
other classes could invoke or
override our delegate variable to do
all sorts of nefarious things.
Generally speaking, if you want to create a dynamic
method system that involves more than 1 class,
use event variables instead of delegate variables.