Extension methods are a way of adding functionality
to a type without having to create a derive type
or change the original type.
They are perfect for situations where you need to add
functionality to a class but cannot edit the class.
Consider the class transform which is built in to
Unity so we do not have access to it's source code.
Let's say we wanted an easy way to reset the
position, rotation and scale
transform using a function.
The ideal place for this function would be in
the transform class, but since we can't
directly add to the class and it wouldn't make sense
to have this function in a derived class
we'll make an extension for it.
Extension methods must be placed in a
non-generic static class.
It is common to create a class specifically
to contain them.
While extension methods are used like instance
methods, they too are declared static.
What makes a function an extension method
instead of a static method is the use
of the This keyword in the parameter.
For our example we will create a static
class called ExtensionMethods.
We then create our extension method named
ResetTransformation.
Notice that this method is declared static.
Also notice that the first parameter has the
this keyword followed by the transform
class and an arbitrary parameter name.
This first parameter will be the calling object
and thus will not have to be supplied when we
call this function.
Furthermore, this first parameter dictates which
class this method becomes a part of.
If we wanted any more parameters we
could put them in here without the this keyword.
Within the method we can now write the code
to reset the transform.
It is important to note that despite this function
declaration having a parameter, when the function is
called it will have none.
The parameter implicitly becomes the
instance of the transform.
In order to use this extension method
you only need to look for it as a member
of the class you extended.
In this case we extend transform
and can see that the method is now a part of the transform class.