The scripting languages that Unity supports
have a feature called inheritance.
Inheritance is one of the cornerstones of object
orientated programming, or OOP for short.
One a class inherits from another
it gains the features of the class it inherits from.
When talking about inheritance, the class that being
inherited from is called the Parent, or base class.
The class that is inheriting is called the Child,
or derived class.
The result of inheritance is that items that exist
in the parent class will also be available
in the child class.
Therefore, methods and variables can be used in the
child class as if it was the parent class.
For example, assume you have a parent class
called ClassA, which contains two methods,
Dance and Sing.
If you have another class, ClassB,
which inherits from ClassA,
then ClassB will also have the two methods
Dance and Sing.
These methods do not need to be created in ClassB
because they already exist in ClassA.
When dealing with inheritance there are three access
modifiers to be aware of;
Public, Private and Protected.
You should already be familiar with the concepts
of the Public and Private access modifiers.
Just be aware that the features of a parent class
that are public will exist and be accessible
in the child class.
While features that are private will exist
but not be accessible in the child class.
The protected access modifier acts as a
hybrid between public and private.
All features of a parent class that are protected
will exist and be accessible in a child class,
like public features, but will not be accessible
outside of the parent or child classes,
like private features.
It is likely that most of the classes you have
used so far in Unity have been inheriting,
indeed, all scripts which are applied
as components to game objects are monobehaviours.
This means they have inherited
from the monobehaviour class.
By default scripts made in Unity
follow this format;
public class followed by the name of the class
followed by a colon and the classname monobehaviour.
The colon in classname monobehaviour
is telling the script that it inherits from monobehaviour.
To make this class inherit from another class
simply change the name monobehaviour
to some other class name.
To change the class so that it doesn't inherit
from any parent class
simply remove the colon and parent class name.
You might be wondering why our scripts inherit
from monobehaviour.
Items like GameObject, Transform, the Start method,
the Update method and more
all come from monobehaviour.
Our scripts inherit from monobehaviour
so that we have access to these features.
The inheritance structure is hierarchal.
A common way to think of inheritance is
to think of the animal kingdom.
In this example we'd have a parent class called Animal.
This class would contain all of the definitions
and properties necessary to make the
class behave like an animal.
From this Animal base class we might have a
couple of child classes, Vertebrate and Invertebrate.
The Vertebrate class would then in turn be the
parent class for more classes, such as
Mammal, Reptile and Amphibian.
Each of these child classes would take the
information given by it's base class and add to it.
Just like our animal example, inheritance
in object orientated programming is known
as an Is A relationship.
This means that the child class is a parent class.
A reptile is a vertebrate.
A mammal is an animal.
An example in Unity that you may have come across
before is a capsule collider is a collider.
This concept will be covered further in the lesson
on polymorphism linked below.
The idea of inheritance can be very useful
and applicable in game development.
We might, for example, have a class called Humanoid.
This class covers all of the things that Humanoid
should do in our game.
We then have two child classes,
Enemy and Player.
These control the specifics of how players and
enemies work in the game while already
behaving like humanoids because they've
inherited all of the humanoid classes members.
We could then have two more child classes
of Enemy, Ork and Goblin.
These already behave like enemies, which in
turn behave like humanoids.
In this way we have much less code to write
to make Orks and Goblins behave
as we want them to because we're reusing
the code from Humanoid and Enemy.
Constructors are an exception to what is inherited
by child classes, as they remain
unique to a class and are never shared.
When a constructor is called in a child class however
the constructor of it's parent class is called
immediately before.
Since classes can have many different constructors
we might want to be able to control which base class
constructor is being called.
We do this with the keyword Base.
By following the parameter list of the child's
constructor with a colon you can explicitly
call a specific constructor of the base class
using the keyword Base and
the base constructors parameter list.
If the base classes constructor is not
called explicitly then the default constructor
will still be called implicitly.
Aside from calling the base classes constructor
you can also use the Base keyword to access
other members of the base class.
This is useful for situations where you wish to
access the base classes version of something
because it is different than the derived version.
This happens often when overriding functions.
For more information on this see the lesson
on Overriding linked below.