In this lesson we'll be covering two generic collections,
lists and dictionaries.
We will also be using some of their methods.
Both work in similar ways to arrays
but with some important differences.
Let's take a look at the list class first.
A list is like a dynamically sized array.
This means that you don't need to know how many elements
it's going to have ahead of time.
Before we go too far let's quickly
create a class that we can store in our list.
Since a list is generic it can store any type.
But for our example we're going to create a
class called BadGuy.
This way we can have a list of badguys.
This class will have no inheritants, 2 public fields
named Name and Power,
and a constructor to allocate these values.
Now we can start making our list.
The first thing to do when making a list is to include
the System.Collections.Generic namespace.
We will do this at the top of the script.
Next we declare the list.
List is a generic class, so after any modifiers
we put the class name followed by a type
that we want to store in the list.
In our case, BadGuy.
Then we give the list a name, and since list is
a class we call the constructor.
Currently our list is empty, so let's allocate to it.
We do this using the Add function.
This will add a new element to the end of the list.
The parameter for the add function is the object
that is being added to the list, in our case
we'll call a constructor for the BadGuy class.
Now let's populate the list.
Items in a list can be accessed in the same way
as an array, using an index.
It also has a count property which works the same
as the length property of arrays.
Lists have functions like RemoveAt and Insert
InsertFromManualArrangement.
RemoveAt removes an element from the list
that are given index, it moves all elements
above it down a place.
Insert takes an index and an element,
pushing each element after that index up a place.
One of the most powerful functions of a list is sort.
This can be used to order a list of a given type
by any variable of that type.
It relies on the type implementing the
IComparable interface.
Let's go back to our BadGuy class and implement it.
First IComparable is in the system namespace
so we need to declare that we are using it.
Next we need to say that this class is
implementing the interface.
This looks like inheritance.
We're going to use the generic IComparable
and it's generic type needs to be this class.
Lastly, in order to complete the contract of the
IComparable interface we need to declare a
public function called CompareTo
which returns an integer and takes our  generic
type BadGuy as a parameter.
The idea behind the CompareTo method is that
if the object that it is being called from is
greater than the object taken as a parameter
then the function returns a positive.
If the object the method is called from is less than
the object taken as a parameter
then the function returns a negative,
and if they are equal then it returns a 0.
What defines one object being greater than another
is decided by the programmer.
For our function we first want to check that the BadGuy
parse to the function exists.
If it doesn't then this BadGuy is greater and the
function should return a positive.
Otherwise the function returns the difference
between the powers of the 2 BadGuys.
Thus it will return a positive if the BadGuy
the method is being called from is greater.
Note that we could have based this result on anything.
The interface only requires that we implement the method.
Now in order to sort the list using this comparison
we call Badguys.Sort.
We will log the Badguys list to the console
to show that they have been sorted.
In order to start fresh with the list and remove
all of the elements use the the clear function.
These are by no means all of the functions
of the list class.
To cover everything falls out of the scope of this tutorial.
For further information please see the related
information links below.
Dictionaries work similarly to lists but instead
have 2 types. This means that each element
makes up a key value pair,
sometimes called a KVP for short.
Dictionaries also differ from lists in their intended use.
A list is generally used in place of an array
where more flexibility or functionality is required.
A dictionary is used as a collection of value
that can be accessed by 1 or more keys.
The process for declaring a dictionary is very
similar to that for a list.
First include the System.Collections.Generic namespace.
Then declare a variable as before
but with 2 generic types.
The first type is the key.
This is the type that is referenced in order to
access the second type, which is the value.
In our example we have a key type of
String and a value type of BadGuy.
We are using this dictionary to store different
search words that can be used to identify
specific BadGuys.
In our start method we declared 2 BadGuys.
Then we add them to the dictionary
just as we would with a list,
only this time we are adding data from
both the key and the value.
Accessing the value that relates to a key
is done very similar to accessing
an element of an array or list.
However, instead of using an index
which would have no inherent meaning to a dictionary
we insert a key in to the square brackets.
In the case for this example we inserted String
and we have the corresponding BadGuy returned.
If a key is provided but no such key
exists in the dictionary however
this will throw an exception.
Therefore if it is not guaranteed that the key exists
it is best to use the TryGetValue method
This method has a parameter of the key's type
and an out parameter of the value's type.
It returns true if the key parsed
as the first parameter exists.
While this is a safer method for returning
a value from a dictionary it is slightly slower
than directly referencing the specific key.
For efficiency use the key within square brackets
but only when the specified key is
definitely in the dictionary.