Namespaces are like containers for classes.
Their purpose is to help you organise your scripts
and to avoid conflicts between scripts.
You might, for example, be making tools in Unity
to help you develop your application.
You could keep the tools and actually application
in separate namespaces so you didn't have too
many unnecessary classes being suggested by autocomplete.
Chances are all of the scripts you have been writing
so far have been using namespaces.
At the top of C# scripts in Unity
by default you'll see two lines.
Using UnityEngine and
using System.Collections.
UnityEngine and System.Collections are both namespaces.
The Using keyword means that anything within
the namespace that follows can be used in the script.
Try commenting out the using directives at the top
of the script and you can see that autocomplete
has far fewer classes that you can us.
That's because classes like GameObject,
Transform, Rigid Body and many more
are all in the UnityEngine namespace.
In order to put our class in a namespace
we need to surround the class with the namespace syntax.
Start off with the keyword Namespace
and then the namespaces name.
This can be an existing namespace or a new one.
In this case we are going to call our namespace
SampleNamespace.
Then we have an open brace before the class
and a close brace after the class.
Since our class now belongs to SampleNamespace
we will indent it to show belonging.
There are three ways we can use the classes
from a specific namespace.
We've already seen the first, which is to include
a using directive at the top of your script.
The second way to access the class
is to use the dot operator.
For example, instead of having
using SampleNamespace at the top of the script
every time we wanted to reference a class from
the SampleNamespace we could type
SampleNamespace dot and then the class.
This option avoids ambiguity but can be cumbersome.
Particularly with large namespace names
like SampleNamespace.
The last option is to put the class that you are writing
in to the namespace that you need access to.
This is generally not recommended unless you mean
to have that class in the same namespace anyway.
So long as classes are in different namespaces
they name have the same name.
However, since scripts have the same name as
the class contained in them the scripts must be
in different folders in order to have the same class name.
When using namespaces be careful to avoid
ambiguous definitions.
For example, two very common namespaces
to use are System and UnityEngine.
These both contain a definition for a class
called Random. If you are already using them
both you need to disambiguate the class
by using the dot operator.
Either use System.Random or UnityEngine.Random.
You might have noticed that the second default
using directive is the system.collections namespace.
This illustrates that namespaces are nestable.
In order to nest namespaces simply enclose
one namespace declaration within another.