Overloading is a process by which you can give
a single method multiple definitions.
This means that you can use the same method name
to do 2 different things.
Let's say you needed a method to add things together.
You could create an AddNumbers method
that would be responsible for adding 2 numbers together.
Adding strings together however works differently
so you would need a new method called AddStrings.
This works fine, but the problem is that now you
need to remember 2 different method names that
in essence to do the same thing.
A better way would be to overload a method name
Add to work with either Numbers or String.
Here we have a method names Add that reads in
2 numbers and returns a number
Every method has what is called a signature.
The signature is comprised of a method's name
and parameter list.
No 2 methods can have the same signature
within the same scope.
We overload methods by giving a new method
the same name but a different signature.
Using our previous example, we can overload
this Add method to create a new method
that adds Strings.
Notice that our new Add method has the same
name but a different parameter list.
Since it is a different signature this is allowed.
In SomeOtherClass, when we try to access
the Add method we can see that there
are 2 versions of it.
The correct version will be chosen based on the
arguments you parse in to it.
By parsing in 2 numbers the method that
adds numbers will run.
Likewise, if you parse in 2 strings
then the method that adds strings will run.
1 of 3 things will happen when the system tries
to decide on the correct version of an
overloaded method to run.
First, if there is an exact match to the
parameters parsed in then that version of the
overloaded method will run.
If there isn't an exact match the system
will look at all of the possible matches and will choose
the 1 that will require the least amount of conversion.
Finally, if there are no possible matches
or multiple version that require the same
amount of conversion then an error is thrown.