In Unity a transform's rotation is
stored as a quaternion
These work similarly to vectors
but have 4 components, X, Y, Z and W.
These components are interdependent and work
together to define any rotations
that an object might need.
One of the most important things to remember about
dealing with quaternions is that since the X,
Y, Z and W components work together
you should never adjust them individually.
Thankfully Unity has many built-in
functions to make managing quaternions easy.
The system for managing rotations that you are
probably already familiar with is called
Euler Angles.
The rotation value shown in the Inspector use
this system as it is slightly easier to understand.
Euler Angle Rotation is based on a rotation
around each of the X, Y and Z axis.
You might be wondering why Unity uses quaternions
if euler angles are easier to understand,
especially since Unity converts the quaternion
to euler angles for the Inspector.
Suffice to say that euler angles are subject
something called Gimbal Lock which can
prevent incremental rotations from working correctly.
Luckily, since Unity stores rotations
as quaternions, which are not subject to Gimbal Lock,
we do not experience this problem.
Let's take a look at some of the functionality that
is available through the quaternion class.
We will start with the LookRotation function.
Here we have a scene setup with a character and a orb.
The character has a script called LookAtScript
attached to it.
The orb has a script called MotionScript
The MotionScript simply moves the object
side to side based on the horizontal input axis.
The LookOutScript has a public field for a target
transform and in the Update function
we will be using LookRotation to cause
the object to rotation to face the target.
The LookRotation function takes in a vector3.
It returns a quaternion rotation
aligned with the vector3 parsed in.
By calculating the relative vector between
the object and the target we could
make the object's Z axis
point towards the target.
This works in a similar way to Transform.LookAt
but utilising quaternions sets the rotation explicitly.
It is also worth noting that we can parse
in a second vector3 to the function
This vector3 tells the function which
direction is considered up.
Back in the Unity Editor, let's run our scene.
We can see that no matter where we move the orb
the character turns to face it.
The next function we want to look at is
the Slerp function.
Slerp is short for Spherical Interpolation.
It is very similar to the lerp function
which stands for Linear Interpolation.
The big difference between the two is that
lerp will interpolate evenly between two
quaternions, while slerp will
interpolate on a curve.
The result is that lerp will provide an even
change over time, while slerp will start
and end slower and be faster in the middle.
We have here a scene with another character and orb.
The character has no scripts attached to it.
The orb has a Gravity script attached to it.
This scene will utilise slerp and some
forward movement to achieve a gravity orbit effect.
In the Gravity script we have a setup similar
to the LookAt script from before.
Again, we have a public field for a target transform.
We are also calculating the relative vector
between the object and the target, though this time
we are adding an offset to account for the orbs height.
We are also calculating the LookRotation
like before except we are not storing it in
the rotation of the object's transform this time.
Instead we are storing it in a quaternion
variable named Rotation.
We are then storing the local rotation of the
object in a quaternion variable named Current.
After that we are using the slerp function
to slowly turn the object to face the target.
The slerp function reads in the current rotation,
the end result rotation and the speed it
should interpolate or turn.
The fact that the rotation doesn't happen
immediately but over time is the key to
making this example work.
After we turn the objects slightly towards
the target we move it forward a little bit.
Back in Unity we can run our scene
and see the result.
The orb is always moving forward and
turning to face the target, which in this
case is the character.
This gives us a nice smooth orbit effect.
The last thing we are going to look at is the
identity property of the quaternion class.
Setting a quaternion to Quaternion.identity
will effectively set it's euler rotation to
(0,0,0), or no rotation.
There are more functions in the quaternion class
that you can find in the documentation linked below.
The most important things to take away from this lesson
are that quaternions are the best way of
dealing with rotation, and that you should
never alter the components independently.
There will always be some functionality
that you can use instead.