Static members, such as variables and methods
are members that are shared across all instances
of a class.
Furthermore, static members can be accessed
directly from a class without instantiating
an object of the class first.
Normally member variables are unique
to each object of a class.
While every object of a class has the same
variables they each have their own values.
With static variables however each object
of the class has the same variable with the same value.
Therefore changing the value of a static
variable in one place will result in a change
of value in all of the others.
Say that you wanted to know how many objects
of an enemy class had been instantiated.
An easy way to accomplish this would be to use
a static member variable named enemyCount.
By putting the keyword 'static' in the
declaration of a member you are declaring that
it is static and thus will belong to the class
itself not any instance of the class.
Then all you need to do is increment
the variable whenever an enemy object is created.
Since every object increments the same variable
it will contain the total number of
all enemies created.
Accessing the static variable is also
a fairly simple endeavour.
Here we have a game class that creates a few enemies.
To find out how many enemies were created
we simply need to access the enemyCount
static variable by using the classes
name and the dot operator.
In this case the enemyCount variable equals 3.
This process works for scripts intended to be game
object components as well.
For example, if we wanted to know the number
of players created in a scene we could
create a player script component.
In this script we could declare a static
playerCount variable and in the start method
we could increment it.
Now any time a game object with this
script attached to it is created the total
player count increases.
In another script component we can access
this static variable using the name of the script
and the dot operator.
Just like static variables, static methods are
methods that belong to the class and not a
specific object of the class.
A very simple example of this would be if you have
a class called Utilities, and inside the class
you have a static method called Add that
return the result of adding two numbers together.
You can tell that the method Add is static
by the 'static' keyword in front of it.
Now in another class you can call the Add
method using just the name of the class and the
dot operator. You do not need to
instantiate and object of the class
to use it's static members.
Chances are you have already used static methods
even if you haven't realised it.
Consider any time you have worked with Input in Unity.
Methods like Input.GetAccess,
Input.GetKey and Input.GetButton
are all static methods.
You can tell that they are static because you didn't
need to instantiate an object of the input class
in order to use them.
In fact, Unity has many static
methods available to you that provide a wide
assortment of utilities and features.
It is important to note that you cannot use
non-static class member variables
inside of static methods.
Remember that a static method belongs to the class
while non-static variables belong
to the instances of the class.
You can also make an entire class static.
To do so simply put the static keyword
in front of the class name.
The result is that the class becomes static
and cannot have instances of it created.
This is useful if you wish to make a class completely
make up of static member variables and methods
like the input class.