The Ternary Operator is a condensed form
for an If Else statement.
In it's most basic form the ternary operator
is used for deciding between two values
based on some Boolean expression.
The syntax has the format
Boolean ? true expression : false expression.
The first parameter is the Boolean, or condition
which evaluates to a Boolean
that you wish to test.
The end of this parameter is marked
with a question mark.
The next parameter is the value of the ternary
operator would evaluate to if the condition
is true. This is followed by a colon.
Then the final parameter is the value that
the ternary operator would evaluate to if
the condition is false.
Here we use a simple ternary operator
to determine if a player is alive or dead.
Ternary operators can be nested within
one another but if used for long expressions
this can make code cumbersome and difficult to read.
A general rule for when to use a ternary operator
instead of an If Statement is if your code
needs a simple If Else structure with
a single short expression in each case.