Now that we've finished our game we need to
present it to our players.
One of the greatest things about Unity is that
once we have created our game we can deploy
it to many of the current platforms.
For more detailed information on building and
build targets please see the lesson linked below.
Before we build our game we should
save our scene.
To build our game we must first open
the Build Settings window.
We can do this by selecting File - Build Settings
or by using the key combination of
shift plus command or control plus B.
This brings up the Build Settings window.
Our current build target is indicated by the Unity logo.
The blue highlight indicates our focus and
shows us on the right hand side the build
options for the currently selected platform.
We want to build to the web player.
Our current build target is PC, Mac and
Linux Standalone.
To change build targets, select the desired platform
from the list and click the Switch Platform button
at the bottom of the window.
Once we have selected our new build target
we need to add the scenes we want to build
to the Build Settings window.
We can add the current scene by clicking the
Add Current button.
Or we can drag and drop any scene from our
project view in to the field at the top of
the Build Settings window.
It's worth noting that we don't need to
include every scene in our project.
We only need to include the scenes we
we want in our game.
It is also possible to perform a build
with no scenes in the build Settings window.
If we do this, Unity will simply build our game
using the current scene we have open for editing.
Now we are ready to build our game.
Let's return to the Build Settings window
and click the Build button.
This will bring up a dialogue box asking us
to choose a build location.
I like to associate my build location with
my project, so I will create a new folder
inside my project called Builds.
This folder must be placed only on the
root of our project alongside the
assets and library folders.
With the build folder selected let's name the build
and then click save.
Unity will now build the web player and
save it to our Builds folder
When building a web player Unity creates a
folder with the name of our game
and in that folder are 2 files.
1 is the Unity3D data file,
which contains the game data,
and an HTML file which holds the code
to make a webpage with our game embedded in it.
We must have both the data file and the HTML file
to run our game in a browser.
However we can write a custom HTML file
to replace the page build by Unity.
It is also possible to create a custom
web player template which Unity can use to build
that custom page automatically.
To run the game open the HTML file.
And now we are running a local copy of the
game in our browser.
To present this to our audience we need
to place both the HTML file and the
data file up on the internet.
I'm going to open an FTP client and
place the folder with both the HTML file and
the data file in it up on my website.
When the folder has been uploaded we can simply
enter the address in to our browser
and play our game.
And, we win!
So in these assignments we have learned how to
create new game objects,
how to position them in the scene,
add new components to them,
write our own custom behaviours for them
using simple scripting.
We've seen how to use lights, cameras,
colliders, triggers, rigid bodies.
We can collect and count objects.
Though this is a very simple example
it covers a large set of basic
subjects important to understanding how to use Unity.
For continued learning about Unity
check the Learn site for more lessons,
assignments and projects.