Generics are a feature where by classes
and methods, amongst other things, can be
parsed a type as a parameter.
This in effect allows you to programme generically
without knowing the exact type of the
data you will be working with.
We have seen before that the GetComponment method
uses a generic parameter to get the type
of the component that it is looking for.
GetComponent is what is known as a generic method.
Let's take a look at creating one.
Here we have an example of a simple generic method.
The first thing to look at is it's generic parameter.
This is named T and is enclosed in angled brackets
after the method's name and before the normal
or formal parameters.
Since this T could represent any type
it's name is arbitrary, but most use the letter
T by convention.
Similarly if you wish to have multiple generic
parameters you can use a comma to add more.
The naming convention usually follows that
parameters after T are U and then V.
Though generic functions are not limited to only
three parameters it is quite uncommon to see one
with more than three.
We now know that the generic type associated with
this method is T.
T is only a placeholder though, and will end up
being an actual type when the method is called.
What ever type T ends up being will also
be the return type and the argument type
for the method since both of those use
T as their type.
Even though we have a method that works
with a generic type it's currently not very useful.
So what can we do with a generic type?
Well since we don't know how this generic type will
act we can't do much with it.
This generic parameter could be anything from a
float to a monobehaviour and more.
Since we don't know what it is there aren't many
operations we can perform on it.
We cannot, for example, multiply our
monobehaviour by two and we can't access
the game object field of a float.
Right now it's just treated as though it
were the class object, which is the base class
that all C# classes implicitly inherit from.
So how do we perform more operations?
In order to know some of the features of the type
we have to limit what types it can be by
placing a constraint on the generic parameter.
To add constraints to our function we type
where after the parameters
but before the function body.
This is followed by the generic type we are going
to constrain, in our case T and then a colon.
After the colon we have the specific
constraints separated by commas.
The constraints generally fall in to four categories.
You can use either the keyword 'class' to
make sure T is a reference type
or the keyword 'struct' to make sure it's a value type.
You can use the keyword 'new' followed by
a pair of parenthesis to ensure that it has
a public constructor with no parameters
You can use a class name to say that T
is that class or via polymorphism
any class that derives from it.
The last category of constraints is interfaces.
You can use an interface name to say that T
has implemented that interface.
In order to use a generic method you must
specify what type you want it to use.
Let's say you wanted to use the generic method
you just created.
In another class you would write the name of the method
followed by the angle brackets and the type you want.
You would then follow that with a parenthesis
and any arguments.
All of the features that we've discussed apply to
generic classes and interfaces as well as methods.
By giving a class generic types you
can effect the types of fields, properties
and methods within it.
Making generic classes is one of the more common
uses of generics and makes it very easy
to implement data structures.
Let's take a look at a generic class now.
This class uses a generic type of T.
This means that every instance of the type T
used as a type in the class will
be replaced by an actual type when it is used.
This class has a single member variable
named 'item' that is of type T.
The class also has a method called UpdateItem
that takes in a single argument of type T
and assigns it to the member item.
In order to instantiate an object of this class
you must specify a type for T.
You do this by typing the name of the class
followed by angled brackets and the type you want.
You must also do this after typing the name of
the constructor and before the constructor's parameter list.
One of the most common uses of generics is for
collections like dictionaries and lists.
For more information on dictionaries and lists
see the lesson linked below.