With inheritance members of the parent class are
automatically available, or inherited
in a child class.
Recreating, otherwise known as redeclaring
members of a parent class in the child class
is known as member hiding.
Hiding a member requires a lightly different
use of the keyword new.
In order to hide a member of a base class
the child classes member should be
declared with new before the type of the member.
Under normal circumstances this doesn't
effect the use of members declared in this way.
However, when a child class is upcast to a
parent class and the member is used
it will be the member from the parent class
despite the instance being a child class.
Consider an inheritance hierarchy
where Orc inherits from Enemy, which in turn
inherits from Humanoid.
In humanoid we have the method Yell,
which plays an audio clip and moves the model's arms.
In Enemy we have another function called Yell
which this time changes the colour of the
enemy's main texture to yellow
and has been declared using new.
Orc also has a new Yell function
but this time it sets the destination
of the nav mesh to a Northern Shetland Isle.
Suppose we have a collection of Humanoid objects
which includes some Humanoids,
some Enemies and some Orcs.
If we call the Yell function on all of
the objects in the collection
each of them will call the Humanoid version of Yell.
This is because we declared the Orc and Enemy
object as Humanoid and they have
been implicitly upcast to a Humanoid.
This sort of behaviour is not usually desired
and is therefore not commonly used
though it is important to be aware of.
In fact, this behaviour is the exact opposite of overriding.
More information on Overriding can be found
in the lesson on Overriding linked below.