Overriding is the practice of changing a
parent class method in a child class.
The result is that when we call the method
the newest or most overridden version of
the method is called.
When working with inheritance hierarchies
we often want to use slightly different versions
of functions from base classes.
Doing so is easy, you simply have
to recreate the method in the child class
and write it to do what ever it needs to do.
Consider a situation where we have a Humanoid base class
which has an Enemy derived class
which in turn has an Orc derived class.
The Humanoid class has a function called Yell.
When Yell is called by a Humanoid the model makes a
yelling noise and puts his hands up to cup around it's mouth.
The Yell method is automatically inherited
by the Enemy class, however we want to modify it.
We want the Enemy to attract other Enemies.
We also want Orc to be able to call this function.
But when Yell is called from an Orc object
all of the Orcs in the area get a bonus to
their attacks for a short time.
What we effectively need to do it
override the parent version of the Yell method
in each of the child classes.
Unity will warn us when we attempt to override
a parent method in a child class.
In order to suppress that warning
and tell Unity that we meant to override the method
we use the virtual and override keywords.
These keywords go before the return type of the method.
The method in the parent class is defined
as virtual, and the methods in all of the
children classes are defined as override.
Any method that is declared virtual can be overridden
by any child class.
A more interesting use of overriding
would be if you wanted each child class to
add specific functionality to a method
without losing the original functionality
provided by the parent.
In order to do this you need to use the base
keyword to call the parent version
of the method as well.
In our previous example, let's say we wanted
Enemy to keep the functionality of Humanoid
while adding it's own effect.
We also want Orc to keep the functionality of Enemy
To accomplish this we would need
to put a base call to the parent Yell method
in both Enemy and Orc.
Now when the Orc Yell method is called
it will call Enemy's Yell method which in turn
will call Humanoid's Yell method.
Overriding is also very useful with polymorphism.
By declaring the parent method as virtual
and the child method as override we will
effectively override the parent version of the method.
The result is that when we upcast a child
reference in to a parent object
and then call a method the child version
of that method will be called.