It is common to need a way to access
the member variables of a class from code that
exists outside of the class.
One way you could do this would be to make the
variables public and just access them directly.
This is sufficient, but there is a better way.
That better way is Properties.
Properties themselves act like variables
and encapsulate member variables, which we call Fields.
This encapsulation gives us a greater amount of
control over when and how a field is accessed
Say we had a field named Experience that existed
in the class Player and we wanted a way
for code existing outside of the class
to access it.
We would want to create a property.
The syntax for a property works like this.
First you specify the access modifier.
Then you specify the type,
followed by the name of the property.
A good rule is to name the property the same
thing as the field, except with a capital letter.
After the name of the property you place open
and closed braces, just like a function.
Inside these braces goes the properties accessors.
A property can have two accessors,
Get and Set.
These are the functions that are called when a property
is referenced and allocated to respectively.
They are declared using the keywords get
and set followed by braces
Within the get accessor we return the
field that we're encapsulating.
In the set accessor we allocate to the field
using the keyword Value.
That is all that is required to implement a property.
Now in another script we can use the property
in place of the field exactly as we would do normally.
You might be wondering why you would go through
the process of creating a property when you could have just
used the the public variable to begin with?
There are two things you can do with properties that you cannot
do with public variables.
The first is that by omitting either the get
or the set you can effectively make
the field write only or read only.
If the field is private you cannot read
it without a get accessor, and you cannot
write to it without a set accessor.
The second is that accessors can also be
treated just like functions.
That means that you can run other lines of code
or put calls to other functions in them.
An extension of this idea is to start
co-routienes using the set accessor.
The field encapsulation need not be direct.
Consider a game where the player gains experience
and levels up after every 1000 experience points.
If you had a field to represent the experience points
you could have a property to represent the level
of the player.
Instead of returning the number of experience points
the level properties get accessor could return
the experience field divided by 1000.
Thus it would return the numerical level
and not the amount of experience the player has.
Further more the level property could have a
set accessor that receives a level
and calculates the amount of experience the player
would have and stores that in the experience field.
Another feature of properties is that they can be
autoimplimented.
To create an autoimplimented property you
would use a shorthand syntax.
In this syntax the get and set accessors
are followed only by a semicolon.
Creating a property in this way makes it behave
exactly like a field, the difference being that
you can make a property read or write only by
removing either the get or set accessor.