In order to get our characters navigating around a scene
we first need to create a navmesh.
The act of creating a navmesh is called baking.
In Unity we can create a navmesh
using the navigation view.
To open the navigation view
click Window - Navigation.
The navigation view, like any other
window in Unity is fully resizable and dockable.
We can see that the navigation view is
broken up in to 3 tabs.
Object, Bake and Layers.
In order to bake a navmesh we must tell Unity
which objects are navigation static.
This means that those objects don't move
and can be used to calculate the walkable areas in a scene.
Objects that are usually navigation static
are things like floors, walls and static obstacles.
We specify these objects in the Object tab
on the navigation view by selecting the game object we want
and checking Navigation Status.
Alternatively we can set the
game object to navigation static
in the inspector view by clicking the
Static dop down and selecting Navigations Static.
The Off mesh Link generation
check box determines whether or not Unity will attempt
to create offmesh links.
More information on offmesh links
can be found in the lesson linked below.
Finally you can choose a navigation layer
for the selected object.
By default there are 3 layers,
default, not walkable and jump.
Layers will be covered in greater detail
later in this video.
We will want to continue applying the navigation
static checkbox to every game object
that should be factored in when calculating a navmesh.
We can use filters to change how
the objects appear in the hierarchy view
so that selecting objects becomes easier.
All will show us all objects.
Mesh Renderers will show us the objects that have
a mesh renderer component.
And Terrains will show us any terrain in the scene.
The Layers tab is where you can create and edit
different navigation layers.
Besides the 3 built-in layers
we can create several user-defined layers.
These layers can be given different cost
which will be factored in to navigation.
For instance, the default layer could constitute
a road where travelling is easy.
It has a cost of 1.
You could also have a Mud layer
which is much more difficult to walk on
and give it a weight of 3 for example.
This means that when calculating a path
characters are more likely to avoid objects
set to the Mud Layer because
it is more difficult to walk on.
The Bake tab is where we choose
our navmesh properties.
The radius determines close a character
can get to a wall or other obstacle.
It also defines the narrowest path a character can walk on
The Height property dictates how tall
the ceiling must be a for character
to walk below it.
For instance, even if there is a clear path
the ceiling might be too low for a character to pass.
Max Slope allows you to specify how steep
a slope must be before it is considered
a wall, and thus impassable.
The Step Height property determines
how tall an individual step or
bump can be before it will block a character.
The generated offmesh links properties
will be covered in detail in the lesson linked below.
There are also a few advanced settings you can use
but the defaults are fine for most situations.
The Min Region Area specifies the minimum area
a surface must have for it to be
included in the navmesh.
The Inaccuracy % properties
allows you to specify how accurate or
inaccurate the mesh will be around it's edges.
Finally you can choose to also have
a height mesh created.
This will improve movement accuracy
though it will make generation slower.
Once all of our properties are set
we will want to click the Bake button.
This will generate our navmesh.
When complete the navmesh will appear
as a blue layer.
All areas that are blue are walkable.
You should note that if you don't see the blue layer,
you should insure the show navmesh
option in the scene view is checked.