The Scroll Rect is a UI element that allows the
user to move another UI element along
the horizontal and/or vertical axis
This is usually a large image or a
panel of other UI elements, such as a list of
buttons or a large block of text.
This scroll rect is most often used
with a mask element.
And is designed to work seamlessly with scroll bars.
Masks and scroll bars with be covered in this lesson,
but only briefly.
For more detailed information on masks
and scroll bars please see the information linked below.
To create a scroll rect
add a scroll rect script to a game
object that is the child of canvas.
Like all UI elements, the scroll rect
must be the child of a  canvas/
One way to add the scroll rect's script
to the game object is to use Add Component.
UI
Scroll Rect.
For this example, the game object
will be renamed Scroll View.
Content is a referent to the rect transform
on the UI element being controlled be the scroll rect.
Associate
For example an image far larger
than the scroll rect.
Associate the content, in this case
the large image
with the content property on the scroll rect.
When in play mode this content is fully scrollable.
The scroll rect is commonly used with a mask element
To use a mask element with a scroll rect
first add an image script to the game object
for the mask to use.
And then add a mask script.
The mask element will use the image to
create it's mask
As specific image is not needed on the image script.
But one can be added for additional
control over the shape of the mask.
For more information on the image and mask elements
please see the information linked below.
Horizontal and vertical enables scrolling
along those axis.
To disable scrolling along one axis
set that axis property to false.
Movement type describes the scrolling mode.
The scrolling mode can be chosen by the
movement type pop-up menu.
Unrestricted allows for unrestricted scrolling movement.
This is not a common mode to choose
and it is entirely possible without
some additional method
to lose the content in a way that is irretrievable.
This mode however may prove to be useful
under certain circumstances.
When using either elastic or clamped
as the movement type
the content cannot leave the bounds of the scroll rect
on any of the scrollable axis.
In these two modes,
for the content to be scrollable,
the rect transform of the content must
be larger than the rect transform of the scroll rect.
If the rect transform of the content is
smaller than the rect transform of the scroll rect
it cannot be scrolled along that axis.
When positioning the content in either of these modes
it is best to position the content so
that it starts within the bounds of the scroll rect
or undesirable behaviour may occur.
as the rect transform tries to bring the
content back within it's bounds.
When using the movement type Elastic
the content will bounce when it reaches the
bounds of the scroll rect.
The amount of bounce is set by the
elasticity property.
When using the movement type Clamped
the content will not bounce when it reaches the
bounds, it will simply stop scrolling.
Inertia defines whether or not the
content will continue to glide when releasing
the pointer after a  drag.
When inertia is false the content
will only move when dragged.
If inertia is set to true the
content will continue to glide after the pointer
has ended the drag.
How soon the content stops gliding
is determined by the deceleration rate property.
A deceleration rate of 0 means
the gliding will stop instantly.
The value of 1 means the gliding will
never slow down.
Horizontal and vertical scroll bars
are optional references to potential scroll bar elements.
To use scroll bars with a scroll rects
simply create the scroll bars needed,
position them,
and associate the scroll bars with properties
on the scroll rect.
They will work automatically.
For more information on scroll bars and how to set them up
please see the information linked below.