The button element detects user input and can trigger an event.
User input is usually the pointer
hovering over or clicking on the button graphic.
To create a pre-made button use the
Create menu to Create - UI - Button.
Like all UI elements the button element must
be the child of a canvas.
If one is not present when creating a pre-made button
a new canvas will be created.
For more information on the canvas
please see the information linked below.
A button element requires an Image script
and a Button script.
Pre-made button elements also include
an optional text element attached as a child.
This text element is optional
and can be removed if the button does not need
any additional text.
For more information on the image and text items
please see the infuriation linked below.
Inter-actable determines whether or not
this particular button will accept input.
To prevent interaction with this button
set Inter-actable to False.
When Inter-actable is set to False
the transition state for this button element
will be set to the Disabled stated.
By default the button element will display
the normal state of the button.
The look of the normal state is automatically
set by the image component attached
to the button element.
Depending upon the transition mode chosen
a button can also display a highlighted,
pressed and disabled state.
Transition Mode determines whether or not
the button element will display any of
these additional states, and if so
controls the button's look in each state,
and the style of the transition between these states.
A highlighted state is set when the pointer is
hovering over the button element.
Or the button element is selected using
keyboard or controller navigation.
The Pressed state is when the button is being held down.
Pressed, but not released.
The Disabled state is set when the button
element is not inter-actable.
The look and behaviour of these other transition states,
if available, are determined by the Transition Mode.
The transition mode can be set with a
transition pop-up menu.
None will have no additional states
and therefore no transitions.
The button element will work as expected
but there will be no visual feedback
and the unaltered normal state will be
displayed at all times.
colorTint is the default transition mode.
In this mode the same graphical element
is used for each state.
Target Graphic is the image component to be tinted.
In almost all cases this will be the image
component attached to the button element.
The button script will set this reference to the
attached image component automatically
if the image component is attached to the game
object when the button script is added.
Normal, Highlighted, Pressed and Disabled color
define the tint color that will be applied
to the target graphic when the button
is in each of these states.
color Multiplier multiplies the tint color for
each transition by it's value.
This allows for colors greater than 1,
which is useful for brightening the colors
or alpha channel on some graphic elements
whose base color is less than white
or less than full alpha.
Fade Duration is the time, in seconds,
a transition takes between states.
SpriteSwap will use different sprite
images for each state
and swaps them depending upon the state of the button.
In this mode a new graphical element is
required for each state.
Target Graphic is the image for the normal state.
In almost all cases this will be the image
component attached to the button element.
The highlighted, pressed and disabled sprites
are references to the sprite images
to be displayed for each state.
Animation allows for each transition to be
fully animated using Unity's animation system.
This is the most powerful of transition modes
due to the number of properties that can be
animated simultaneously.
To use the animation transition mode
and animator component needs to be attached
to the button element.
To add this animator component automatically
and generate an animator controller
with states already setup
click Auto Generate Animation.
The new animator controller will need to be saved.
No action needs to be taken with this new animator controller.
The transition between states can be
customised if desired, but this is not necessary.
For more information on the Animator Component
and the Animator Controller
please see the information linked below.
It is worth noting that, unlike most animator controllers
this controller will also store the animations
for the button's transitions.
With the animator controller attached
and the button element selected
the animations for each of these button's states
can be edited by opening the animation window.
The animation window can be found under
Window - Animation.
Or by using the shortcut keys of
command 6 on the mac
or control 6 on windows.
To select the state to be edited
use the animation clip pop-up menu
to select the desired clip.
With these pre-made controllers there should be a
state for Normal, Highlighted, Pressed and Disabled.
In most cases the normal state will be left empty
with no animation keyframes created
as the normal state will be set
by the values on the button element itself.
On all other states
the most common configuration for each state
is a single keyframe at 0 seconds
or the start of the timeline.
The transition animation between states
will be handled by the animator controller
as it fades between states.
For example, the width of the button
in the highlighted state could be changed
by selecting the state to be edited, in this case
Highlighted from the animation clip pop-up menu.
And with the playhead at 0 seconds
or the start of the timeline.
Selecting the Record button.
Changing the width of the button in the inspector
And exiting record mode.
When in Play mode, note how the button
now grows when highlighted.
It is worth noting that any number of properties
can have their values set in this one keyframe.
For more information on animation, animation clips,
and the animation window please see the
information linked below.
If several buttons share the same behaviour
these button elements can share animator controllers.
Make sure all of these buttons have their
transition modes set to Animation.
And that they all have an animator component attached.
Finally, associate the shared animator controller
with all of the button elements.
When in play mode
note how all of the buttons now share
the same animator transitions.
Navigation describes how the selection
of UI elements is handled
when using keyboard or controller input.
Navigation is shared by many UI elements
and will be covered in it's own lesson.
For most circumstances navigation
can simply be set to Automatic.
For more information on navigation
please see the information linked below.
The UI framework contains
a powerful event system.
A new event system is added to the
scene when the canvas is created.
When the event system detects a press
and a release over the same button element
the event system will process a click
and the On Click event will be called.
The button component includes a built-in
On Click functions list that contains
a list of all the functions that are called
when the button is clicked.
Additional events can be detected
and used by the button element.
Like when the pointer enters or exits
the area over the button element.
But this requires an additional component to be attached.
For more information on events, the event system and
event triggers please see the information linked below.
All of the functions in the functions list
will be called when the button is clicked.
To add a new function to the function list
click the + icon to create a new row in the list.
To remove a function from the function list
click on the row containing the function
even if there is only one
and then click the - icon to remove it.
Looking at a row in the function list.
The checkbox indicates whether or not
this function will be called by the On Click event.
The first field is an object field.
Associating a game object with the object field
will allow the event system to find all the functions
on that game object eligible to
be called by the On Click event.
This can be done by either using the object picker
or by dragging the object in to the field.
The function list shows all of the components
on the game object, including both the built-in
components and custom scripts.
After selecting the desired component
a new list shows the eligible functions
on the component.
Select the function that will be called by the On Click event.
The final field is a parameter field.
This field is for parsing an argument
in to the function when it is called,
and can be left empty.
To be eligible a function must be public,
have the return type of Void,
and have 1 or no parameters.
If the function has a parameter it must be a
float, int, string, bool or a Unity object.
It is worth noting that Unity object
is the base of almost all classes in Unity
including game object, component,
mono behaviour and more.
This makes the object parameter more powerful
than expected at first glance
as it can accept many items as an argument.
If the parameter is a float, int or string
the value needs to be entered in the parameter field
If the parameter is an object
an object needs to be associated with the parameter field.
This can be done by either using the object picker
or by dragging the object in to the field.
If the parameter is a bool
a checkbox will appear and the bool parameter
can be set by checking on unchecking the box.
As an example we can add the sphere
as the game object to the first row,
select the mesh renderer,
and then set the mesh renderer's material
The parameter needs an object reference
we can choose any available material.
At the same time the On Click event could
call a second function,
this time on the capsule.
Using the game object itself, the On Click event
could call Set Active
with the value of False.
The most common function to call will
most likely be a custom one.
Custom functions need to be public,
void,
and have 1 or no parameters.
If the function has a parameter it
must be a float, int, string
bool or a Unity object.
The script must be attached to a game object.
And that game object must be associated with the object field.
The custom script will be visible in the list
and from the custom script the custom
function can be selected.
If there are no parameters
the parameter field can be left blank.
Now in play mode
the effect of all three functions can be seen
when the button is clicked.