canvas は、UI要素のグループが
レンダリングされる方法を制御するコンポーネントです。
すべてのUI要素は、canvas の子でなければなりません。
シーン内に複数の canvas を持つことも可能です。
UI要素を使用するためには、少なくとも1つの使用可能な
canvas が存在する必要があります。
If a new UI element is created
and no canvas exists
a new canvas will be created
and the new UI element will be attached
to that canvas as a child.
Each canvas has a number of different
possible render modes.
The render mode can be set by using
the Render Mode pop-up menu.
Scene Space - Overlay is the most common render mode
and it is the default render mode setting
for a canvas.
With Screen Space - Overlay selected
the UI will overlay the scene.
And all of the UI elements will be drawn
on top of
everything else rendered in that scene.
In this mode the canvas will
fill the screen automatically
and will resize automatically if
the screen settings change.
It is worth noting that in Screen Space - Overlay mode
the canvas will drive the Rect Transform component.
And the entire rect transform component
is uneditable.
The canvas will set all of the values
in the rect transform to fill the screen automatically.
For more information on the rect transform component
please see the information linked below.
This render mode has the option of Pixel Perfect.
When Pixel Perfect is selected UI elements
will be adjusted to the nearest pixel when they are rendered.
Which can, in some cases, sharpen the look
of the UI element.
Screen Space - Camera is very similar
to Screen Space - Overlay.
It is, however, rendered by a specific
camera in the scene.
This will allow camera-specific settings to be
applied to a screen space UI.
The most common being the use of a perspective camera
to give the UI a feeling of depth.
In this mode the canvas will fill the
camera's viewport automatically
and will resize automatically if the camera's
viewport settings change.
In this render mode the rect transform
is also being driven entirely by the canvas.
This render mode has several options,
including Pixel Perfect,
which acts just the same as in screen space - overlay.
Render Camera is for setting the camera
that will render the UI elements on this canvas.
If this is none, the canvas component will use the
screen space - overlay settings
to render this canvas.
When Screen Space - Camera is selected
and a camera is assigned to the canvas component
the UI elements will be moved
in to the camera's frustum and resized to fit.
This allows for the UI to be rendered relative
to game object in the scene view.
To control where in the scene the UI
elements will be rendered use Plane Distance
to move the canvas closer to,
or further away from, the camera.
The canvas and it's UI elements will be
automatically resized to fit the frustum
based on their position in front of the camera.
It is worth noting that the plane distance must
be within the rendering camera's near and far
clipping planes to be rendered.
When using Screen Space - Camera
the canvas can be rendered by any camera in the scene.
To isolate a canvas and it's contents
from any other cameras rendering the scene
use the camera's clear flags culling mask
and depth properties.
For more information on how to use these
camera properties please see the information
on cameras linked below.
Render Mode World Space renders UI elements
in the scene volume.
These UI elements could be static objects in the scene
or mobile objects like speech bubbles
or player tags that follow game objects in the scene.
The first thing to note about a canvas in world space mode
is that the canvas no longer drives the rect transform
and the canvas can be set anywhere in world space.
With the understanding that there can be more than
one canvas in the scene it is not uncommon to go
create new world space canvas' as necessary for
world space UI elements.
Event Camera is required to received
events and determine which camera will be used
to detect events like clicking on a UI element.
In most cases, with screen space world selected
this event camera will be the camera rendering the scene.
Receives Events indicates whether the
UI elements on this canvas will
receive events like clicks and hovers.
Disable this property to ignore events on
all UI elements that are children of this canvas.
Sorting Order and Order in Layer are
for controlling the render order of the canvas
when compared to other renderers in the scene.
Sorting Order and Order in Layer are exposed on the
canvas component and are available for
canvas' set to either screen space - camera
or world space.
For more information on Sorting Layers
and Order in Layer please see the information linked below.
UI elements on a canvas will be rendered
in a top-down order,
where the first items are rendered at the back
and lower items are rendered later and appear on top.
To change the order in which a UI element renders
simply change it's order in the hierarchy