Often, when using UI elements in a scene
we want them to be interact-able.
A user interacts with UI elements via events.
This lesson covers generating and handling those events.
Whenever a canvas is created in a scene
an Event System game object is also created.
This game object has components including an
event system component and one or more input module components.
When a scene starts, the event system looks for input modules
on the same game object, and uses those to
define how each UI element should react to input.
The event system itself has one property
First Selected.
All interact-able UI elements can be selected and
whichever element is applied to this property
will be selected by default when the scene starts.
We could, for example, apply a button to this property.
Then, when we start the scene,
we can see that it has changed colour slightly
indicating that it is selected.
When we press the space bar we see that the button
becomes pressed without needing to click on it with the mouse.
This is useful for non-pointer based menu systems,
such as those used with game pads.
Along with the event system components
there are by default two input modules.
One for standalone builds that make use of a mouse,
keyboard or game pads,
and one for touch input.
The standalone input module has a series of properties
that refer to the different input axis
used for navigating different interact-able UI elements.
These input axis include the Submit and Cancel buttons.
These have been added by default to the input manager.
For more information on navigating between interact-able UI elements
please see the information linked below.
The frequency of input being registered can be changed
using the input actions per second property.
By default 10 input actions are allowed per second.
This means that there will be a 10th of a second delay
after an input action before the next action is accepted.
The last property allows you to accept standard
alone input whilst on a mobile device.
By default the standalone input module
will not function on a mobile device.
Since touch input works like mouse input
there are no navigation axis.
However, like the standalone input module
you can activate the touch input module
while on a standalone device.
There event system and input modules
determine when events are sent, or fired,
to different game objects.
One such event is the OnClick event,
which is called when a button is pressed.
Specifically the selected button must have a pointer down
and a subsequent pointer up event
while over the button's rect
for an OnClick event to occur.
For details on all of the input events
see the documentation linked below.
There are many ways to use these events.
Some interact-able UI elements have function lists
on their components that are called when
a specific event pertinent to that element is fired.
For example, button components have lists of functions
to be called when the OnClick event is fired.
To catch a specific event that is not listed
on a component by default
use the Event Trigger component.
This works like any of the other lists
for other components, however, the event trigger component
can have multiple lists for which ever events are desired.
For instance, an image control
does not utilise any specific events.
To allow it to use events with the event trigger component
first add the component by clicking
Add Component and then Event and then Event Trigger.
To add a new event click the Add New button.
This will give you a list of all of the different
available events to catch.
Select one of the events and a list for that event
will be added to the component.
To add a function to the list click the + icon.
This will create  an empty entry for a function to be called.
Drag an object that you wish to manipulate with this event
on to the object property in the list.
Once the object has been applied the drop down will
be populated with all of the available functions to be called.
As you can see, many components have functions
that you can call with these events.
You can even call functions on scripts that you write.
In order for an event to call a function
that function must be public, have a void return type
and take one or no parameters.
If the function has a parameter
it must be one of the following types:
float, integer, string or an object reference.
And that's it, your event is setup and ready to go.