The image component is used to give UI elements
actual graphical presence on the screen.
Images can be used to make up the backgrounds of
buttons, panels, sliders and literally anything you want
to put in to your UI composition.
The first property of an image component is the source image.
This is a reference to the sprite that the image
is displaying, when using None, the color will be used
to represent the outline of the image.
Here we simply have a white image color,
so let's add a sprite to our source image.
The next property is the color.
This color is multiplied to the color of the sprite.
As such it can be used for fading
or tinting a sprite.
By default an images doesn't need a material.
But one can be added if you wish to use the
properties of a shader on the image.
Note that the texture property of a material
will be ignored.
Unity provides a number of shaders that can be
used with the UI system.
To use them create a material
and for it's Shader property select
one from the uGUI menu in the Shader drop-down.
The Image Type property effects how
the source image is used
and has a number of options.
Simple means that the sprite will just stretch to
fit the rect transform's size.
The Preserve Aspect option here simply means
that the image will be as large as it can be
within it's bounding rect,
but maintaining the aspect ratio that
it was imported with.
This means that it won't lose it's original proportions
as it's resized.
The Set Native Size button is available
whilst using this option also.
It will revert the rect transform's size
to the size of the sprite in it's source image.
Here you can see that our rect has been reverted
to the 64 square size of our sprite.
Sliced means that the image will be displayed
using the 9 sliced method.
A 9 sliced sprite is separated
in to 9 sections in a grid pattern.
The outer border sections of this grid do not stretch
whilst the centre does,
allowing for scaling without distortion of the edges.
These sections are defined by the Borders Set
in the sprite editor for the texture.
For more information on the sprite editor
see the information linked below.
The Sliced option also has another property
Fill Centre.
This toggles whether or not the centre section
of the 09 sliced sprite is shown.
This allows you to design and render
borders only of an image.
The Tiled option will tile the source image
starting from the lower-left corner of the rect.
In this example we're using an un-sliced sprite.
The next image type is Filled.
This type allows you to show a proportion of the image
defined by the Fill Amount property.
At 0 none of the image will be shown
and at 1 all of it will be.
There are a number of sub-options when using
the filled image type.
The Fill Method along with the Fill Origin
determine which point represents the fill amount being 0
and in which direction the image will fill
as it increases.
For radial fill methods the fill origin defines
where the fill will be carried out from.
For the radial fill methods there is also the
option to switch between clockwise and anti-clockwise.
These fills are ideal for making UI for
health bars or car speedometers
in the case of radial fills.
For more information on the image component
see the information linked below.