The Mask element is for creating a shaped mask
over any UI element or family of UI elements.
A mask is often used in conjunction with a scroll rect.
Scroll rect's are good for moving oversized elements.
A mask element is then used to clip this
oversized content to the desired size.
For more information on the scroll rect
please see the information linked below.
Two items are needed to create a working mask.
A mask element, to create the mask,
and an image element to define the shape of the mask.
A graphical element does not need to be
assigned to the image for the mask to work.
If no graphical element is assigned
the mask will use the bounds of the
rect transform to clip the contents.
To change the shape of the mask
change the graphical element.
Show Mask Graphic is a toggle
and will toggle whether or not the graphical
element is displayed.
The graphical element does not need to be shown
for the mask to work.
For more information on the Image element
please see the information linked below.