The Slider is a UI element
that allows the user to select a numeric value
from a predetermined range of numbers
by dragging the handle of the slider control.
Common controls using a slider
include settings for audio volume, colour channels or brightness.
The slider element can also be repurposed
as a simple display for items like
health bars or volume meters.
The slider's value is set by the position
of the handle along the length of the slider.
The value starts at a minimum value
and increases up to a maximum value
defining a range between the two.
To create a new slider use the Create menu
to Create UI Slider.
Like all UI elements the slider element must be
the child of a canvas.
If one is not present when creating a pre-made slider
a new canvas will be created.
For more information on the canvas
please see the information linked below.
When the slider is created
it is made from a family of game objects.
The parent game object is where the required
slider script resides.
All of the children are the rect transform
and image components that make up the separate
elements of the slider control.
The elements that make up the slider
are the background graphic,
the fill graphic, which indicated the relative value chosen,
and the handle, which displays a
handle at the location of the chosen value.
The background and handle elements are optional.
Interact-able determines whether or not
this particular slider will accept input.
To prevent interaction with a slider
set Interact-able to false.
When interact-able is set to false
the transition state for the slider element
will be set to the disabled state.
By default the slider element will display
the normal state of the slider.
Depending upon the transition mode chosen
a slider can also display a highlighted,
pressed and disabled state.
Transition Mode determines whether or not
the slider element will display any of
these additional states
and if so controls the slider's look
for each state and the style of the
transition between these states.
The transition mode property is shared
by many UI elements and will be covered
in it's own lesson.
For more information on transitions and
the transition mode property
please see the information linked below.
When using transitions with the slider element
it is worth noting that with the exception of
the animation transition
any visual change is only seen
on the handle graphic, not the rest of the UI element.
Navigation describes how the selection
of the UI elements is handled when using
keyboard or controller input.
Navigation is shared by many UI elements
and will be covered in it's own lesson.
For most circumstances navigation can
simply be set to Automatic.
For more information on navigation
please see the information linked below.
Fill Rect is a reference to the rect transform
on the graphic used for the filled area of the element.
The slider's current value is displayed
by the fill graphic.
Handle Rect is a reference to the rect transform
on the graphic used for the handle.
This is an optional reference and it can be none.
Direction sets both the axis and
the direction of the value change.
The Min Value will be at the
starting end of the direction.
For the choice of left to right
the min value will be at the left of the slider.
The value of the slider will increase proportionally as the
handle moves from left to right
and the Max value will be at the right.
The choices for direction are
LeftToRight, RightToLeft, BottomToTop and TopToBottom.
The range of the slider is determined by
the Min and Max values.
Min value is the minimum value of the range of the slider.
Max value is the maximum range of the slider.
Minimum value can be a negative number.
The minimum value however should be numerically
less than the maximum value
or aberrant behaviour could result with the slider.
Whole numbers will clamp the value of the slider to
whole numbers within the range from min to max value.
If the values in the min and max value
fields are not whole numbers
they will be adjusted to the closest whole
number when Whole Numbers is selected.
Value is the current value of the slider.
When value is set in the inspector during edit time
this will set the starting value for the slider.
The UI framework contains a powerful events system.
This is created automatically when the
canvas is created.
When the event system detects the mass
down on the slider,
either a click or a drag,
the event system will call an OnValueChanged event.
The slider component includes a built-in
OnValueChanged function list
that contains a list of all the functions
that are called when the slider value changes.
Additional events can be detected
and used by the slider element, but this
requires an additional component to be attached.
For more information on how to use the
built-in function list, events, the event system and event triggers
please see the information linked below.
To hook up the current value of the slider
to a component, first create a new row in
the built-in OnValueChanged list.
Associate the game object when the desired
script or component attached to the first object field.
Then using the function pull-down menu
choose first the component
then an eligible function on that component to be called.
It is worth noting that ever time the value
of the slider changes the OnValueChanged
event will be called.
To parse the current value of the slider
the eligible function needs to have a float parameter.
And this function must be chosen from the dynamic float list.
This is done by selecting the function from
the top part of the list, indicated by the label
Dynamic Float.
If the only functions in the list are under
the header Static Parameters
this means the functions do not have a float
parameter and won't be able to accept
the current value of the slider element.
The final field is a parameter field
And when the current value of the slider
is parsed as a dynamic float
this field should be left blank.
It is worth noting that the value of the slider
element can also be driven externally,
and the slider will display the current value
sent to the slider.
One classic example of this is the
simple health, mana or fuel bar.
In a script with a reference to the slider element.
The slider value can be set.
In these cases it would be best to
set the slider's interact-able value to false,
preventing any input on the slider.
And if desired, removing the handle graphic.