The transition property defines
how a UI element behaves in each state
and how it behaves when changing states.
The following lesson uses the button
element as an example, but transitions work the
same for each UI element with transitions.
By default the button element will display
the normal state of the button.
Depending upon the transition mode chosen
a button can also display a highlighted,
pressed and disabled state.
Transition Mode determines whether or not
the button element will display any of
these additional states
and if so controls the buttons look in each state
and the style of the transition between these states.
The highlighted state is set when the pointer is
hovering over the button element,
or the button element is selected using
keyboard or controller navigation.
The pressed state is when the button is
being held down, pressed but not released.
The disabled state is set when the button element
is not interact-able.
The look and behaviour of these other transition states,
if available, are determined by the transition mode.
The transition mode can be set with a
transition pop-up menu.
None will have no additional states
and therefore no transitions.
The button element will work as expected
but there will be no visual feedback
and the unaltered normal state will be
displayed at all times.
ColourTint is the default transition mode.
In this mode the same graphical element
is used for each state.
Target Graphic is the image component to be tinted.
Normal, Highlighted, Pressed and Disabled Colour
define the tint colour that will be applied
to the target graphic when the button
is in each of these states.
Colour Multiplier multiplies the tint colour
for each transition by it's value.
This allows for colours greater than 1,
which is useful for brightening the colours
or alpha channel on some graphic elements
who's base colour is less than white
or less than full alpha.
Fade Duration is the time in seconds
the transition takes between states.
Sprite Swap will use different sprite
images for each state
and swaps them depending upon the
state of the button.
In this mode a new graphical element
is required for each state.
Target Graphic is the image for the normal state.
The highlighted, pressed and disabled
sprites are references to the sprite images
to be displayed for each state.
Animation allows for each transition to be
fully animated using Unity's animation system.
This is the most powerful of transition modes
due to the number of properties that can be
animated simultaneously.
To use the animation transition mode
an animator component needs to be attached
to the button element.
To add this animator component automatically
and generate an animator controller
with states already setup
click Auto Generate Animation.
The new animator controller will need to be saved.
No action needs to be taken with this
new animator controller.
The transition between states can be
customised if desired, but this is not necessary.
For more information on the animator component
and the animator controller, please see the information linked below.
It is worth noting that unlike most animator controllers
this controller will also store the animations
for the button's transitions.
With the animator controller attached
and the button element selected the animations for
each of these button's states can be edited
by opening the Animation window.
The animation window can be found under
Window - Animation.
Or by using the shortcut keys of
Command 6 on the mac or
control 6 on windows.
To select the state to be edited
use the animation clip pop-up menu
to select the desired clip.
With these pre-made controllers there should
be a state for normal, highlighted, pressed and disabled.
In most cases the normal state
will be left empty with no animation keyframes
created as the normal state will
be set by the values on the button element itself.
On all other state the most common configuration
for each state is a single keyframe at 0 seconds
or the start of the timeline.
The transition animation between states
will be handled by the animator controller
as it fades between states.
For example the width of the button
in the highlighted state could be changed
by selecting the state to be edited,
in this case Highlighted from the
animation clip pop-up menu
and with the playhead at 0 seconds
or the start of the timeline
selecting the record button
changing the width of the button in the inspector
and exiting record mode.
When in play mode note how the
button now grows when highlighted.
It is worth noting that any number of properties
can have their values set in this one keyframe.
For more information on animation,
animation clips and the animation window
please see the information linked below.
If several buttons share the same behaviour
these button elements can share animator controllers.
Make sure all of these buttons have their transition
mode set to Animation.
And that they all have an animator component attached.
Finally associate the shared animator controller
with all of the button elements.
When in play mode
note how all of the buttons now share
the same animator transitions.