In Unity we can add buttons to
editor windows so that we can call the
functions from our scripts.
Doing so gives us the ability to
write scripts specifically to improve our workflow,
and that is always a good thing.
Here we have a script called ObjectBuilderScript
The purpose of this script is to instantiate
an object at any given point
using the BuildObject method.
First we declare a game object
named obj and a vector3 named spawnPoint.
These will contain the object being built
and the location to build it respectively.
After that we have our method BuildObject,
which handles instantiating our object.
We also have a custom inspector script
written for our object builder script
named ObjectBuilderEditor.
For more information on writing custom inspector scripts
see the lesson on custom inspectors linked below.
The first thing we have inside the
OnInspectorGUI method is the
DrawDefaultInspector function.
More information on this function can be found
in the lesson linked below.
Next we create a button which when clicked
will call the BuildObject method
of the ObjectBuilderScript.
To do this we first create a variable to
hold our ObjectBuilderScript reference
named myScript.
We set our myScript variable
equal to a cast of the inherited target variable.
Casting allow us to treat the target variable
as if it was an ObjectBuilderScript variable.
We then create our button by writing the
GUILayout class name
followed by a . and the Button function.
We parse in a single parameter,
which contains the text we want displayed on the button.
The Button function returns a boolean
that is true if the button is pressed.
Therefore we wrap the whole line up in an If statement.
Then when the If statement
evaluates to true we simply call the
BuildObject method of our myScript variable.
In Unity we have a scene with
an empty game object in it.
Attached to the game object is our
ObjectBuilderScript.
Notice in the inspector, in addition to the 2
fields we declared in the script
we also have a button that says Build Object.
If we click the Build Object button
we can see that an orb is created in the scene.
By changing the values of the Spawn Position field
we can keep building objects at various
places around the scene.
We can see that adding functions to our inspector
allows us to add a lot of custom
functionality when working in Unity.