The DrawDefaultInspector function allows us to easily
recreate the default inspector for a script
inside a custom inspector.
This is very useful if we only want to add
new items to the inspector for a script
instead of changing the currently existing items.
Let's take a look at an example.
Here we have a script called SomeScript.
This script contains an integer named level,
a float named health
and a vector named target.
We also have an editor script called SomeScriptEditor.
This script creates a custom inspector
for the SomeScript component.
We can see that the OnInspectorGUI method
has ben created but there's nothing inside.
For more information on creating custom inspectors
see the lesson on custom inspectors linked below.
In Unity we have a scene with
an empty game object in it.
This object has our SomeScript attached to it.
We should notice that even though SomeScript
has 3 public variables
nothing is appearing in the inspector view for it.
This is due to the custom inspector existing
but having no graphical user interface code.
Back in our SomeScriptEditor
we could write out all of the code required
to display public variables in the inspector.
But that is cumbersome and requires a lot of work.
This is especially true if we do not want to
customise how they appear.
Instead we can replace all of that code
with the DrawDefaultInspector function.
This function will create all of the default
inspector fields whilst still allowing
us to add any custom elements we would like.
If we go back in to Unity
we can now see that our SomeScript fields
appear correctly in the inspector
with barely any extra work.
Our script is now primed to add any
new functionality we may desire.
Let's demonstrate that by adding a
HelpBox to our inspector.
Back in our SomeScriptEditor
we can add a HelpBox in the OnInspectorGUI method.
We do that by typing the editor GUI
layout class name, followed by a .
and the method name HelpBox.
We will parse 2 parameters in to the HelpBox method.
The first is the text that we want
to appear in the HelpBox.
The second is the type of HelpBox we want.
This is an enumeration that allows us to
choose Error, Info, None or Warning.
Back in Unity we can now see that
the HelpBox appears in our inspector
along with all of our other script fields.