In Unity we can utilise the built-in navigation system
to give our characters intelligent and accurate movement.
Using this system we can have player
and non-player characters alike
moving around in our 3D environments in no time.
Traditional navigation around 3D objects in a scene
is slow and inefficient due to the complexities of the models.
That is why Unity employs something called a Navmesh.
A navmesh is a very simply 3D mesh which is derived
from the geometry of more complicated elements in a scene.
This more basic navmesh is much easier to
navigate and path-find within.
The process of creating a navmesh,
often called baking,
is achieved through the navigation view
in the Unity editor.
For more information on baking meshes
see the lesson linked below.
Once the navmesh has been created
a navmesh agent component allows any game object
to find a path around the scene and move accordingly.
Simply apply the component and tell it where to go
using the navmesh agent's scripting AVI.
For more information on navmesh agent components
see the lesson linked below.
Navigation can also be enhanced
by the use of off-mesh links to control
movement across meshes
and navmesh obstacles to get in your character's way.
For more information on off-mesh links
and navmesh obstacles can be found
in the lessons linked below.