Game objects that are part of a navmesh
are a great way to build static walls in to a scene.
But what if we wanted moving object
that would block a character's path?
For that we would want to use
a navmesh obstacle.
Unlike game objects that are marked as navigation static
and baked in to a navmesh
navmesh obstacles are able to
block paths dynamically.
Some examples of navmesh obstacles
might be openable doors or moving blockades.
For more information on navmeshes
see the lesson on navmesh baking linked below.
Here we have a scene with a capsule in it.
The capsule has a navmesh agent attached.
The capsule also has a script on it
that will move it towards our target game object.
For more information on navmesh agents
see the lesson linked below.
Also in our scene is a teddy bear model.
This teddy bear is not navigation static
and therefore is not baked in to the navmesh.
Still, we would like this teddy bear
to block the path of any navmesh agents in our scene.
To add a navmesh obstacle
component to a game object
click the Add Component button and select
Navigation - Nav Mesh Obstacle
The Radius and Height properties of the
navmesh obstacle component
determine the dimensions of the cylinder
that will block the character's path.
We will talk about the Move Threshold property in a moment.
The Carve option determines whether or not
the obstacle will create a temporary hole in a navmesh.
With this selected we can see that the obstacle
creates an impassable spot in our navmesh.
The way this works is thus.
Let's say that a navmesh obstacle
is blocking a narrow walkway.
If Carve is selected a navmesh agent
will avoid that walkway when calculating it's path.
If Carve is not selected
then the agent may attempt to travel that pathway
but it will not be able to pass.
The Move Threshold property
is only used if Carve is enabled.
This property dictates how far
the navmesh obstacle must move
before the hole in the navmesh
is recalculated.
With an obstacle in the way
we can run our scene.
We will notice that the navmesh agent
avoids the obstacle while moving towards it's target.