Many times in Unity you will want to connect
2 navmeshes together to allow characters
to move between them.
For example, you may want to allow
a character to jump over a gap in the ground
or drop down from an elevated height.
We can achieve this effect using off mesh links.
Off mesh links are pathways
that connect pieces of a navmesh
so that navmesh agents can traverse them.
For more information on navmesh agents
see the lesson linked below.
We can create off mesh links in 2 ways.
We can either allow Unity to generate them automatically
or we can manually place them with the
off mesh link component.
Here we have a scene that has a capsule
with a navmesh agent attached.
The capsule also has a script
that will make the agent move towards
a target game object.
As you can see the target game object
is on the other side of a gap
and is thus on a different piece of navmesh.
In order to get Unity to generate off mesh links for us
we will need to select all navigationally
static object in our scene that we want links between.
In this case we will want to select the 2 storage boxes.
Once selected we will want to check the
Off Mesh Link generation checkbox.
Next we will want to go in to the
Bake tab of the navigation view.
The 2 properties that affect Off Mesh Link generation
are Drop Height and Jump Distance.
Drop Height dictates how far of a drop
is an acceptable distance to create a link.
For example it would be reasonable to be
able to drop off of a box, but not a skyscraper.
The Jump Distance determines how far of a gap
an off mesh link can span.
Once again, the bigger the number
the further an agent can jump from one navmesh to another.
By default these are set to 0
so we will want to set them to something that
makes sense for our scene.
It is worth noting that in order to have Unity
generate off mesh links you will need
to disable the Height Mesh property.
When you're done setting your properties
you will simply click the Bake button.
You will see any generated off mesh links
in the scene view.
If we run our scene we can see that the agent
is now able to traverse the gap
and reach it's destination.
The second way to create off mesh links
is manually with the Off Mesh Link Component.
Creating links this way gives us better control
over where they are placed and how we can interact with them.
Here we have the same scene as before
except we have removed the generated off mesh links
and added 2 new empty game objects
which are named LinkStart and LinkEnd.
These will be the game objects
that we create our link between.
To add an off mesh link component to an object
click the Add Component button and select
Navigation - Off Mesh Link.
The first 2 properties of the off mesh link component
Start and End require the game objects
that will represent the start and end of our link.
This means that the component doesn't have to be
on an object that is part of the link.
Though organisationally it is a good idea.
The Cost Override is used to adjust
the cost of the link for the purposes of calculating a path.
If this property is not a positive number
it will be ignored and the default
value will be used.
Bi Directional dictates whether or not
a character can traverse in both directions
across a link.
The Activated property allows you to
turn a link on and off.
Auto Update Positions determines whether or not the link
will be updated if either of the
start or end transforms are modified.
The Navigation Layer is the layer that the
off mesh link belongs to
For more information on Navigation Layers
see the lesson on NavMesh Baking linked below.
It is worth noting that once you have setup
your off mesh link component
you do not need to rebake your navmesh.
The link will automatically be visible on the navmesh
when you open the navigation view.
We can now run our scene and see
the agent move across our newly
created off mesh link.