In Unity any scene with a navmesh can easily
be navigated by a game object
with a navmesh agent component.
Here we have a scene in Unity.
The scene already has a navmesh bake.
The scene also has an empty game object
which will be the target of our navigation.
Finally there is a capsule which we will
apply our navmesh agent to.
The capsule has a SampleAgentScript attached.
This script has a public variable Target
which is already set to our empty game object
named Target.
To add a navmesh agent
click the Add Component button
in the inspector view and select
Navigation - NavMesh Agent.
The agent has several settings which
we can modify to change it's behaviour.
The Radius represents the radius of the agent.
While the Speed is the agent's max speed.
The Acceleration is how quickly
the agent will accelerate.
And the Angular Speed is how quickly
the agent can turn.
The Stopping Distance property
represents the distance from the target
that the agent will begin slowing down.
Auto Traverse Off Mesh Links
dictates whether or not the agent will
utilise off mesh links automatically.
More information on off mesh links
can be found in the lesson linked below.
Auto Braking determines if the agent
will brake when nearing it's destination.
Leaving this checked will stop the agent
from overshooting it's target.
Auto Repath will allow the agent
to rebuilt it's path if it's
current path becomes invalid.
The Height property is the height of the agent.
The Base Offset is the vertical offset
of the agent's collider.
The Obstacle Avoidance Type
has several options.
At higher qualities avoidance is more accurate.
At lower qualities avoidance is more efficient.
The avoidance priority determines which
agents have priority when navigating.
Agents of a higher priority should have a lower number.
Finally the NavMesh Walkable property
tells the agent which navigation
layers it can traverse.
For more information on navigation layers
see the lesson on navmesh making linked below.
It is worth noting that while we can
change these properties,
to achieve a large range of effects
the default properties will work for most situations.
Once the navmesh agent component
is applied and configured
we only need to tell it where to go.
In our SampleAgentScript
we can see that we first declare a variable
of type NavMeshAgent named Agent.
In the start method we get a reference to our navmesh agent
and store it in our agent variable
using the GetComponent function.
In order to tell our agent where to go
we use the Set Destination method
of the NavMeshAgent class.
This method reads in a single vector3.
In this instance we will call the SetDestination method
by typing Agent.SetDestination.
Then in the parenthesis we will type
target.position.
This tells our agent to move towards
the target game object.
Back in Unity we can run our scene.
We will notice immediately that the capsule game object
begins moving and traversing our level.
The capsule will eventually reach our target game object
and come to a stop.