The rigidbody 2D is a component that allows
a game object to be affected by 2D physics.
The game object must also have a collider 2D
component attached to interact with other game objects
using 2D physics.
A rigidbody 2D is required when working with
specialised 2D physics components
such as 2D joints.
The rigidbody 2D is also used to define important
physical properties about the game object,
such as it's mass, linear and angular drag,
gravity scale and other properties.
It is worth noting that unlike 3D physics
the rigidbody 2D has a gravity scale
which allows gravity to be set on a
per-game-object basis.
In this scene the prop_ammo_crate
is a simple game object with a sprite
renderer to hold and render the sprite.
Enter play mode, and nothing happens.
2D physics behaviour can be added to the ammo crate
by attaching a rigidbody 2D
with Add Component - Physics 2D - Rigidbody 2D.
It is worth noting that there are other ways to
attach a component to a game object.
For more information on components and
how to add them to game objects
please see the information linked below.
When in play mode, the ammo crate now falls
under the influence of gravity.
But it does not collide with the space ship.
To interact with other game objects using 2D physics
all game objects involved need collider 2d components
and at least 1 needs to have a rigidbody 2D attached.
The space ship already has a 2D collider.
A collider 2D component can be added
to the ammo crate by selecting
Add Component - Physics 2D - Box Collider.
The size of the 2D collider will automatically
match the size of the sprite.
In this case the collider needs to be adjusted
to match the image of the ammo box.
Now, when in play mode,
the ammo crate collides with, and comes to rest on
the top of the space ship.
For more information on 2D colliders
please see the information linked below.
The rigidbody 2D component not only allows a
game object to be affected by 2D physics,
it is used to define important physical
properties about that game object.
Mass is the mass of the rigidbody 2D.
2D rigidbodies with higher mass,
like those in the real world,
take more force to move and will have greater affect
when colliding with other 2D rigidbodies.
In this first case the ammo crate
and the asteroid have the same mass.
When the mass is changed on the asteroid
the interaction between the two game objects
is significantly different.
Linear and Angular drag affect
the velocity of 2D rigidbodies.
Think of this as something similar to air resistance.
Linear drag will slow the speed, or velocity
of the rigidbody 2D.
And angular drag will slow it's rotation
or angular velocity.
Gravity Scale controls how gravity affects the rigidbody 2D.
Unlike changing the global value of gravity
gravity scale allows for precise
control on a per-game-object basis.
When in play mode the ammo crate
falls under the influence of gravity.
Lower the gravity scale value
and the game object falls more slowly.
To disable gravity set this value to 0.
When Fixed Angle is selected the rigidbody
2D will respond to 2D physics forces
but it will not rotate.
Under normal conditions the asteroid will fall,
collide with the ammo box and roll away.
When Fixed Angle is selected
the asteroid will continue to react to physical forces,
such as the collision.
But it will not rotate.
When Is Kinematic is selected
the rigidbody 2D is considered to be a
kinematic rigidbody 2D
and is not affected by 2D physics forces,
including gravity and collisions.
This is typically done when moving a game object
with a 2D collider without using
physics or physics forces.
For example, when creating a moving platform.
The platform could be controlled by a
script or animation
and be moved by it's transform,
not by physics forces.
However, the platform needs to interact
with other 2D game objects.
So the platform needs a 2D collider
attached as well.
This means there is now a moving game object
with a collider 2D attached.
When moving a collider 2D while the game is playing
it is highly recommended that a rigidbody 2D
be attached as well.
Yet we don't want this platform to react
to physics forces.
In this case, the rigidbody will be set
to Is Kinematic.
This platform is moved via scripting
with a 2D collider attached.
The Interpolate settings can help smooth
movement of a game object.
If a game object appears to jitter when
being moved by it's rigidbody 2D
use the Interpolate settings to help
smooth it's transform movement.
The Interpolate setting will smooth the
movement based on the game object's
position in the previous frame.
And the Extrapolate setting will use the
predicted position in the next frame.
Sleeping Mode controls how the rigidbody
will sleep to save processing time.
Never Sleep will disable sleeping
Start Awake will make sure the rigidbody 2D
is awake when instantiated.
Start Asleep will initially set the
rigidbody 2D to sleep
but it can be woken by collisions.
For more information on sleeping
please see the information linked below.
The collision detection settings control
the type of collision detection used
when a rigidbody 2D.
The default is Discrete
and it is best to use discrete unless
there are problems.
In this case collisions are registered if
the game object's 2D collider
is in contact with another during a physics update.
Continuous is for fast moving game objects
and collisions are registered if the game object
appears to have collided with another between updates.
For more information on physics 2D and the rigidbody 2D
please see the information linked below.