The spring joint 2D component
allows you to create 2D springs
using your rigidbody 2D physics objects.
It can be added to your game object
from the physics 2D area
of the component menus.
In this example we have a plank
and a meteor, both of which are
2D physics objects,
meaning that they have rigidbody 2D
components attached.
The meteor game object has the spring joint
2D component attached
as this is the object we which to
affect with our spring.
A spring joint 2D can be attached
to your object if you wish it to be
affected by a spring.
But it also needs to be anchored to a point
in your scene.
This is defined by the connected rigidbody.
Here we have dragged our Plank game object
on to this property.
Note that this plank is a kinematic rigidbody.
This means that it won't be affected by physics.
it won't be pulled down by the meteor being attached.
This is perfect for an anchor point.
Let's look at this in action.
As we can see, the meteor is attached to the plank.
And in the scene view we can see that there are
gizmos representing the spring.
If I move the meteor
the spring reacts.
And if I move the plank
the spring continues to act
on our meteor.
If we want to offset the position of our anchor point
or where it attaches to our meteor
we can use the anchor, or connected anchor
X and Y values.
You can see this using the gizmo in the scene view.
Adjusting the anchor will adjust the
position of connection.
And adjusting the connected anchor
will adjust the position of anchoring
to the connected rigidbody.
So if your sprite has a point that makes
visual sense to attach to you can use this
offset to attach the spring here.
For example, we may want to connect
to the edge of our meteor.
The distance is how long the spring should be.
And the frequency acts as a strength value.
Having a low frequency makes for a very
slow bouncing response.
And having a high frequency makes for a very tight spring.
Damping ratio is a value from 0 to 1
which will allow you to dampen the response of the spring,
slowing it's affect on your object.
As with all of the physics 2D components
the best thing to do is to play around with these values
until you find something that feels satisfactory
for your game play and visuals.
For more information on the spring joint 2D
please see the resources linked below.