Now let's finish our level dynamics chapter
by making the lift itself, start by dragging
the model in to the scene and positioning it.
In the Models folder, locate the model
prop_lift_exit and
drag this in to the scene
Position it at (-21.85, 1.5, 48).
We will also need to rotate it by 270
degrees in the Y axis.
As always with dynamic objects in the scene
we wish to use light probes to light them.
Expand the parent object of the lift
and the inner doors and then select
door_exitInner left and right,
the carriage, the mechanism and the wires.
Then in the mesh renderer component check
the box for Use Light Probes.
The next thing to address with the lift is to
make sure that the player can collider with it
and be carried to safety.
As such it will need a collider.
However, since we are going to need a trigger
collider on the parent game object
we will need to add the physical collider
to a child game object.
To keep this collider separate from the more
complex meshes of the existing child game objects
we will make an empty game object
and add a simple convex box mesh
that we've prepared for this purpose.
Go to Game Object - Create Empty
and then drag and drop this on to the parent
object prop_lift_exit.
Now that this is a child game object it needs
to be set at the same position as the parent.
So reset it's position to (0, 0, 0) as well as it's rotation.
And finally rename it prop_lift_collider.
Now we can add a mesh collider to this game object
and use the circle select button to
search for the prop_lift_exit collision mesh.
Click Add Component - Physics
and Mesh Collider.
Then under Mesh click the selection button
search for prop_lift and choose
prop_lift_exit_collision.
Close the window and you should see that this
mesh is outlined in green
and has three walls and a floor.
This is all that we need collision-wise for the lift.
Now reselect the parent game object
prop_lift_exit. We'll add a box trigger
collider so that we know when the player has
entered the lift.
Click Add Component - Physics - Box Collider.
Finally ensure that the Is Trigger box is checked.
We want the trigger to be just over the
floor of the carriage, so set it's centre to
(0, -1.1, 0).
and the size to (3.3 0.5, 3.5)
Since the colliders will be moving we
need a rigidbody component.
And since we don't want it to react to collisions
we will make it kinematic.
Click Add Component - Physics - Rigidbody
uncheck Use Gravity and check Is Kinematic.
The lift should make a whirring noise as it
moves and as such it will require
an audio source component.
Add this now.
We don't want this to play on awake
but we do want the clip to loop.
Also, since this audio source is only going
to play one clip we can apply it
directly to the source.
In the Audio folder, the clip is called lift_raise.
Drag and drop this on to the Audio Clip property.
Next apply the lift door tracking script
that we made in the last assignment.
Remember that you can collapse your components by
clicking on their names.
We can then go in to the Scripts folder
and Level Dynamics and drag and drop
LiftDoorsTracking on to the Inspector for this object.
The last thing we need for the lift is a script
to trigger it's movement.
Choose Add Component - New Script
and we'll name our new script LiftTrigger.
Double click it's icon to launch for editing
and prepare it as usual.
For this script we are going to need a few
public variables that we can tweak.
The first one we want is a float to control
how long before the doors close
after the player enters the lift.
We don't want the lift to start the instant
doors close so we need an amount
of time before the lift starts.
Also we don't want the level to end as soon as
the lift starts moving so we need a variable for that too.
It would also be nice to be able to tweak the
speed that the lift moves at
so we will have that as a public float as well.
Next we need some private variables
including some references.
First we need a reference to the player.
And also a reference to the player's animator
component so that we can stop the player from
moving when the lift starts to move.
Since we will be referencing an animator
we want to use our HashIDs script.
When the lift moves we would like it to disappear
at the top of the screen, instead of being
tracked by the camera all the way up.
So we will need a reference to the CameraMovement script
so that we can disable it when the lift moves.
To end the level with our fade to black
we need a reference to our SceneFadeInOut script.
So that we can control when the lift doors
are opening and closing we need a reference
to the LiftDoorsTracking script.
We don't need any more references but we do
need a Boolean variable to store
whether the player is in the lift or not.
And finally a timer that will set
the doors closing, when the lift can start moving
and when the level should end.
Now we can setup our references in the Awake function.
The next two functions we will use in this script
are OnTriggerEnter and OnTriggerExit.
to handle detection of the player entering and
exiting the lift's internal trigger zone.
Firstly we will use OnTriggerEnter.
If it is the player that is the triggering
game object then we can set the
playerInLift variable to true.
Next we set this variable back to false
when the player leaves the trigger zone
by using OnTriggerExit.
If the player leaves the lift we will
need to reset the timer that controls it's actions.
So that when the player returns to the lift
the process can start over again.
Next we're going to add an Update function.
We're going to use Update for a couple of things.
Primarily we will use it to check whether the
player is in the left and if they are
we will call a function to activate the lift.
We will create this function first and
then come back and add the call to it later.
We will call the function liftActivation.
The first thing we need to do when the function is called
is to start the timer counting upward.
Then we only need to worry about doing anything
if the timer exceeds the
timeToLiftStart variable.
If the lift has started then we want
to stop the player from moving and we can do this
by setting the Speed parameter of
their animator to 0.
We also want the camera to stop tracking the player
so we will disable the CameraMovement script.
In order that the player moves upward with the lift
we're going to parent the player to the lift.
This means that his position will be local
to that of the lift.
To move the lift we are simply going to use
the Translate function. We are moving the lift
in an upwards direction multiplied by an amount
of lift speed per second.
This function is going to be called every
frame once the player is in the lift.
And this part of the function will be called
every frame once the lift starts moving.
To play the audio of the lift we only
need to start the audio source playing
so we will add a call to the Play function
but only call this if it is not already playing.
So that each frame after this we are
not trying to play it unnessisarily.
The last part of this function will end
the level when an appropriate amount
of time has elapsed.
To actually end the level we will call
the EndScene function from the
SceneFadeInOut script, which fades to black
and reloads the scene.
Now that the LiftActivation function is finished
we can put a call to it in the Update function.
We only want to do so however
when the player is in the lift.
The last thing to do in this script is
control when the inner lift doors open and close.
We will do this in the Update function as well.
If the timer is less than the time before
the doors should close then the
inner doors should be tracking the outer doors.
We can make this happen by calling the
Door Following function from the
LiftDoorsTracking Script that we wrote previously.
However if the timer has exceed the
TimeToClose variable then we want the doors to close.
That completes the lift. Save your script now
and return to the Editor.
We will also store the lift as a prefab
Drag and drop it in to the Prefabs folder
in the Project panel to do this.
Now we want to save the scene and the project.
Now we have a scene with working level dynamics.
We can explore the level with the doors
opening and closing and pick up the key
so that we can escape in the lift.
One final thing to do is to tidy up our script.
Select the Assets folder in the Project panel
and then drag the LiftTrigger script
in to the Scripts - Level Dynamics folder.
In the next and final chapter we will
create the robot guards that patrol the level.