The next phase we're going to go in to
is to create our first enemy.
We need our enemies in the game to
damage the player, we need them to follow the player,
but in this particular one we're just going to create
the first enemy and make him follow you around.
So let's get on with that.
As before with the player
in the Models folder in Characters you will
find there are some models.
One of those models
is this lovingly created zombunny,
which looks something like this.
And what we're going to do with that is to
place him directly in to the scene and then
start working with him in a similar way
that we did with the player.
As usual I'm just going to quickly hit Save
just so I don't loose any work if we get a crash
and then I'm going to
drag my scene view around
and this bit really doesn't matter where we place
him because we're going to spawn him later on
I'm going to use dragging
from the project window and you can see that it
snaps to the environment or whatever I happened
to place him on to.
I'm just going to drop him near the player
somewhere like that.
Then when we shoot this
bunny we're going to have
stuff kind of fly out of him.
We've created for you a particle system to do just that.
In the Prefabs folder you will find
a HitParticles prefab.
So like we said before prefabs are a way of storing
something that you've already setup and we did
exactly the same thing, we've created this
HitParticles, and what we need to do
is apply this to the Zombunny.
In Unity all game objects that you put in
can have a hierarchy.
The Zombunny has a child object which is it's
mesh, it's kind of outline
but it also has a parent and we want to
drag drop this particle system
on so that it's attached to the parent.
So what I'm going to do is select my Zombunny
and I'm going to drag and drop HitParticles
on to the parent Zombunny
so that when we expand it we've got
Zombunny, the actual object itself and we've got HitParticles.
And basically all this is doing, if I select
my HitParticles now,
is creating this little puff of stuffing.
I can see that because I've got
that game object selected the scene view shows
me the particle effect overlay
and you can see it's creating a puff of
fluff that's coming out of him.
This particle system, we didn't want to get bogged
down too much with these various
settings but we're basically using
a texture which is applied to
this to just fire out a little emission of those.
Again we want to
detect whether this is something that we
can shoot at, so similar to how
we detected whether we can turn to face
a particular way by isolating
the floor on to a floor layer
this Zombunny is going to be on a shootable layer.
So with the Zombunny parent selected
make sure you reselect the parent,
go to Layer at the top of the inspector
and choose Shootable.
Set that to shootable and then
it's going to ask you if you would like
to changing the children.
Basically all this is saying is do you want them all to be on
the same layer, this child objects, say yes, change the children.
A quick note, the environment
that you all dragged in to the scene at the start
is also on the shootable layer, so that
means that when we later give the
layer a working gun you can hit the environment as well.
We've done that, and then we basically
want to setup the Zombunny in a similar way
to the player, so we want him to have physics,
we want him to have a physical presence in the world
so we're going to do some similar
things that we did before.
The first one of those we're going to do is to
add a rigidbody component.
Just to give you a different way of doing things
we've previously used the menu but
you'll notice that this is actually a search field.
So I'm just going to type in Rig and I go
straight to rigidbody, I can hit
return to add that.
I'm just going to make that expanded
so that I can apply some settings.
Again, drag an angular drag
should be set to infinity, so I'm going to
type in INF, hit return,
and it should change to capitalised Infinity.
And the constraints are exactly the same.
We want them to be able to rotate
only in the Y axis, we want them to only
be moving in X and Z
and frozen position Y.
Your constraints should look like this.
Freeze position Y, freeze rotation X and Zee.
In order to actually give this physics
object a boundary we're going to put in
a capsule collider,
the outline of it's physical shape.
I'm hitting Add Component one more time
and then I'm going to type in Cap for capsule collider
and the settings for it are
Centre value of Y 0.8,
and a height of 1.5.
So it should look like this.
We need this character to attack the player
so this bit's going to be slightly different
to how the player was setup.
The capsule collider is there to give
the character a physical presence but what
we want to do is to give him the
ability to detect the player
We're going to use one more collider to do that
and we're going to use a trigger collider for this purpose.
So we're going to Add Component one more time
and we're going to say SPH, sphere collider.
Hit return.
You can also go to Add Component - Physics
Sphere Collider, but that's just a short way of doing that.
A trigger is something that doesn't have a physical presence,
it's a collider, which means you can check
when something's intersecting it, but it doesn't have
a physical presence so we can just walk straight through it.
So we check the Is Trigger box
and then if we just have a look
back at our bunny very briefly at the same window
you can see that by default it's set at the
origin of this, which is at it's feet.
So we're going to set the centre Y to 0.8
and the radius also to 0.8.
What you'll see is that if I just expand my
capsule collider again
it's slightly further out than the
capsule collier is, the reason being that
we want to detect the player within
the bunnies reach.
So we want it to bump in to stuff but we want
it's reach to be able to harm the player
so we make that sphere collider slightly bigger,
we make it a trigger so that it's not actually
going to bump in to anything,
that's how we're going to detect the player.
Again with triggers
the actual interactions within a
scene is not what we use a trigger for.
More importantly a trigger, when anything collides
with a trigger or goes in to a trigger
a function is called when you have a script attached
that says 'hey, something touched that trigger'.
And that's when we write our
individualised code that'll be like
'okay, something touched that trigger'.
It's interactions in the scene view are not what
we're interested in, we're actually interested in the
behind the scenes interaction we get to write
with our own code.
Finally the last thing we're going to do
to complete the Zombunny is just add an audio
source so I'm going to type in
Audio, I'm going to scroll down,
I can use my arrow keys in this Add Component menu
and I'm going to use return to choose Audio Source.
This thing is just to allow him
to make a sound when he gets hurt
and then we're going to make that the default sound clip as well.
As before, using circle select I can
just click and choose Zombunny Hurt,
it's the very bottom one from the list.
I can double click it
to assign and close the window.
As before we don't want it to make
the sound so we're going to uncheck play on awake.
We obviously don't want that to loop or anything
so we're going to leave that there.
Next we need to make the guy actually follow
the player so in Unity there's a
system called Nav Mesh.
In Unity Window - Navigation is what you need.
Window - Navigation.
That should automatically dock itself
next to the inspector. If it doesn't that's a great place
to put it, so drag and drop that tab
next to the inspector on the right of your interface.
We're going to reselect the Zombunny and go
back to the inspector.
The navigation panel is
there for us to setup our level.
We're going to setup our Zombunny first and then
go back and setup the level.
With our Zombunny selected
I'm just going to close
some of these by collapsing them up to give us
more space to look at.
I'm going to add something called a Nav Mesh Agent.
Like I said there's a system called Nav Mesh
which is used for a simple AI in Unity
and what it means is you can
do a process called baking, which is to
specify which parts of the level are navigable.
And then you have something called an Agent
which is something that's going to traverse that, or move
over that environment.
The Zombunny is something that's going to do that.
We are going to give it a
Nav Mesh Agent Component.
You can see that it has an outline here
similar to a collider
and we're going to set a more appropriate default of 0.3.
0.3 in radius.
We're going to set the speed to 3 by default
and stopping distance to 1.3.
We're going to set the heigh, which is slightly
lower down to 1.1.
Because it's easier to see these settings
on the powerpoint I'm just going to switch over to that.
So we've added a nav mesh component.
The radius is 0.3, the speed is 3,
stopping distance is 1.3
and height, a few properties down is 1.1.
It should look like what we have in Unity.
If you recall for the player we're moving
the player using physics,
but we're not doing that with the bunnies themselves.
The nav mesh agent is actually
what is moving.
Just keep that in mind.
We're not actually going to be using forces with the bunnies,
instead the nav mesh agent is going to
pick and follow the targets
automatically while also
avoiding obstacles and things like that,
and that's what Will meant when he was talking about AI
it's AI pathfinding.
What I wanted to point out as well
and you guys don't need to do this so just watch,
the environment is already prefabbed.
We put colliders on to everything so you can see
that the player could bump in to all of these objects.
We used primitive colliders for performance reasons
to make it all work nice and neatly.
What you should also note about that is there's a
checkbox up at the top here called Static.
That's checked and that means that
Navigation Static is also checked.
So what that means is that all of the
things we've specified in here
as being a navigable space
are going to be included
when we bake the nav mesh, when we create
this navigable area.
What I want you to do now is to go to that
navigation window again and we're going to
switch over to the Bake tab,
the middle one of the three, and there we have
some settings that we're going to put in there.
The radius of the nav mesh is
approximately how near to a wall an agent can move
so we're going to have multiple types of enemy
in this so we've got some Zombunnys,
Zombears and some Helephants.
Now Helephants are a lot bigger
so we need to compromise with the
radius of the nav mesh.
Normally you'd want to have nav mesh agents
and nav meshes with the same radius
but since we've got different size agents we're going to
compromise and make the radius for it 0.75.
Likewise this height
is a compromise, we have Zombunnys
which we made 1.1 in height.
The Helephants are going to be a lot bigger
but we're going to make our height
a compromise between the two,
we're going to give it 1.2.
But normally if you've got one type of agent
and they're all the same give the radius
the same as the nav mesh agent and the height
the same as the nav mesh agent.
The next thing we're going to
change is the Step Height.
Your nav mesh agent can go up steps and
because our floor is uneven,
it's made up of floorboards that are
sticking up a bit like that, we need the nav mesh
agents to not go like 'oh I can't get over that
floorboard, I'd better got around it' so we need a
small step height to make sure that it can get up
over those bumps.
Then we're expanding the Advanced area
and we're setting the Width Inaccuracy
to just 1%, so drag that Width Inaccuracy down to 1.
The Width Inaccuracy affects how
carefully the nav mesh is baked.
A nav mesh can be baked very quickly
if you give it high inaccuracies
and it'll look quite angular and
it'll be quite approximate to your
environment but we want
it to be a very accurate nav mesh.
This is going to take a little while to bake but
we'll end up with a very nice nav mesh afterwards.
Once that's done you are hitting Bake
at the bottom of the window.
What you'll see in the scene view
once it's completed that process
is that you will see a blue overlay
on the entire level.
You will get a progress bar at the bottom,
it says 'exporting tiles' like this.
Once it's done that process you will
see an overlay in the scene view
as long as you are on the navigation window.
And it should look something like this.
So what's happening here is
nav agents and pathfinding and all that
will work with complex meshes,
however it is incredibly inefficient
and you're going to have all sorts of issues
if there's bumps and cracks and things like that
basically saying that while you can
traverse these unusually sized
and shaped meshes it's really not
worth it, right?
Generally you want your movement to be smooth
and you don't want it to be that inefficient.
When we bake a nav mesh what it's doing is
it's finding all of the static meshes
in our scene, things that are marked as
navigationally static and saying
'these aren't going to move, these are going to be
things that we can walk on'
and it's going to calculate a very simple
flat mesh and say 'it's not exact but it's
close enough and no one will ever know'
so it's much more efficient and it actually makes it
much more accurate as far as actually moving
around how you would expect things to move around.
That's what we're doing, we're on the fly
Unity is generating a new mesh
which is just a flat plane,
possibly with a slow to it,
but it's very simplified and it makes
the actual AI process of navigating very simple.
Just to make this very clear,
these things in our scene are marked as static
so if we wanted to move our blocks,
at some point we changed the design of the game
we would move them and we would rebake the nav mesh
to recalcuate that traversable area.
Okay, so we need this character to
run around and chase the player
so we're going to apply animation to this.
What we want to do is select the Animation
folder in the project panel.
I'm going to click the Create button and I'm going to choose
Animator Controller.
So select the Animation folder and choose
Create  - Animator Controller.
This one is going to be EnemyAC.
AC is short for Animator Controller and
then we're going to assign this to our Zombunny.
The Zombunny, if we drag and drop that asset
on to it it will assign it for us,
but just to be clear what we're actually doing
is assigning this to the controller
property of the animator.
Either drag and drop to
that component or simply drag and drop
straight on to that object to
automatically assign it for you.
So when you select the Zombunny you should have
Animator - EnemyAC as the asset.
So that is a animator controller, a state machine,
so I'm going to double click EnemyAC
to open it in the animator window.
We should have an empty new state machine
to add animations to
just like we did with the player.
As before with the player the
animation for the Zombunny is
stored within it's model so I'm going to
expand the model and go to the Characters
folder in the project.
In the project panel open up Models
and select Character and then
expand the Zombunny and you will see
that and it's animations.
The Zombunny has Move, Idle and Death
and they are clips that are on a
particular point on the timeline.
You can see as I go between these clips
they are all in a different part of the timeline
as you can see from here.
The way that you can do that when you bring in an FPX
model that you've animated is you can just
create new clips and tell it what
frame range you animated them on
and Unity will import those for you
as different clips.
Just like the player they appear
underneath that in the hierarchy
so you have Death, Idle and Move.
Just as before I'm going to drag them in.
I want the default state to be Moving
so I'm going to drag that one in first because
that gets made default,
default signified by orange.
Then I'm going to drag in the other two,
Idle and Death even.
I'm going to put Death next to the Any state,
and I'm going to put Idle and Move together.
Again the position of these is kind of irrelevant but
I like to have things nice and neat.
Once those are in there we've positioned
them nicely we're going to
create parameters for them.
So making sure that Move is the default,
so Set As Default with right click
if you haven't already, we're going to create parameters.
We have just two parameters for this one
and as before we're going to click the + icon
and we're going to select the type
of parameter that we want.
We want
a trigger parameter called PlayerDead.
These enemy characters are going to walk,
they're going to have their moving animation
until the player dies and they are going to go
in to their Idle animation.
Then we're going to create another trigger
which says that they themselves are dead,
which is just called Dead.
So two trigger parameters, PlayerDead
so that they can go to Idle when you get killed
and Dead themselves so that they can animate
in to their Death animation.
Then of course we need to actually control the
logic of the state machine.
We want our move to transition to Idle
so I'm going to right click Make Transition
and again I get the transition handle.
I'm going to click on Idle to assign it.
I will select
the transition by clicking on it.
Once that transition is highlighted in blue
I should have my list of transitions.
So in order to go from Move to Idle
the condition is that
the player is dead.
Then very simply in order to go from
the Any state I will make a transition,
click on Death,
select that transition.
The condition for that is that the
Dead trigger has occurred.
So if I just scrub through you see we go from
Moving in to Death.
Also notice that you can't go from Idle back to Move.
Because at that point the player is dead.
So we have no need to create a transition back.
These state machines don't work by themselves
The connection between the state machine and
animator and the actual functionality
is that the scripting needs to tell those
parameters what their value is.
We need a script to say that the
animator SetTrigger Player Dead will actually
happen otherwise the animator does nothing by itself.
In the Scripts folder in your project
you will see a folder called Enemy.
Go to Scripts folder and open the folder Enemy.
In that you will see a folder called
EnemyMovement.
We are going to drag and drop that on to
Zombunny in the hierarchy.
And then once you've assigned it either
double click EnemyMovement's icon
or go to the cog icon
and go to Edit Script, but basically we're opening
that for editing.
and when you open that for editing it should look like this.
What you'll notice here is we have a script that's
been ready written for you.
Some of the functionality has been disabled,
you'll notice the double forward slash
symbols at the start of some of these lines.
That's commenting, so you can write
comments in a script, I.E. just notes
to yourself or to coworkers, whatever,
but you can also use that to turn
functional lines of code in to deactivated
lines of code, so that's what we've done here
and we're going to come back to this script at some point
and enable some of that functionality.
But for now we're just going to explain how this script functions.
This is our EnemyMovement script and at the very
beginning we have this Transform player,
and the Transform player is going to be
what the enemy is going to move towards.
You will notice the Transform player is not public.
With the camera we had that public transform
target so we could click and drag
in the editor and the camera knows what it's following.
However our enemies are
not going to be in the game when the game starts.
Our enemies are actually going to be what's called
instantiated or spawned
later so whole hordes of them can appear.
As such we can't just click and drag
the player on to them.
So what's going to happen is they're going to have to find
the player on their own, so for now
that's just Transform player, not public.
We also have a reference to a nav mesh agent,
which is the component we put
on the Zombunny previously, this is just our
reference to it which we've called Nav.
Now down in the Awake method here
we are finding the player.
So we have Player, which is that Transform before,
player = GameObject.FindGameObjectWithTag.
So if you remember previously when we were
setting up the player we
gave the player the tag Player.
So now that we've set the player with the tag
Player, we can find
that player using this function.
So basically what it's going to do is go through all of the game
objects in our scene, it's going to say 'hey do you have that tag?'
until it finds the one and it gives it back.
And then what we're going to do is say
.Transform, which is going to give us
a reference to the transform,
basically where the player is.
So we're storing that in our variable named player.
Next we have a variable named nav
and we're just setting that equal to GetComponent
which is basically going to
pull a reference to the component we have in the editor.
At this point we're just setting up.
Then down in our update function
you'll notice we're using update, not fixed update.
As this is a nav mesh agent it's not
keeping in time with physics
so we're just going to use the regular update
and inside there we are going to say
nav.SetDestination (player.position); and that's it.
So nav being the nav mesh agent we're saying
'hey, that's where I want to go'.
'I want to go towards the player'
and that's it, the nav mesh agent goes
'cool, I'm going to head towards the player'.
And the nice thing about doing it this way is that
the enemies aren't going to bump in to each other,
they're not going to crop in and out of each other,
they're going to move around all the creepy
baby arms and Legos and
weirdness that we have in the scene there and
they're going to viciously and unerringly
attack you with extreme prejudice and violence.
The nav mesh agent makes it very easy to do these things.
And that's the whole script.
We'll revisit this script later when we want to
do uncomment it, re-add in that
functionality that you see is currently greyed out.
We could switch back to the Unity editor
right now, we don't need to save anything because
we haven't actually edited it,
but I do want to make sure you have applied it to Player.
So the Zombunny in the hierarchy should
have the enemy movement script attached to it.
I'm going to save my scene
and I'm going to press Play to test
my game, when you press Play it now
follows the player.
We don't have any coding for attacking
yes or anything like that
so it's not doing to do any harm to you,
you can walk around and push him around.
That is the end of phase 4.