Okay, so as we said before, some of the
scripts in this project are pre-written.
So the main camera
is the camera that we're viewing our
game at, if I zoom our right now you can see
that the main camera is sitting behind the character.
And what we want to do is to set that up slightly
differently, currently by default when you
make a new camera in Unity you're making
a perspective 3D camera.
We want to make an isometric view
and because of that we're going to use
orthographic cameras.
So the first thing we're going to do is setup
where the camera is positioned.
We're going to select our main camera in the hierarchy
and in the transform
component we're going to set
the position to (1, 15, -22).
We're going to set the rotation to
(30,0,0)
Then in the camera component we're going to set the
projection mode from perspective
using the drop down to orthographic.
And finally the size value that then appears to 4.5.
And when you look at your scene view, your game view
you should see that you have
an orthographic view.
Then a couple more camera settings.
We're going to set our background
to black, so when you move over
to the front of the level you will see
the background colour of the camera.
We don't want it to be blue so in our
camera component we're going to click on the colour
block next to the world Background.
That's going to open up a colour picker, which looks like this.
We're going to set this to black, so drag it all the way down
to the bottom of the colours.
Close that panel.
Then we're going to save our scene
just to make sure it's up to date.
And in the Scripts folder
we're going to select Camera.
So this time we are going to
create one more script.
This script is a lot shorter than our player
movement and is quite simple.
So whenever you select a folder in your assets,
so for example we are selecting,
Camera in the Scripts folder right now,
we can go to the Create button and choose
C# Script.
And it's going to create something called 'New Behaviour.
When you create a script, especially in C#
it's very important that you name it in accurately.
We're going to call this CameraFollow so don't
have any spaces
on your file names for scripts and
try to name them in this
capitalised style. Capitalised  style, capital F for Camera Follow.
Quick note on creating
scripts like this if you
created it and then accidentally clicked off so it would
briefly new behaviour.
Then the script, the class
that it makes will be called
new behaviour, so you'll need to
rename that when you open it.
So if I look at this one that I've correctly
named now, CameraFollow you can see it's
written the script for me, public class
CameraFollow, and what you'll see is
when you open it up in Unity and switch back
Unity will say 'class name does not match file name'.
So you need to make sure that everything in that class
is named the same as the actual file,
your CameraFollow script.
So once you've named that click
Open to open it up in Mono Develop.
And you should see something like this.
What we're going to do is
you get Start and Update
in your script, whenever you make a new script.
But we don't want those there
so we're going to select over that code,
making sure not to select
the final curly brackets.
We're going to hit backspace just to remove it
So we've got public class CameraFollow
and the open and closed curly braces.
Okay so as usual we're going to start
with the public variables at the top,
so those are the ones that can be accessed through the inspector,
or through other scripts.
To start off, we need to have
a target for this camera to follow
so we're going to make a public transform
called target.
Next we're going to make a public float
called smoothing.
and we're gong to give that a default value of 5.
So basically our camera's going to follow
the player around, but we don't want
it to be super sharp.
We're going to give it a little bit of lag, a little bit
just to make it smoother for the player to see.
So that value there is going to be
how smooth it is.
Lastly we're going to make a private variable
called offset.
We're going to store the offset of
the camera from the player, the distance between
them at the start of the script
and what we need to do is store that so
in each update we can make sure that we can
have the same offset.
So let's store that offset now in star.
Offset is the vector from
the camera to the player,
so that's transform.position - target.position.
We're going to apply the script once
we finish writing it to the camera
so we need to make sure that the
transform position, the position of the camera
is subtracted from the target position,
the position of the player.
So we're going to drag and drop.
Because target's a public variable we're going to
drag and drop the player game object on to
this transform target and you'll see that in a minute.
That's the end of our start function.
We just needed to create that offset
Now in fixed update,
so remember this is following
every physics step, and we're going to use fixed update
to move the camera because we're following
a physics object.
If we used update then it would
be moving in different time to the player
because the player is moving in fixed update.
So we're going to use fixed update to move the camera
and we need a target position
for this camera to try and reach.
TargetPosition is going to be the
position of the target + this offset.
So we're trying to find a place for this camera
to be up above the level
and that's the position of the player plus
this offset that we've stored.
And now we need to actually move the camera
and we're going to do that using a lerp.
A lerp just smoothly moves
between two positions,
so you get that through vector3.lerp.
The position that we want to move it to
is between it's current position
so transform.position,
and this target position that we've just made.
So what that's going is it's saying
I've got my current position and the position
I want to be, I'm going to try and move
a little bit towards that.
That's what this function is doing.
We've got the two vectors that we need to
move between, now we need to tell it
how fast we're going to do that,
and we're doing that using our smoothing variable
that we stored earlier.
And naturally since we don't want it to
do it 50 times a second
we're going to times by Time.DeltaTime.
And that's the end of the script.
Very simple.
So for those of you who are ready
what I want you to do is in the Unity editor
select CameraFollow and drag and drop
this on to Main Camera.
So from the project panel,
drop it on to Main Camera.
When you've done that and selected Main Camera
in the hierarchy, so you should see
this CameraFollow script that I have in the lower right.
You'll see that the public variables target
and smoothing appear
as things that we can assign to in the interface.
So target is looking for something called a transform
and smoothing is a number that we can
change to whatever we want.
Then what we're going to do is to assign the target,
the target is of course the player,
so we just drag and drop
player on to the target variable.
Grab the player from the hierarchy and not the scene view.
Clicking and dragging the player in the scene view is
just going to move the player.
One thing you'll notice as well is if you go
to click then drag
you lose the context of the main camera, so
select the main camera then
drag and drop player on there.
So basically all that's doing is it's finding
the game object reference and then it's finding the
exact thing that it wants, it wants to find the transform.
Then we're going to save
and then finally we're going to save our
player as a prefab.
So like I said before when we introduced the
environment the environment
was saved as a prefab because we've already assigned
a bunch of components to it so if you've got
something setup the way you want it and you want to
save it in to the project, so we might want to use
the player in other levels of the game
so we save it as a prefab and the way that you can
do that is just to drag it anywhere in to the project.
We happened to have a prefabs folder but you don't need to
drag it in to there but we'd like you to.
Player, drag and drop from the hierarchy
and drop it in to the Prefabs folder in the project.
If you turn it in to a prefab it's an asset,
a hard dry file you can save it, export it, reuse it
all over the place and then
yeah, so there's more benefits to turn things in to prefabs.
So I want you to save your scene right now and
press play and you should have
a little character that runs around
and you can move the camera, it should be tracking him.
And we'll show you what that looks like right now.
You should be seeing this.
Camera's now tracking around,
and we can rotate
like this.