So what we're going to do is setup our player now
which is going to get him moving and jazzing and
beboping and doing all that stuff.
What we're going to do is we're going to go ahead and locate
the player model, which is going to be located
in Models folder, and we're going to
expand that and we're going to look in the Characters folder
and we should see a player,
there we go, Player, it should be right there.
So what we're going to do is we're going to go ahead and
drag that either in to the scene or in to
the hierarchy view.
So we'll just click and drag and drop and there he is.
There he is, looking pretty swag.
And so obviously if we just click and drag him to the scene he might
go where ever, you know, so we need to
place him at a specific spot so we're going to be sure that
the position is at (0, 0, 0).
If it is then you're golden, if it's not then
go ahead and set it to (0, 0, 0)
by typing (0, 0, 0) or again we
have this cog or gear icon
and you can just click reset or reset position,
which will put it where ever we want it to be on the origin.
Now we need specific things to
interact with the player in a very special way.
And so we want to ensure that we have properly
tagged our player so certain things will know
when they've come in contact with the player.
To do that we have this Tag drop down
here in the inspector and it currently says Untagged.
And what we're going to do is we're going to click that drop down
and we are going to select Player.
Thus tagging our player
as the player so that the player will
behave appropriately when they are playing.
Alright, fantastic.
Now what we need to do is
we're going to go ahead and create
an animation controller for our player,
which is going to allow us to
have all the neat little
animation effects of moving and turning and
doing all that stuff,
and I'm still zoomed in here.
So what we want to do is we want to go ahead and
locate the Animation folder
which we'll just click on right here.
Currently it is in fact empty and we are going to make
an animator controller.
Shall we just talk a little bit about the
animations that we've setup first?
Great idea!
Cool. So the model that we've just dragged in
is the player model and what you can do is drag up
the preview window in the lower right of the editor.
So this model has been animated
for you, so when you bring in an FPX
in to Unity, or a Maya file
or a 3DS Max, whatever package you use,
When you bring that in you can
store animations within it or if you have
a humanoid, a biped-type model
you can retarget those animations on to
similar type of models.
This particular thing is rigged
in what we call a generic manner.
So if I look at my rig you can see generic up at the top.
And what that means is that it's a very specific
bone structure because our character is going to move like this.
It's going to be kind of hopping around.
So he's not got two arms, two legs as a biped would.
So the animations that are stored in this
particular model that we've given you
are a move, an idle and a death.
So what we're going to do now is to create
a state machine called the Animator Controller
to control when these three different
animations are going to be played back.
If you're looking in the inspector here
I highly encourage you not to
touch anything.
Because these changes change how Unity
imports the stuff and if you just start clicking
and a little box comes up and says 'would you like to apply?'
and you're like 'yeah, apply for what?'
and then all of a sudden your stuff is not going to
work later, so just look but don't touch.
So we're doing this just to
show your where the animation's going to be
coming from and we're going to go ahead and
actually implement it now.
We're going to go back to this animation folder
and again it's still empty so
no magic there yet.
And we're going to go ahead and add what's called
an animator controller.
Animator controllers are part of the mecan animation
system, they're basically a finite state machine that just
blends animations and does all this neat stuff,
it's actually magic, we hired wizards.
And what we're going to do is we're going to go ahead and
create this asset that's going to allow us to do that.
So I'm going to right click here inside
this animation folder in the project view here
and I am going to select
Create and then Animator Controller.
Not Animation, not Animator Override Controller
but Animator Controller.
And I'm going to get this name here and I'm going to name it
Player AC for Animator Controller.
There we go.
And so once we have that what we're
going to do is we are going to
actually just click and drag that on
to the player, which is going to apply this animator
controller to the player,
I'm not going to put it under the player
I'm going to put it on the player and you'll know the difference
because Player itself will become highlighted.
And I'll let go.
I can confirm I did this correctly be clicking on the player
and I see here Player AC
is now listed in the animator
component, Player AC, right there.
That's how I know I've done it correctly.
Now let's go ahead and look at this animator controller,
now that we have it created,
and to do that I can go to Window
and then select Animator
but easier is to
see my Player AC and just double click on it,
which is automatically going to open up the animator window.
If it's not docked here
you can just dock it by clicking the
tab, dragging it and docking it in to the window.
So as we were looking at earlier
when Will clicked on the player
FPX model and we looked in the inspector and we saw
those animations that were baked in to those settings.
Those actually create assets that we're able to use.
So if I go back to the Model's
character's folder right here.
and again look at my player.fpx.
If I were to expand that I would
see the assets that make up
this imported model
and so I'm going to go ahead and click this model here
and what I see is I see these three animations
death,  idle and move.
So not only were the animations imported
as part of the model but we actually have them assets
that we can utilise.
And so what I'm going to do now is I'm actually
going to just take each of these in turn
and move them in to my
animator window, I'm just going to click and drag them,
and drop them
I'm just going in order here so I'm going to do death,
idle and move, the order's not going to matter because
we're going to reorder them in just a moment.
So when you have this done right
you'll see that you have this Any state
and a Death state and an Idle state and a Move state.
And so we'll notice that the death state is
orange, or which ever state you drag in first
is orange, right?
Orange means that it's the default state.
Obviously I do not want death as the default state
It's a sad game but it's not that sad.
And so what I want to do is
I am going to set a different state
as our default state, so I am going to right click
on Idle and I'm going to click
Set As Default.
So that will then turn orange.
And I can reorder by clicking and dragging and moving
things around, if you just happened to be very particular
about how things look you can start
building yourself some geometric structures if you really
feel like it, whatever.
Anyway, now we have idle as the
default state and so what we need to do
is we need to
tell the animator
when we want to transition from one
state to another state.
So we've got these three states, idle, move and death.
And they're self-contained animations, they can play and all that stuff but
the logic of when we go from one
to the next isn't currently in here.
So what we need to do is we need to create something
called a parameter which is basically going to control
when something happens,
when something changes state.
And we access those parameters right here
with this little Parameters button
it's very cleverly named,
and we have this little + icon right there.
What we want to do is we want to create a parameter
so the first parameter we're going to create,
when we click this we're going to see some options
we can create a float, as in a floating point number,
int is an integer, bool is a boolean
or trigger, we want to create a boolean
and we're going to call this IsWalking.
It's very important that you spell it right
like I just did not.
There we go, IsWalking,
and then enter.
It has to be capital I
lowercase s, capital W alking.
alright, it's important that it's spelt
right because we have scripts that you're going to use
that reference it by name
so if you named it something else, like Skeletor,
when the time comes it's not going to work
you'll just have to open up your code and change it
which you really don't want to do.
So we have this IsWalking which is a boolean which
means it can be either true or false
and that true or false will dictate whether
he is walking.
I'm going to create another one now so again I'm going to click
this little + icon and I'm going to select
Trigger, and a trigger is like a boolean.
It can have a state True or False
but unlike a boolean the moment we set it to true
it sets it back to false.
Which is useful when I just want to
trigger something to happen one time and then it resets itself.
So we're going to select a trigger here
and this trigger is going to be
called Die.
We listened to a lot of heavy metal while making this.
So die is a trigger that's going to
be triggered when the player
actually dies.
Now what we want to do is
we have these parameters which is
great but now we need to tell
mechanim and the animator specifically how to use
those parameters, we need to set up some logic
to move us from one to the next.
So what we want to do is we want to setup
transitions that basically says
'this state is capable of going to that state'
and 'this state is capable of going to that state'.
We set up these transitions explicitly
so that we can't accidentally transition from
say Dead to Jump,
because that doesn't make a whole lot of sense.
So what we want to do is create these
transitions which basically are one-way bridges
that define logically how
we go from one state to another.
So what I'm going to do is I'm going to right click on Idle
and I'm going to select Make Transition.
And when I click Make Transition I get this
rodeo lasso thingy
which is fun to play with by itself,
but we're here for business,
so what I'm going to do is once I've confirmed that
there's this white line attached to my mouse
I'm going to move my mouse over the Move
animator state and I'm just going to click
and it's going to connect the two.
So now what we have is a transition from idle to move.
See, there you go in case you didn't believe me.
And so this is basically saying that we
can go from idle to move.
So what I'm going to do now is in order to
actually dictate when that happens
I have to click on the transition.
Too close.
There we go.
I'm going to click and you'll see it turn blue
and so now I have selected
the transition between the two.
And once I've done that over in the inspector view we get
the properties of this transition
and what I'm interested in is
is down on the bottom we have these conditions.
What is the condition of this transition?
And so what I'm going to do is
click this drop down that says Exit Time
and I'm going to select IsWalking
and I'm going to leave that as true.
So the way you read this is you are transitioning
from idle to move when IsWalking
equals true.
So now what I'm going to do
is I'm just going to do the exact opposite,
so I'm going to right click on move
make transition, get my fun rodeo arrow,
now I'm going to click on idle,
so this is stating that I am able to move
from the move state back to the idle state.
and I'm sure that you can all guess what
the condition for that is going to be but we'll
go through it anyway, I'm going to select Conditions
IsWalking equals false.
So if the player is walking we play the walking animation.
If the player is not walking we don't,
we play the idle animation.
Finally what I want to do is
I am going to create one more transition,
this time we want the player to be able to die.
So to do that  we're not going
to transition from idle or move or death
because we can theoretically die
in any state depending on whichever animation is
currently going on.
So we are going to use the Any state.
And by that I mean the actually green any state,
I don't mean you're going to transition from any state you want.
So the one that says Any state.
So I'm going to right click on that and
I only have one option and that's Make Transition
and I am going to transition from
Any state to Death, so no matter what state
you're currently in if you die, you die.
I'm going to select that transition,
you'll see it turn blue
and I'm going to set my condition to be
Die.
Now since it's a trigger I don't need to
specify true, false or a value like that,
it's just if Die get's triggered
we immediately switch in to the death animation.
The next thing we need to do with this player character
is to give him a physical presence in the scene.
So if you change from your animator window
back to the scene view using the tab at the top
then you can select the player.
We're going to add a rigidbody.
A rigidbody component is something that allows
the physics engine of Unity to be applied to the object.
We are going to click Add Component
and choose Physics
and Rigidbody.
It's important that you don't select Physics 2D
Rigidbody 2D, we're doing 3D physics
so just physics.
So then what we're going to do, because we don't want
this to slow down over time
we're going to set the drag and angular drag
to infinity.
So you can do this actually by just typing
INF in the drag box and hitting return.
If you've done it correctly you'll see a capitalised
infinity.
We do want to use gravity, we want to keep the player
firmly grounded, despite this being a dream sequence.
And we do want to use
constraints, so basically we're going to use
constraints to ensure that the player
character doesn't fall forward or fall over any
different directions, and we also want
to freeze the Y position so he doesn't sink through the floor
or jump up or anything like that.
In Freeze Position we're going to choose the Y coordinate
and Freeze Rotation X and Z or Zee.
You'll have to expand constraints if it's not currently expanded.
Yep, sorry, you need to expand constraints,
if you can't see those properties you should see them
at the bottom.
Next we need to make sure things can actually
bump in to the character because currently
he reacts to physics
but if he doesn't bump in to anything
nothing's going to happen.
So if you go to Add Component
and then Physics
and then there's a capsule collider along with
all the other colliders there.
We need to give it specific settings
so we make sure that the capsule covers the player.
So if you change the centre
to 0.2 in the X
0.6 in Y and leave the Z as 0
or Zee a 0.
We also need to change the height
to 1.2, so what that's going to mean is that
this sort of leaning over character thing here
he's got a little bit of an X offset so that the
capsules going to cover him nicely.
Next we need the player to make
a little yelping sound when he gets hurt.
So we're going to add an audio source
component, so if you go to Add Component
Audio, and then find Audio Source
and we're going to change
the audio clip from None, using the little
circle select by it
to Player Hurt.
When it opens the context sensitive menu
you can see Player Hurt there.
One thing about the selection window is
that you can double click to close
it at the same time, if you want to assign something
you can open up the circle select, double click
will also close the window.
Once other thing I'm going to quickly do because we've got these
settings done is I'm going to close the rigidbody
or collapse it up using the arrow next
to it just so that we can see the ones below it.
We do not want the player to make a yelp sound
on awake, so we're going to uncheck Play On Awake
You'll know that if you haven't unchecked that
when you start the game it'll go 'oh'.
If it does that go back to this
and uncheck Play On Awake.
So we're going to find the Player Movement script
and that's in the Scripts - Player folder.
So if you look in the project panel, find Scripts, expand that
and then click on Player, you'll see on the right
hand side the different player scripts that we've got.
We've got an empty class called
Player Movement and we're going to go through
making that now.
You can assign a script a number of different ways.
A script is just a component
like any other component.
But what we're going to do is we're going to drag and drop
for this one, so I'm going to grab
my Player Movement script, I'm going to drag it
up and drop if on to the player game object.
When that's done you should see that it appears
as a component at the bottom of the list.
Be sure to save your scene before we go on to this next part
too because we're in the beta software.
So first of al double click it for opening and
you should get mono develop to come up.
There's a number of different ways to open a script.
You can either double click the icon
in the project panel, you can
click open with it selected
at the top of the inspector.
Or one final way is to, when it's
applied as a component
you can actually click the cog icon and choose
Edit Script.
If you give it a moment it's going to open up that
script editor for Unity which is
Mono Develop.
All of this is going to be done within
the class, so you notice there's a pair
of early braces, or brackets?
What we're going to start off by doing is
making some variables
that we can adjust throughout the course of class.
We're always going to start off with our public ones at the top.
and then underneath with private ones.
So we'll start off with a public float
called Speed, which is obviously
going to control how fast the player is.
I'm going to give it a default value of 6.
So the F on the end there is just
saying that this is a floating point variable.
Now we move on to the private  variables.
So I could go ahead and type
vector3 because vector2 is the first thing it suggests
I could accidentally press return and get that
but I don't, I want a vector3 type of variable.
So these variables we're declaring
the type of them first, if you're familiar with Java Script
you'll remember that it does it the other way round.
So in C# we say the type of variable first
and then the name.
So this one's going to be called Movement and
we're going to use that to store
the movement that we want to apply to the player.
The next one we're going to have a reference
to the animator component
and we'll call that Anim.
We're also going to have a reference to
the rigidbody component
and we'll call that Player Rigidbody.
So the next one is an integer
called Floor Mask, now I'm going to explain this one.
If you remember earlier we made that floor
quad, that big square that we just left
on the floor, that's the thing that we want to raycast
in to and the way we tell our raycast
that we only want to hit that floor is we use
a layermask, which is stored as an integer.
If I hit save right now, basically we designed
this project on a PC,
we've opened it on a Mac,
files have different line endings, it doesn't matter
at all, just hit Convert, everything will be fine.
So the last private variable that we're going to make
is a float
called camRayLength.
That's going to be the length of the ray
that we cast from the camera,
and we're going to give that a value of 100.
The next thing that we're going to do is setup
those references.
We're going to setup the references
in the awake function
Some of you will be familiar with
the start function, awake is very similar
but it gets called regardless of whether
the script is enabled or not.
So it's good for setting up references and things like that.
We're going to start off by setting
up our floor mask
and we're going to use LayerMask.GetMask
so then we can parse in a string
which is just a word or a sentence
of the layer that we're going to get.
So we put the floor quad
on the floor layer so we're going to get mask from floor.
Then we're going to use GetComponent to
get the references to the animator, like that.
You'll notice a little angled brackets there,
that's just denoting the type of what we're looking for.
In this case we're looking for an animator so we write .
If we were looking for a rigidbody we'd write  and so on.
So we write  here.
And that's all we need to do to setup the references.
Next what we're going to do is
put a call to fixed update.
Fixed update is a function
that Unity will automatically call on it's scripts
that fires every physics update.
Unity runs on a number of updates.
The normal update system that you're familiar with
runs along with rendering.
The fixed update runs with physics.
So since we're moving a physics character
he's got a rigidbody attached we're going to
use fixed update to move him.
So what we're going to do is get the input
from the horizontal and vertical axis,
but we're not going to get the standard input,
we're going to get the raw input.
So whereas a normal axis would have values
varying between -1 and 1
the raw axis will only have
a value of -1, 0 or 1.
It won't have any variation in between those.
So what that means is that
when we're controlling the character, rather than him
slowly accelerating towards it's full speed
he's going to immediately
snap to full speed, which will give us a much
more responsive feel.
Just so you know, an axis is actually input.
So these axis, horizontal
vertical, jump, fire1, fire2,
those are defaults within Unity,
so if you're wondering what horizontal is it's
already in there.
So the horizontal axis basically maps
to the A and D keys
as well as the left and right arrow keys.
Either of those manipulate the horizontal axis.
Pressing the A key gives me a value of -1
in the horizontal axis, pressing the D key
gives me a value of 1 in the horizontal axis.
Vertical is another axis, it's the W and S keys
as well as the up and down arrows.
Fire1 is your left mouse button
or right control, so on and so forth.
If you're curious you can go in the input manager,
I think Will had that up there a second ago
and that's where these axis exist and how we set them up.
But the ones we're all using here are defaults
so there's nothing special that you need
to do to get those.
Go ahead and put in the vertical axis as well,
we're storing that as a float called V,
so these are private variables within
fixed update so we can use
them within specifically fixed update.
So remember that the variables that we created earlier
are outside of these functions so we can use
them within any of the functions in this script.
Fixed update and awake are automatically
called by Unity, they're mono-behaviour functions.
But we can also make our own functions
that we can call within those fixed update and awake.
What we're going to do now is create a
move function that we can call in fixed update later
to move our character.
We're basically going to split up the actual
operations of those player movement script
in to movement, turning and animation.
We're going to put them in to separate functions
to keep them all modular.
If you make a Move function
that's going to have 2 parameters,
a float called H
and a float called V
and unsurprisingly those are going to be the input
that we'll parse in to this function when we call it.
We have this movement vector that we stored
earlier and we want to set the value
of that, so if you type movement.set
then you get the chance to put each of the
X, Y and Z components of those
so we're going to use H for it's X component.
We don't want any vertical components so we're
going to put that as 0.
We're going to use an F because it's a floating point.
And then V for the Z component, so what that means is
X and Z are flat along the ground.
The horizontal and vertical movement that we give it
will translate to lateral movement in the game.
Now we've set that we have a bit of a
problem because if you move
just in the Z axis or just in the X axis
then you've got a value of 1,
like a size of 1 for that vector.
However, if you use both then
the length of the vector is different,
it's 1.4,
so we need to change that so that you don't
get an advantage by moving diagonally.
What we want to do is normalise that.
So what that means is it's going to take
a direction that we have
but it's going to make sure that the size is always 1.
Effectively make sure that the player moves at the same speed
regardless of which key combination you use.
We don't want it to move at a speed of 1, we want it to
move at our speed, so we're going to times
that by our speed variable that we stored.
Also, this is called fixed update.
So we don't want it to move at
6 units per fixed update,
it would move 6 units every 50th of a second
and we wouldn't see our player ever again,
so instead we're going to change it so that it's
per seconds and the way we do that is by
multiplying by Time.DeltaTime.
DeltaTime is the time between each update call.
So if you're moving it by that much
per 50th of a second
over the course of 50 50ths of a second
it is going to move 6 units.
So finally in this function the last thing we need to do is
apply that movement to the player.
So we're going to do that using a rigidbody function
called MovePosition.
So MovePosition moves a rigidbody
to a position in world space.
So we need to move it relative
to the position that the character currently is.
We need to add our movement
to the player's position, the transform.position + movement.
So it's going to be it's current positions plus
this input that we've given him to move him
slightly further along.
The next thing that we're going to do is look at the
turning of the character.
Again we're going to make a new function.
This time we're going to call it Turning.
We don't require any parameters for this.
Because the direction the character
is facing is based on the mouse input
rather than the input that we've already stored.
The first thing that we're going to do is create
a ray that we cast
from the camera in to the scene.
Let's have a little look at how that actually works first.
If you have a look at this diagram we have
a representation of the camera,
the screen and the level plus the floor quad around the level.
So that box that you're looking at there
is effectively your level,
the floor quad is around that
and the camera, if you think of the camera as
something that's looking from where you're
looking at the game on the screen
forward on to the game level
you cast a ray, a single invisible line from that point
to the floor quad to get a particular position back.
And we want to use that because we want the
character to turn and face the
point of wherever the camera's looking.
So when you move the mouse around in the game
he's going to turn around and face that position
so that you can turn around and also shoot
in a particular direction.
So we see this end bracket on line 40,
make sure that's there.
It's a real quick gotcha that everyone always does is they
move their functions down outside of the class
by accident, so if you have
avoid Turning with your open and closed brackets
and you don't have another bracket immediately after that
you've missed one.
And don't just add another one
because then you're going to have one in the wrong spot
and another one in the wrong spot.
Instead just move that function back
up so that it is inside the class.
The first thing we're going to do in this function is
we're going to create a ray.
So we'll call that camRay,
a ray coming from the camera.
And we're going to use a function of
the camera, the main camera called
ScrenPointToRay.
So what that's going to do is take a point on
the screen and cast a ray
from that point forwards in to the scene.
So the point that we're going to give it
is the mouse position.
So it's always going to find the point
underneath the mouse if you imagine.
So if you're looking at the game,
there's a mouse on your screen, the point underneath that
mouse is the point it's going to find
if that hits the floor quad.
We need to get information back when we
do this raycast and in order to get
information back from this raycast
we need a RaycastHit variable,
so that's what we're creating here.
The next stage is to actually
cast the ray that we've created.
So we created this imaginary invisible line
and now we need to actually perform the action
of casting the ray
so that it can hit something.
A raycast function will return
true if it has hit something
and it will return false if it hasn't
So we're going to put that inside and If statement.
And if it has hit something
then the code within the If statement
will be carried out.
If it hasn't hit anything then the code within
the If statement won't be carried out
so we'll just skip out of this function.
That's what that little If at the start there is for.
So we need to give this a number of parameters.
Let's start off with the ray itself, that's the
positions and directions of the cast that we're going to have.
We need to use an Out variable
for the floor hit, so Out means
that we're going to get information out of
this function and we're going to store it
in that floorHit variable.
Next we need to give it a length,
so how far are we going to do this raycast for?.
And that's the variable camRayLength that we store earlier.
And finally we want to make sure that this raycast is
only trying to hit things on the floor layer.
That's that floor mask that we created earlier.
Remember that since this is an If statement
and a function there should be
two closed braces at the end there.
So if you see you've got if (Physics.Raycast (
and then at the end we need to close both of those brackets again.
Okay so we've got the open curly braces afterwards
and this will be the code that's carried out
if we've hit something, so we need to
create a vector3 from the
player to where the mouse has hit.
And that's the floorHit.Point,
so that's the point that it's hit the floor
minus transform.position, that's the position of the player.
We're going to apply this
to the character to make him turn
but we don't want him to sort of start leaning back
so we need to make sure that the Y component
of this vector is definitely 0.
Now we can't set a player's rotation based on
a vector so we need to change that
from a vector in to the
horrible word, quaternion.
So quaternion basically speaking is
a way of storing a rotation.
We have a vector3 but we can't
use that to store a rotation so we use a
quaternion and we're going to create one called newRotation
and quaternions are also a class
that has a number of functions of
which we're going to use one called LookRotation
So what lookRotation does, the default for
characters and cameras and things like that
in Unity and in most 3D modelling
is that the Z axis is their forward axis.
So we want to made the playerToMouse vector
the forward vector of the player.
So that's all that this function is doing
when we give it the playerToMouse.
When we actually have to apply it so we're going to
address the player rigidbody.
I'm going to use the moveRotation function
and since we don't want to give it an offset
we're trying to give it a completely new rotation.
We're just going to assign it like that, we don't need to do
transform.rotation + newRotation,
it's just this rotation.
So that's our turning, the next and final function of this,
we're going to look at the animation.
After the turning we're going to make another function
called Animating.
Now we do need to give this the
H and V parameters because
whether or not the player is walking
or idle is dependent on the input.
So what we're going to do is we're going to create
a boolean variable called Walking.
And we need this to be true
if either the H variable
or the V variable has some value.
If it's 0 then
there's no input on that axis
and we don't need to worry about it.
But if either H or V has
a value that's non-0 then
it's true and the player is walking.
So what that complicated bit of code there is doing
is saying that first of all H
is that not equal to 0?
That will return either true of false
depending on whether it's 0 or not 0.
Or
is V not equal to 0?
What this is basically saying is 'hey, did we
press the horizontal axis or did we
press the vertical axis'?
If we pressed either of those we're walking.
If we didn't we're not.
So the reason we're doing that is we want to
parse this to our animator component
so you'll remember we made a parameter called IsWalking.
And the way that we set that is we say
anim, so our reference to the animator component,
Set.Bool, so we made a parameter which
was a type bool, a boolean, true or false.
And it was called IsWalking.
So first to actually set this
we tell it which one so the IsWalking parameter
and then we give it a value, so we could here write true or false
but we want to use Walking, the variable
that we just made.
So the very last thing that we need to do in this class
is we need to put, so we need to put
calls to those functions that we've made.
Currently they're just functions sitting there by themselves.
We need to make sure that those functions are
actually being called an actually being used.
These three functions aren't happening
until we tell them to, we haven't actually
called them anywhere in the script, they just
exist and are waiting to happen.
In fixed update that we created earlier
we already got the input, we stored that.
Now after we've got the input entirety
we now need to call these functions that we've created.
So we call them just by using their name.
And then parsing in the values if they're required.
So Move requires 2 floats,
we've got our floats for input there
and that's all that we need to do.
So we need to say H and V
semi-colon.
Then we'll call Turning which doesn't take any parameters
And finally we'll call
Animati, which does.
Like that.
These are in fixed update, so they're being called
every physics step.
That is the end of that script so what I want you to do
now is to go to File - Save
and switch back to Unity.
If anything is wrong you will see an error
at the bottom of the screen in red.
When you have no errors in your script,
when you press play at the top of the editor
you can move your character around with the arrow keys
or W, A, S and D.
The animation should function
but the actual movement of the mouse should be a little bit
tricky right now because we haven't moved the
camera to the right point, so the camera isn't
seeing the entirety of the floor quad yet
and that can be a problem, but we're going to solve
that in the next phase.
So you should be able to move around.
You'll note if I move the mouse up away from the floor quad
that it doesn't rotate.
As soon as I move it back over there the rayCast
kicks back in and I can turn around
and run around this this.
Okay so we're at the end of phase 2.
Phase 3 will be setting up the camera
and we're going to have a quick look at the script that
will make that camera work.