So we have created shots,
and we can now shoot them.
But we have a problem.
Our shots are simply accumulating in the scene
flying off towards infinity on the Z axis.
Even though each shot only requires a
tiny amount of our resource budget
we will quickly have a lot of them,
each being processed and moved and tested in our scene.
We need to find a way to remove these shots
from the scene when they leave the game area.
There are a number of different ways that
that we can approach this issue.
In this assignment we are going to create
a box around our game
and we will destroy these shots as they
leave the box.
As an added bonus this boundary box
will also deal with our hazards and
destroy them when they leave the game area as well.
To create a box around our game area
create a new cube by using
the Create menu and selecting Cube.
Now a cube has a mesh
held by the mesh filter, and a mesh renderer
that we don't strictly need for our purposes.
We only need a box collider component.
However, being able to see the cube rendered
in the game view will be helpful to us
when placing the box around our game area.
So we'll use a cube
with it's mesh, mesh renderer and box collider
for our bounding box.
Rename the cube Boundary.
And reset it's transform to make sure
it is at origin.
If we turn the mesh renderer off
we will see the box collider in the scene
We don't want a physical collision with this box.
We want this box to trigger a new action
when our object's leave this box.
We want this box to be a trigger collider.
So on the box collider component select
Is Trigger.
Now in our Game view we can't
see our boundary.
the gizmo indicating the box collider
is only visible in the Scene view.
The trigger collider by itself is invisible
to our game camera.
This makes sense though, we don't want to see
see our triggers in the game.
This is why using a cube makes sense.
Let's turn the mesh renderer back on.
We want to place this box evenly
around the game area.
The centre of the game area is defined by
the position of the camera as it looks
down on the game.
The camera's transform on the X/Z plane
is 0,5.
So let's keep the boundary's transform position
X at 0 and let's set the boundary's
transform position Z to 5.
Next, using the transform scale
let's change the scale of the cube
until it surrounds our scene.
We are less concerned by the sides for this
particular game, as nothing will leave
the game area by the sides of our game.
Our background is 15 units wide
so let's match that with our cube
and use a value of 15 in the
transform scale X.
The top and bottom are more critical.
We want to get the boundary as close
to the edge of the game area as possible
as all of our shots and hazards
will leave the game area by the top
or bottom edge.
This looks like about 20.
So let's use a value of 20 for the
transform scale Z.
We actually know that 20 is the
correct value because 20 is twice
the size of our orthographic camera.
The number of units from the top of the screen
to the bottom is always twice the value of
of our camera's orthographic size.
Now that we have placed the boundary
we can turn off the mesh renderer.
When we look in the Scene view we can now see
our collider in green surrounding our game area.
We now need to have our boundary do something.
To do this the boundary needs
a script attached.
So with Boundary selected click on Add Component.
Then select New Script.
Rename the script DestroyByBoundary.
Accept these changes to add this script
to Boundary.
Select Assets to see our new script
in the root level of our project.
And let's file it in the Scripts folder.
Open the Scripts folder and select
DestroyByBoundary and open it for editing.
Our boundary game objects behaviour
will be driven by the box collider
and that box collider is a trigger.
To find out how to script to a trigger collider
we can search Trigger
in the documentation.
This will give us a list of all of the uses of
Trigger in Unity's API/
We want to destroy the shots as they
leave the box collider's trigger volume.
So let's look at OnTriggerExit.
If we look at the description it tells us that
OnTriggerExit is called when the other
collider has stopped touching the trigger.
Conveniently the sample code does
exactly what we want.
When the other collider leaves the
Boundary's trigger volume
we want to destroy the other
collider's game object.
Copy this code and paste it in to our script.
Save this script and return to Unity.
When we select Boundary we don't see any
properties on the component.
This is because there are no options
we can set on this component.
This component simply does it's job
if it's active, destroying any object that
leave the trigger's volume.
Now that our boundary is setup and in position
we can remove the mesh renderer
and the mesh filter components.
Let's save the scene and test.
And as the shots leave the game area
they are destroyed.
With our ship setup and it's weapons systems
ready to go, in the next assignment we will
create hazards to challenge our player.