Now that we can destroy our hazards
we should reward our player with points.
Let's count and display a score
where every asteroid hazard destroyed
gives our player 10 points.
We will start by creating a display for the score
before we create a score value to feed it with.
First using the Create menu
in the Hierarchy view select GUI Text.
This creates a new game object with
a GUI text component attached.
Rename this game object Score Text.
We can now see GUI text being
displayed in the centre of our game area.
The Text property on the GUI text component
drives what is being displayed.
The rest of the component describes
how this text is displayed and where this
text is displayed on screen.
We will not go in to all of the details
of the GUI text component.
For more information on GUI text
see the details linked below.
In later assignments we will create
additional GUI text objects
to hold different information.
With the default GUI text in the Text property
on all of them the Game View at edit time
could become a little confusing.
Change the Text property to Score Text.
We can see Score Text is now being
displayed in the Game View.
We will be changing this value at runtime.
Changing this label now will help
us identify which display is which while editing.
Our Score Text is currently displaying
in the middle of our screen.
Let's move it so it displayed in the upper
left of the game screen.
Before we change any settings
it's important to understand
that GUI text is drawn on a layer
above our game, not in the game world.
We won't see it in our Scene view.
Moreover it is important to understand
that the GUI text uses something called
Viewport Space, rather than screen space.
The difference, very briefly,
is that screen space is defined in pixels.
This is the number of pixels wide
and high that we set in our player settings.
Viewport Space is defined simply
as a single width and height value
with (0 0) in the lower left
and (1,1) in the upper right.
With Viewport Space in mind
set the transform position on the display text
from (0.5, 0.5) on the X and Y,
in other words the middle of the screen,
to (0, 1), which is the upper left.
The text seems wedged up against
the upper left corner.
It would be good to give it some pad
or space around it to separate
it from the edges of the game screen.
Because of the viewport space
it is awkward trying to set such a small
value of space using the transform component.
This solution to this is to use pixel offset.
Pixel offset is, not too surprisingly,
using pixels.
So we can set our primary location
with the transform component,
the upper left corner,
and then perfect it with pixel offset.
Change Pixel Offset to 10 and -10.
This will give us a 10 pixel
pad around our score text.
Separating it from the edge of the screen.
Next we need to feed Score Text
a score value.
Select Game Controller and open the
GameController script for editing.
The first thing we need is a
public GUI Text variable called scoreText
to hold a reference to our GUI text component.
The next thing we need is a
public int variable called score
to hold our current score.
We use int because we will never count
a partial point.
Score will always be a whole number.
Our game controller will keep track
of our score, increment it when we destroy hazards
and feed that value to our score text.
To update our score we need to write a new function.
Write void update score.
And the code within this function is
scoreText.text = "score: " +score.
This function will set the text property
on the Score Text component
to the string Score: plus whatever our
current score value is held by our score variable.
When written like this Unity automatically
converts the int value of Score
to a string of text characters
so it works with our text property.
This feeds our score value
to our GUI text component.
We next need to update our score
in two different places.
When we first start the game
and when a hazard is destroyed.
When we start the game the first thing we need
to do is set our score to 0.
Then we want to call update Score
to set the score text to this starting value.
Now how can we tell from inside Game Controller
when a hazard has been destroyed by the player?
Well, we can't.
But we can expose a public function
to the other game objects in our game
like the hazards themselves
and when they are destroyed the hazards
can inform Game Controller to add to the score,
and the Game Controller can use this information
as a signal to update the score text.
Let's create a public function for our hazards.
Write public void AddScore
with the parameter int newScoreValue.
First we write code to update our score value
with score += newScoreValue.
And then we call the function UpdateScore
to update our score text to display
the new current score.
We now need to call Add Score
from our game when a hazard is destroyed.
Save this script and switch back to Unity.
Let's look at our asteroid hazards
We want our instances of this prefab
to call addScore on GameController
when they are destroyed by the player.
The player destroys our hazards through the
DestroyByContact script.
So open DestroyByContact for editing.
First let's give our hazards a value
with public int scoreValue.
Now how do we call a function
on another component on a different game object?
We can try to access this by writing
GameController.AddScore
and then send the new score value
with the argument scoreValue.
Save this script and return to Unity.
Well we seem to have an error.
We can see the most recent error in the footer.
Let's open the console and look at this
error more closely.
The error seems to be on the script
we have just edited, not surprisingly,
the DestroyByContact script.
This error says
an object reference is required to access
non-static member GameController.AddScore(int).
Why is this?
This is because we are addressing the
class directly, not a specific
instance of our class.
If we look at our Game Controller object
we can see that there is a GameController
script attached.
This is an instance of this script or class.
This is very much like all of the asteroid
hazards or laser bolts that we have
instantiated in our scene.
Each one is an instance.
Even though we have one and only one
GameController script in our game
there is nothing technically stopping us
from having several.
If we created a new game object,
say a cube, there is nothing stopping
us from having another instance of
GameController on it.
Now we have two instances of our
GameController script.
When our hazard is destroyed it needs to know
which one to call AddScore on.
This is very much like valet parking.
We can't simply say
'please, can you bring our car?'.
We must have a reference to a specific car,
usually through a numbered ticket
so the valet knows which one to bring.
Let's delete our example cube.
Even though we have only one instance
we still need a reference to it.
That valet won't bring our car without a ticket,
even if it's the only one on the lot.
Reopen DestroyByContact for editing.
Let's write a variable to hold our
reference to our instance of GameController.
Write public GameController gameController
Note the 2 different capitalisation's.
The first Game Controller with a capital G
is the class name, or type.
The second Game Controller with the lower case g
is the name of our variable.
Now if we copy and paste the
name of our variable in to the
offending line of code we change the line from
addressing the class directly
to using the reference to our instance
that we have held in our variable.
Save this script and return to Unity.
And the error is gone.
Let's switch to the Game View.
Select the Asteroid prefab.
We can now see the Game Controller
type reference on the DestroyByContact component.
We need to associate our instance of
GameController with this variable.
So let's drag our GameController object
on to the slot to make the reference.
Okay, that doesn't work.
Let's try to use the asset picker.
Nope.
This is not working.
Why?
This comes back to the nature of instances.
Instances are copies of objects within a scene.
Now if we think about the nature of prefabs,
prefabs are templates of game objects
that can be instantiated in any scene in our game.
It doesn't make sense that a template
that can be added to any scene in our game
can hold a reference to an instance
in just one scene.
Now once we have instantiated our
hazards in to the scene
and we have an instance of our hazard
these instances can hold a reference
to our instance of the Game Controller.
So we have to find our references
to the Game Controller after the game has started.
Each new hazard will have to find a new
reference to Game Controller
when they are instantiated.
Open DestroyByContact for editing.
Every hazard has an instance of this script
and every hazard will have to find
their own reference to the Game
Controller component on the Game
Controller game object.
Let's modify this script to do just that.
In Start we first need to find
the game object that holds
our Game Controller script.
Let's call this reference the
gameControllerObject.
We will set this reference by using
GameObject.FindWithTag
and the tag we will look for is
GameController.
This will find the first game object in the
scene that we have tagged as GameController
and we have only one.
Remember we tagged our Game Controller object
with Game Controller when we created it.
Next if we have successfully found the
game controller object,
and we check this by testing the reference
to the Game Controller object.
So if the Game Controller object
is not null
where null means nothing or empty
essentially no reference,
then we will set our Game Controller
reference to the Game Controller component
on the Game Controller object.
We do this by searching the Game Controller
object and getting the component on it,
with GetComponent.
searching for the type of GameController.
Note this syntax where
Game Controller is in angle brackets
followed by parenthesis.
Technically this is all the code we need.
We are however going to write
an insurance policy.
If, after all this work,
our Game Controller reference is
the same as null
we will use Debug.Log
to put "Cannot find 'GameController' script"
in to the console.
Note that we are using single quotes
around GameController so the entire
message is one string of text.
This is an insurance policy.
With hope this line of code will never get called.
If however something goes wrong
and we accidentally break something
and our game stops working or behaves badly
with messages like these in our console
we will have a place to start.
Save this script and return to Unity.
Let's setup our asteroid hazard.
Select the Asteroid prefab game object
and set the Score value to 10.
Below Score Value is the reference
to Game Controller.
We can't set this in the Inspector.
If we cannot set this in the Inspector
let's not see it in the Inspector.
Open DestroyByContact for editing.
Change public to private
on the Game Controller reference.
Save this script and return to Unity.
Now we have no access to this property
in the Inspector or from any other
script, it is private.
Let's setup our Game Controller.
Select Game Controller.
Take note of Score.
Unlike the Game Controller reference on the
Asteroid prefab we can set Score in the Inspector,
we just don't want to.
Score is handled perfectly well in the script.
This property is set by the script on the
first frame of the game so let's
set this one to private as well.
Open the Game Controller for editing.
Change score from public to private.
Save this script and return to Unity.
We no longer see, not have access,
to score.
Let's set our reference to our Score display.
With GameController selected
drag the Score Text game object
on to the Score Text property
on the Game Controller component.
Save the scene and enter Play mode.
And now we score 10 points for each
asteroid we destroy and the score is
displayed in the upper left.
Fantastic.
Next, in the penultimate assignment,
we will learn how to break out of our infinite loop
and end the game.