Our player is powered up, armed and ready to go.
Let's create some hazards to challenge our player.
We will be creating an asteroid prefab to
throw at our player and we will use an
architecture similar to the one we used
to make the Bolt prefab.
We will have a parent game object for the logic
and the artwork will be a child.
To start, let's create a new game object
and rename it Asteroid.
Reset the asteroid's transform to origin
and move it up along the Z axis to about 8.
By moving the asteroid parent a little further
up the game area it will both separate
the asteroid from the player while we build it
and allow us to easily test it when we are finished.
Next let's get some artwork for our asteroid.
If we open the Models folder in Assets
we have 3 asteroid models to choose from.
We are going to use the first one.
Select the asteroid model and drag it on
to the Asteroid parent game object.
When we drop it the Asteroid model will
be a child of the Asteroid game object.
I am going to reset the model's transform.
By resetting the entire transform
the model will be centred on the parent game object
with no relative rotation and a scale of 1
relative to the parent game object.
For our game it's important that the transform's
position be at local origin.
The game is designed to work with the asteroid
model at a local scale of 1.
But we may find it interesting to experiment
with local scale after we are done with this project
to see how it changes the game and gameplay.
With our artwork in place let's setup
the components and logic.
Select the parent Asteroid game object
and use the Add Component button to
add a physics rigidbody.
As our game is playing along the X/Z plane
deselect Use Gravity so the asteroid
does not fall in to the void.
Now let's use the Add Component again
to add a physics capsule collider.
Again we have what looks like a green wire
sphere around our asteroid.
We need to change the radius and the height
of the capsule collider to more accurately
match our model.
Now we could try to set these using the
properties on the component.
But this is a less than ideal way of doing things.
We can however change the shape of the
capsule collider directly in the Scene view.
The trick here is to hold down the shift key.
When we hold down the shift key drag handles
appear on the collider.
With these we can simply drag the collider
shape until we are satisfied.
Now that we have our basic physics component setup
let's save the scene and enter Play mode.
Wow, that's one boring asteroid.
Exit Play mode.
Let's give it some life and make it tumble.
With the asteroid game object selected
use the Add Component button to
create a new script.
Rename the script RandomRotator.
and accept the changes to add
this script to Asteroid.
Select Assets and file the new script
in to the Scripts folder.
Open the Scripts folder and select RandomRotator
and open the script for editing.
The first thing we want to do is create a public
float called Tumble
to hold our maximum tumble value
which we will be able to set in the Editor.
Now in Start
we want to set our rigidbody's angular velocity.
What is angular velocity?
Angular velocity is how fast a rigidbody
object is rotating
and we want to set our angular velocity to
some random value.
Now Unity has a Random class
and it's very convenient for giving us all
sorts of random values.
The most basic is literally random value.
This will return a random float value
between 0 and 1
and then we can do anything we want
to with this random number.
But there are several more interesting items in
the Random class that can give us more complex
and more useful values if we look at the
class in detail.
For our asteroid let's look at
Random.InsideUnitSphere.
This may sound intimidating, and it may also
sound like it has nothing to do with tumbling
an asteroid, but in actuality it is
everything that we need.
InsideUnitySphere gives us a random
vector3 value that we can apply to our
rigidbody's angular velocity.
And each of the 3 X, Y and Z values
will be randomised individually.
Copy Random.InsideUnitSphere
and paste it in to our code
and multiply it by Tumble.
This simple script takes our tumble value
from the Editor and at start
we set the new asteroid's rigidbody.angularVelocity
to a random vector3 value from
Random.InsideUnitSphere.
and then we multiply this by tumble.
Save the script and return to Unity.
Select Asteroid and let's set the
tumble value to 5.
Save the scene and enter Play mode to test.
And our asteroid now has a random tumble.
Let's enter and exit Play mode a few more times.
We can see that every time the script calls Start
we get a different random angular velocity.
If, however, we leave it for a short
period of time
the asteroid slows to a stop.
This is due to a default value
on the rigidbody component.
The rigidbody has 2 parameters to simulate
resistance, like air friction,
and these are Drag and Angular Drag.
Angular Drag by default has a small
but working value.
Exit Play mode.
Let's drop this value to 0.
Enter Play mode.
Now our asteroid has now angular drag
being applied to it's angular velocity
so it will keep tumbling until it's destroyed
by the player or by the boundary.
Exit Play mode.
Speaking of which, what happens if our
player tries to shoot the asteroid?
Enter Play mode.
Nothing.
Our asteroid has a collider on it
and so do our laser bolts.
Why don't we see any interaction?
That's because they are both trigger colliders
and triggers don't have physical collisions,
and we have written nothing that can
capture the trigger event.
We will need to write more trigger related
code for our 2 colliders to have any effect.
Exit Play mode.
With Asteroid selected use the Add Component
button to create a new script.
Rename this script DestroyByContact
and accept the changes to add this
new script to Asteroid.
File the script
and open it for editing.
After removing the sample code
let's write Trigger again and
search the documentation.
In this case we want to destroy the asteroid
when the bolt first touches it
so let's select OnTriggerEnter.
This code is very much like the code
we used for our boundary.
except this code is called when a
collider first touches the trigger collider
rather than when the collider leaves the
trigger volume.
This sample code is also convenient
as it does almost everything we need.
When another collider enters the trigger
we are given a reference to that other collider
as Collider other.
The code then destroys the other
collider's game object.
Copy this code and paste it in to our script.
This code as it stands will destroy the
laser bolt when it hits the asteroid.
Next we need to destroy the asteroid
itself with Destroy (gameObject).
Destroy (gameObject) will destroy the game object
this script is attached to
which in this case is the asteroid
and all of it's children and all
their attached components.
One quick note about destroy.
Destroy does not immediately destroy the
object listed in the parenthesis.
It marks the object to be destroyed
and all of the marked objects are
destroyed at the end of the frame.
So we can put these destroy lines
in any order.
It seems wrong if we destroy this
game object before we call destroy on
the other one.
But code-wise it doesn't matter what order
we mark our objects to be destroyed
as long as they are marked in the same frame.
Save this script and return to Unity.
Again, this script has no properties
for us to set in the Editor.
It will just work as long as it's
attached to an active game object.
Let's save our scene and enter Play mode.
Where's our asteroid?
Let's exit Play mode.
There it is.
Okay, enter Play mode
and it's gone!
We can see our asteroid in Edit mode
but it vanishes in Play mode.
No, we aren't standing at a flux point
in the probability field, we have a bug.
Let's do some simply debugging.
Let's exit Play mode.
We turn to our DestroyByContact script.
If something is calling our new trigger code
and destroying our asteroid we need to
find out what that something is.
In OnTriggerEnter let's write
debug.logOther.name
This will send the name of the game object
that Other is attached to
as a line in our console log.
Save this script and return to Unity.
Enter Play mode.
and now we see who the culprit is,
it's Boundary.
We see the most recent error or message
in the footer, we can also check the
console for more detailed information.
If we look in to the Hierarchy we can see
that Boundary is also missing from
our scene, it has been destroyed.
Exit Play mode and switch to the Scene view.
Now if we focus our Scene view camera
on the Boundary we can look at
the relationship between the asteroid and Boundary.
Asteroid is right there in the middle of the boundary
On the very first frame Asteroid
detects it's inside Boundary
and Boundary triggers our OnTriggerEnter
code on Asteroid, and the code destroys
both game objects in the very first frame.
We need to test our OnTriggerEnter
code and ignore collisions with Boundary.
One way of identifying an object is with a tag.
Let's tag our boundary.
Select Boundary and in the header of
the game object is it's tag.
We can see it is untagged.
Click on the Tag drop-down and select Add Tag.
This brings up Tags and Layers in the Inspector.
Our custom tag list is empty
so let's add a new tag, Boundary.
Now if we look back at our boundary game object
we can see it is still untagged.
This is an important note.
We used Add Tag on the Tag drop-down
to create a new tag, but we still must
assign that new tag.
So with Boundary selected
click on the Tag drop-down and select Boundary.
We now have successfully tagged this game
object as Boundary.
Return to our DestroyByContact script.
Let's remove our Debug line and replace it with
If the other tag
is the same as Boundary
then return.
Return ends the execution of a function
and hands the control back to the
function that called it, which in some cases
maybe Unity itself.
Optionally a value can be passed back
as well with return.
In our case return simply ends this
function at that point and returns the
control back to Unity's game loop,
which means we will never reach or execute
the Destroy code if the other's
tag is Boundary.
Save the script and return to Unity.
Enter Play mode and there's our asteroid.
Fire our weapons and the asteroid
and the laser bolt are destroyed.
When the asteroid entered the boundary
on the first frame the trigger message
was cut short and the destruction code was ignored.
Now we have a tumbling asteroid and destruction code.
In the next assignment we will add explosions,
move the asteroid and save it as a prefab
for our game controller to use.