Welcome to the Space Shooter project.
In this project we will build this
top down arcade style shooter.
In the foundation assignments we will
import the assets we need,
setup our base project and set the
build target for our game.
We will then setup the basic player game object,
preparing it to move, shoot and interact
with the other objects in the scene.
To prepare the scene we will setup
the camera, lights and background.
We will show how to setup game object,
attach pre-made components,
and use our models and artwork in our scene.
With our scene setup we will write simple
custom code in C#
to capture the player's input and use it
to move our player's ship.
We will create lazerbolts for our player to shoot.
We will create asteroid hazards
to challenge our player.
We will write a game controller to control out game,
spawn our hazards in waves,
count and display our score and manage
how we end and when we can restart our game.
We will add audio effects and a background music track.
Finally we will build and deploy the game to the web.
In more advanced lessons and live sessions
we will use this project for further learning,
where we will add enemy ships,
scroll the background and add the star field and more.
To get started begin with Assignment 1 - Setting Up The Game.