In this assignment we will create a new project,
import our assets, save our main scene
and set up the basic foundations for our game.
Let's begin by creating a brand new project.
We can do this by selecting File - New Project.
This opens the Project Wizard.
In the Project Wizard we can open an existing
project or create a new one.
We will be creating a new project.
First we need to set a location for our new project.
We can do this by selecting the Set button,
which brings up a Save As dialogue box.
I'm going to put this new project on my desktop.
I will call it Space Shooter.
Save this and return to the wizard.
Now if we look at the desktop
we will see that no files have been created.
We have simply set the path to the location
where Unity will build the new project.
At this stage we have the choice to import
packages of assets we have on our computer
These could be packages that came from the
original install, packages from the asset store
or packages that we have saved ourselves.
For this assignment we want a new clean
empty project, so we won't select
any packages to import.
Click on Create Project to create this new project.
Unity will close the existing project,
build the project files and open the new
project in the Editor.
Now we are ready to go.
The next step is to import the
assets for this project.
Most likely you will download these from the
learn site and asset store.
When your import is ready
you will see a window like this one.
These are all the files we need for this project.
Make sure they are all selected.
If not click the All button in the bottom left,
then select Import to import these assets.
Unity will copy these files to our new project
compile any scripts and import all of the assets.
We will be creating this project from scratch
using the assets provided.
If however you are confused by any step
this project does include a Done folder
which contains the entire project in finished form.
There is a final scene, Done_Main,
final scripts, final prefabs and more.
Now that we have our assets let's save
the scene that we will be working in.
When working in Unity we will always
have a scene open.
Unity opened a default scene for us
when we started the project.
Our current scene is unsaved.
We get a hint to remind us if our scene
has been saved if we read the header bar.
The header bar always lists the scene,
project name and build target.
Our header bar shows Untitled
which is our unsaved scene.
Space Shooter, our current project
and PC, Mac and Linux Standalone
which is our build target.
We will discuss build targets in a moment.
To save our scene select File - Save Scene,
or use the hot-key combination.
Scenes need to be saved in our Assets directory.
They can be in any directory within the Assets directory.
I'm going to create a new directory to hold
my scene, I will call this new directory
_Scenes.
The underscore is not necessary but I like it
as it will sort this directory to the top of
my project view where it will be easy to find.
Next I will name this scene Main
and hit Save to save it.
We can see that we now have a directory called
_Scenes and a scene file called Main.
We can also see Main as the
scene listed in the header bar.
Now that we have imported our assets and
saved our scene we need to set our build target.
Whenever we are working on a project we are
always working with a build target.
Our current build target is the default
PC, Mac and Linux Standalone.
All of our assets will be imported for this target
and all of our scripts will be compiled
for this target, so it's important to have our
build settings set to the intended target platform.
Don't forget Unity can have one project
and one codebase for all of our build targets
and most of what we develop will work
for all platforms, but we will be developing
for only one platform at a time.
To set our build target we can select
File - Build Settings, or use the hot-key combination.
This will bring up the Build Settings window.
Here we can set the details of our build
and select the scenes we want to build in to our game.
We want to change the build target to
Web Player, as we will be building and
deploying this project to the web.
Click on Web Player to select the web player build target.
The blue highlight indicates we have selected the Web Player.
We can see the details on the right change,
but we have not changed the build target.
Our current build target is indicated by the
Unity logo and is shown in the header bar.
To change build targets select the
platform you want and click Switch Platform.
Now the Unity logo is associated with
our new build target, and that new build
target is listed in the header.
Now that we have set our build target we need to set
the build details for our game.
We can do this from the Build Settings window
by selecting Player Settings.
This allows us to inspect and change our player settings.
If we want to change our player settings and the
build window is not open we can select
Edit - Project Settings - Player.
With Player Settings open in the Inspector
we can change both project-wide settings
and platform-specific settings.
For more information on player settings
see the details linked below.
For this project we can leave everything at
default except Resolution.
I would like this Space Shooter game to have
the feeling of an upright arcade game,
portrait rather than landscape,
so let's change the resolution to 600 by 900.
So that we can see an accurate representation
of our game let's make sure that
the aspect ratio in the Game view
is set to Web.
This will use the 600 by 900
size and aspect ratio.
With this size and aspect ratio however
I do notice that the game view looks cramped
and small in it's window.
I'm not sure this is how I want to view my game
as I develop.
The solution to this is easy, change the layout.
I'm going to grab the Game view tab and drag
it up to the top between the Scene view and Console.
This will give me a big easy to read view
of my scene, game and console.
Undoubtedly you will have a different layout.
but be aware that changing the layout is easy
Now that I've changed the layout let's save it.
If we don't save our layouts and we reselect
the current layout our layout will return
to the last saved configuration.
To save the layout select Layout and choose
Save Layout.
Either save over the current layout to update it
or choose a new name for a new layout.
I'm going to create a new layout and I'm going to
call it Space Shooter.
Now that I've changed my layout I can return to
this one by simply selecting it from the
Layout pull-down menu.
That's it for setting up this project.
Now that we've setup the project, in the next
assignment we will setup the main player game object.