In this assignment we will setup the camera
and lighting for our game.
Our game will be a top-down style game
where we are looking down on the game area
from a fixed position above the game.
If we switch to the Game view we can see
that the camera is in a completely different
position from where it needs to be for our game
When we look at the main camera in the Scene view
we can see that it is behind the player
game object and slightly above it.
This is the default starting position for the
main camera in a new scene.
Unity will always include a default main
camera at this position in every new scene.
At this point it's worth noting that in the
Scene view, when we have a camera selected
we can see a preview for that camera in the
lower right of the Scene view.
So we want to move the camera to
a position above the game area
where it is looking down on the game.
Don't forget that the camera is simply a
camera component attached to a game
object in our scene.
We can manipulate the camera in our scene
by effecting the camera's transform.
First let's reset the camera's transform
by using Reset on the context sensitive gear menu.
This will reset the transform values and
set the camera to the origin point with
no rotation and a scale of 1.
With the camera at origin let's rotate it
to face down by adjusting the rotation
on the X axis to 90 degrees.
Next let's grab the transform
by using the transform handles
and lift it up along the Y axis.
We can see how the camera preview is updating
to show what the camera is rendering
For our game we can simply change
the Y value to 10,
placing the camera 10 units above the player ship.
Now that the camera is in place, let's setup
the camera component.
The first decision we need to make is about
the camera type.
Will our projection be perspective or orthographic?
Our game needs to feel like an upright arcade game.
These did not have any perspective
so we will choose orthographic as our projection mode.
When we are using a perspective camera
if we want to change how much of our game
the camera sees we can adjust the
field of view value.
This is a lot like changing the zoom on a
real world camera.
The larger the field of view, the wider
the lens as it were,
and the more our camera can see and render.
When we are using an orthographic camera
we can adjust how much the camera will see
by changing the orthographic size.
But what is the correct size for our game?
We can see a fairly reasonable representation
of the camera in the preview window.
But it might be better to do any final
adjustments in the Game view itself.
We will still have control over the component
in the Inspector and we can see the
actual camera output full size.
It seems that the ship feels right when the
orthographic size is around 10.
So let's set that value to around 10 exactly.
Now the player is in the exact centre of the game area.
I feel that the ship should start
near the bottom of the screen.
What's the best way to do this?
We could switch back in to the Scene view
and move the ship by dragging the ship's
transform handles, but we have no good feedback
from the Game view or the camera to know if
we have chosen the correct position.
We could change our layout so we have both
the Game and the Scene view open at the same time.
But we don't need to.
Let's switch back to the Game view
and move the ship while we are able to see it
in the full sized Game view window.
We will need to move the ship by directly
manipulating the ship's transform component.
We want to move the ship along the Z axis,
so click on the Field title,
in this case the Z,
and drag back and forth until the ship
looks correct in the scene.
Now we have a problem.
We really want the player's game object
to be at origin.
We want this for 2 reasons.
1, it just feels better to me.
And 2, it will make certain steps
later on in this project easier to manage.
Yet I still want to have the player's ship
start down here at the bottom of the game area.
Well as we know, all things are relative.
So let's move the camera, not the player.
Reset the ship's transform back to origin
and select the main camera.
Again, by dragging the Field title,
move the camera's transform up along the Z axis
until the ship is in a good position.
This feels like a good position for the player's ship.
Let's clean up the value for the camera's
transform Z axis.
A clean round 5 is good.
Next let's set the camera's background.
Currently we have the default background
found in the Clear Flag setting.
This is Skybox.
We won't be using a skybox today,
we simply want a black background.
So let's change the clear flags
to solid colour.
It's worth noting that if our clear flags
is set to Skybox and we have no
skybox assigned clear flags will use the
background colour instead.
This is why, even though we have skybox selected,
we see the blue from the background colour.
Click on the colour box.
This will bring up a colour picker.
Let's make our background black.
When we are done we can close the colour picker.
We have no lights in this scene.
Our background is black, yet we can still
see our player ship. Why is that?
If we go to Edit - Render Settings
we can see a property called Ambient Light.
Ambient Light is the light from
no fixed point that lights all
the surfaces in the scene.
All new scenes have an ambient light set to
(51, 51, 51).
So every new scene has a very
dim ambient light added to all objects in that scene.
These values can be adjusted to add
a general colour or full white light
to all objects in the scene.
However, this light has no directionality
and it can be very unflattering if used incorrectly.
We will set our ambient light to Black,
effectively turning it off.
Now let's light our scene.
We will be creating a modified 3 point lighting
system for our game with a main or key light,
a fill light and a rim light.
These three lights will show off the shapes of
our objects and give our game a
good sense of atmosphere.
Start by selecting Create - Directional Light
from the Create menu in the Hierarchy view.
This will add a directional light to our scene
Rename this game object Main Light.
Next let's reset the light's position.
This will set the light to origin.
We won't see any change in the lighting
as directional lights light the entire scene
based on their rotation, not their position.
Switching back to the Scene view will show us the light
and the gizmo will show us it's
orientation in the scene.
Let's now reset the rotation as well,
so we can have a clean set of values to start from.
This is our main light, so it will be the
brightest and most important.
We need to see the light on the ship
from our main camera, which is above the player.
So let's tilt the main light down on to
the scene, but not too much.
We want to see the shape of the ship,
but not wash it out.
That looks good. It's nearly at 20 degrees.
So let's clean up that value to around
20 degrees down in to the scene.
Now let's rotate the light around on it's Y axis
and bring the light in from the side.
Let's pick a good point towards the front
but not directly in front.
It feels good about here.
Let's clean up these values to around -115.
To see how this light works in our game
let's switch back to the Game view.
We want the main light to feel like the light
from a nearby sun, so let's increase the
intensity to 0.75.
This gives a nice hot feeling to
the right side of the ship.
We could change the colour, but let's
leave the main light at white for now.
This lighting might seem realistic for some
deep space environment but the other side
of the ship is far too dark for this game.
To light this side of the ship we need another light.
This will be our fill light, to fill in the
shadows on the far side.
To build our fill light duplicate the main light.
Make sure the main light is selected
and then use Edit - Duplicate
or use the hot-key combination.
Rename the duplicate Fill Light.
These 2 lights are now doubling up on the same
surfaces as the lights add together.
Don't worry, we'll soon change this.
First, let's reset the rotation on the fill light
and then switch to the Scene view so we can see
the gizmo on the light.
We could set this light by eye in the Game view
but it can also be helpful to see the light's
gizmo when making adjustments.
Let's grab the fill light and rotate it around
on the Y axis.
Here we want to light the other side of the ship.
Also from a direction in front of the ship
to compliment the key light.
This feels good.
Let's look at the lighting in the Game view.
The direction of the fill light looks good
but it's feeling like we now have 2 main lights.
We don't need 2 main lights,
so let's reduce the intensity of the fill light
down to 0.5.
And let's change the colour as well
A hint of blue will tell us that this is a secondary light.
Let's reduce the red channel to 128
and then let's also reduce the values of
the green and blue channels as well,
down to about 192.
Generally darkening our fill colour.
By toggling the fill light we can see how it's
lighting that side of the ship.
Lastly, let's tilt down a little in to the scene,
5 degrees is enough,
and let's clean up the rotation on the Y axis,
making it a nice round 125. That looks good.
Now let's add the rim light.
Duplicate the fill light and rename it Rim Light.
So we can see our rim light,
which will be fairly subtle,
let's turn off the fill light.
Now select the rim light and reset the
transform to remove the rotational values.
This rim light needs to be fairly clear
and it needs to stand out when mixing in
with the fill light, so let's change the
colour to pure white.
Now we want to light the rear of the ship
in a way that compliments the fill light.
So let's rotate the light around to catch
the rear edges of the ship,
but on the same side as the fill.
This looks good.
Let's make this value a clean 65 degrees.
This shows the edge well, but it's also
acting now like a second fill light.
This is mostly due to how much light
spills on to the top of the ship.
To fix this let's rotate the light on the X axis
and come up from below.
Now this may seem counter intuitive,
as we are looking down on the ship,
but this will keep the light from shining on the top
surface of the ship and it will still
catch the edges that we need to light.
-15 degrees seems fine.
Lastly, let's drop the intensity down to 0.25.
This may seem overly subtle
but when we add the fill light back in
we can see that they add together to give
us a good rim light and fill.
Now that we have added our lights to the hierarchy
they are sorted alphabetically and mixed in
with all of the other game objects.
This is not very well organised.
If we look in to our Scene view and select our new lights
the gizmos appear right where we are working
on top of our ship in the middle of the scene.
Let's add some organisation to our scene.
We can organise our scene by using empty game object.
Add a new empty game object to the scene using the hot-key.
Use shift-command-N on the mac
and shift-control-N on windows.
Rename this Lighting.
Reset the game object's transform.
It's important to note this step
When we are using empty game objects
to organise our hierarchy
those game objects should be at origin
with no rotation and a scale of 1.
This can be accomplished by simply
resetting the transform component.
Now that we have setup our lighting game object
we can drag our lights in to it.
This organises our hierarchy and keeps
our lights together.
To clean up the gizmos at origin
we can move our lighting parent game object
up on the Y axis to get it out of the way.
Let's move them up by 100 units.
Now, there they are, up there out of the way.
We can move these lights like this because
they are directional lights
and directional lights light the entire scene
based on their transform's rotation
not their position.
This sets up our camera and our lighting.
In the next assignment we will create
a background for our game.