Our player can now move their ship
around the game area and it can't
leave the bounds of the game.
So now let's create shots
for our player to shoot.
First let's begin by deactivating
our player game object.
This assignment won't involve the players ship
and again it will simply be in the way.
Next create a new empty game object
Use shift+command+N on the Mac
and shift+control+N on Windows.
Rename the new empty game object Bolt.
This will be a parent game object for our shot.
We are going to separate the game logic
from our visual effect of the shot.
This will allow us to easily make new
weapons with different visual effects
by reusing the parent game object with the
logic and replacing the visual effect layer
Reset the game object's transform to make
sure it is at origin.
Now create a quad to hold our
visual effect image, just like we did
for our background.
Rename the quad VFX
and reset the quad's transform.
Now add the VFX game object
as a child of Bolt.
If we switch to the Scene view we can see the quad
just like the one we used for the background
is oriented in a way we can't see
with our game view camera.
Change the transform rotation X to 90.
This will rotate the quad to face upwards
towards the game view camera.
See, it's perfectly face-on to
camera in the game view.
Let's make this shot look like a laser bolt.
So next we need to find artwork
for our laser bolt.
Open the Textures folder.
In the Textures folder find  fx_laser_orange.
When we created the background
we simply dragged the nebula texture
on to the background quad and allowed
Unity to make the material for us.
This time let's not drag the texture
on to the quad, but let's create
and assign the material ourselves.
We want to create a new material
in the Materials folder.
When we create a new asset
Unity will create that asset in the
folder we have focused or in the
same folder as the asset we are currently inspecting.
Select the Materials folder in the
root level of Assets.
With the Materials folder selected click on
the Create menu in the Project view
and select Material.
This creates a new material
in the Materials folder.
The new material is ready for a new name.
So let's rename the material fx_bolt_orange.
We want to add our texture
fx_laser_orange to our material, but how?
If we can't inspect the details of a material
it's inspector may be collapsed.
Click on the Materials header to expand the
Materials Inspector panel if it's closed.
We can now see all of the fields
for this material.
There are 2 ways we can associate
a texture with this material.
The first is, in the Materials
main texture field we can click on Select
and this will bring up an Asset Picker.
At the top of the asset picker is a search
field to refine the contents of the picker.
Otherwise we will get every possible object
in the project that can go in to this field.
To associate a texture we simply
click on the texture we want.
In this case fx_laser_orange.
If there is already an existing texture
associated with this field, and we want to remove it
we can select None.
The other way is to simply drag and drop
a texture in to this field.
Select Textures in the root of Assets
and drag fx_laser_orange on to our
fx_bolt_orange material.
and drop it in to the main texture field.
Both ways associate a texture to a material.
If we look below the material in the Inspector
we see a preview window where we can get
a sense of how this material will
behave in our scene.
Now to associate the material
with the VFX quad
we can simply drag the material on to the quad.
Now if we look at the VFX game object
and inspect the mesh renderer
we can see the fx_bolt_orange material
has been added to the top slot of the materials array.
Another way of associating the material
with this game object is to populate
these slots in the materials array by hand.
We can simply drag and drop a material
in to the slots we need.
If we swap to the game view however our
laser bolt looks like a dull streak
in the middle of a big black square.
Not very flashy.
What we need to do in this case is change
the shader we are using.
Just like when we created our background
diffuse is not the best shader
choice for our weapon.
For our weapon we want the bright parts to
add on top of the scene and the black parts
to vanish.
When looking at the VFX game object
we can change the shader on the material.
Choose Particles - Additive.
With this shader black has a value
of 0 and will add nothing to the scene.
And white has a value of 255
on all channels and will add
full white to the scene.
All of the other colours will be added
on top of the existing background.
This will give us a strong, hot laser bolt.
We can also try mobile particles additive.
For our game I don't see any noticeable issues
with using the mobile shader.
It looks just fine when we look in the game view.
In many cases mobile shaders can be used
effectively in non-mobile games.
In general the mobile shaders will
be more efficient with our game's resource budget,
but in some cases may sacrifice either
quality or control.
The main control that we will lose
by using this mobile shader
is the ability to change the tint colour,
which we don't need on our laser bolt.
With our visual effects setup let's move
on to setting up our logic.
If we look at our Bolt parent game object
we can see that it has no components,
beyond the default transform component.
We will be moving these shots with physics
and, almost more importantly
we will be moving a collider in our game.
Both require the rigidbody component
so let's click on Add Component.
and select Physics - Rigidbody
to add a rigidbody component to the Bolt game object.
Deselect Use Gravity as we don't want our shots
falling down off of the game plane.
Next we need a collider to participate
in collisions.
Before we add one however we want
to remove one.
Click on VFX to show our quad.
The stock quad is created with a
mesh collider on it.
We can disable the mesh renderer to see
the green lines of this mesh collider.
We don't need 2 colliders in this game
object family, but more importantly
we don't want a collider that sticks out
so far to the sides
beyond the image of our laser bolt.
This would mean what looks like a near miss
could cause a collision.
One the mesh collider component
use the context sensitive gear menu
and click on Remove Component.
This will remove the mesh collider component
from the VFX game object.
Now let's add the collider component
we want for our game.
Click on the parent Bolt game object
and click on Add Component.
Select Physics - Capsule Collider.
Now this looks like a sphere but it is
not, it is a capsule.
A capsule is defined by 2 spheres
or hemispheres, one at each end.
and the space in between.
We are looking at a capsule that is
as compact as possible, and there's no
space between the 2 end caps.
So let's adjust the size of the capsule.
We can reduce the radius dramatically
as our bolt is long and thin.
When we do we can see that the
capsule is oriented differently from our bolt.
The default orientation, or direction of a capsule
is along the Y axis
to accommodate humanoid characters.
Let's change the direction to the Z axis.
Now it's oriented with our Bolt VFX.
Let's move in to a top-down position.
This view will help us size the collider
correctly to our visual effect.
Let's pick a radius that best matches our image.
0.03 looks good.
Now let's reduce the height to fit
our image as well.
0.5 looks good.
We don't need the outer glow to have any
physical effect in our game
just the hot core of our laser bolt.
Before we leave this collider component
we need to set one other property.
We need to select Is Trigger
to make this collider a trigger collider.
For more information on triggers and colliders
please see the lesson linked below.
With the basic component setup
we now need to write our custom logic.
With the Bolt game object selected
click on Add Component
and choose New Script.
Name this script Mover.
Confirm this choice to add it to Bolt.
Let's file Mover in to the Scripts folder
and open it for editing.
Again, let's remove the sample code.
So what do we need to write?
That depends upon what we want our laser
bolt to do.
We want it to move automatically when
it's added to the scene.
We want the laser bolt to have it's own velocity,
which we can set through the rigidbody.
So let's write void Start.
With Start the code we will write
will be executed on the very first frame
the object is instantiated.
Let's continue with rigidbody.velocity =
Well what?
We want the laser bolt to travel along
the Z axis towards the
oncoming hazards the game will
throw at our player.
The local Z axis of an object is
also known as it's transform forward.
So let's finish with transform.forward.
We will want some control over how
fast our laser bolt moves in our game
so let's add public float speed.
and let's multiply transform.forward by speed.
That's it. It's a very simple script.
Save this script and return to Unity.
We can see Bolt now has Speed as part of
the Mover component we have just written
Our player is going to shoot many copies
or clones of this shot, so let's save this
game object as a prefab.
The easiest way to do this is to drag
the Bolt game object from the Hierarchy view
in to the Prefabs folder in Assets.
Click on Prefabs so we can see our Bolt prefab.
Currently we have full access to the
components on this prefab, but note that the
preview window is open.
Even though we can scroll to see all of the
components on a game object.
If this preview window gets in the way
it can simply be dragged down and closed
against the bottom.
Let's set the speed value for our bolt.
How fast was our ship travelling?
10?
Our shots need to go faster than our ship
so let's try a speed value of 20.
Lastly we only want an instance of
the Bolt game object in our scene
when our player fires it's weapon.
So let's delete our working instance
of Bolt from the scene.
So save the scene.
Turn off Maximise On Play
if it's on and enter Play mode.
To test the bolt, as we don't have any shooting code
we can simply drag copies of the prefab
in to the hierarchy window
while the game is running.
And they work as we expected.
Of they go towards the top of the screen.
These are our shots with their VFX
and their logic.
In the next assignment we will write the code
for our player to fire these in the game.