Now we have shots for our player to shoot
so let's enable our player to shoot them.
For this assignment we will need our
player game object, so select Player
and reactivate the player game object.
Next we need to edit our Player Controller script.
There are several different ways that we can
open a script for editing.
In this case, with the player selected,
use the context sensitive gear menu
on the Player Controller component
and selected Edit Script.
This will open our script in our script editor.
We want our player to shoot shots
in to our scene.
We have saved our shots as a prefab
game object in our project.
This is an asset that we can use
when our game is running.
What we need to do is instantiate
a copy of clone of this Shot prefab
when we hit a button or click a mouse
during our game play.
Where are we going to write this code?
Well, simply getting input from a button
doesn't require physics,
and we don't want to wait for a fixed update
to fire our weapon.
So let's put our code in the Update function.
Write void Update.
Unity will execute all of the code in Update
just before updating the frame, every frame.
Now we want to instantiate our shot.
How do we use instantiate?
Well, let's check the documentation.
The shortcut to Unity's scripting reference
in the documentation is command+' on the Mac
and control+' on Windows.
And choose Object Instantiate.
For more detailed information on instantiate
please see the lesson linked below.
Instantiate needs an object to instantiate
and a position and rotation to set
the object to when it is instantiated
in the scene.
So let's write object, position, rotation.
We know what object we want to instantiate,
that's our Bolt prefab.
Where, on the other hand, will we find
a position which is a vector3
and a rotation, which is a quaternion
to set our object to when it is instantiated?
There is one compact package where we can find
both a position and a rotation
and that is in a game object's transform.
The transform component contains
a position as a vector3
and a rotation as a quaternion.
The transform also includes a scale
as a vector3, which we can ignore
for instantiate.
In the Inspector the quaternion
for rotation is simplified as a quaternion euler.
For more information on quaternions and
quaternion euler please see the lesson linked below.
So how do we use this to instantiate a shot?
Create a new empty game object.
Rename it Shot Spawn.
We can use this empty game object's transform
as a spawn point in our game.
We can think of this as some sort of
virtual hard point to attach our weapons to.
This spawn point should move with our player ship.
So let's drag Shot Spawn
on to our player game object
and drop it as a child.
If we open the player game object family
we can see the Shot Spawn in the Hierarchy
as a child game object.
Let's switch to the Scene view for a
good look at our player ship
and the Shot Spawn game object.
We can now position the Shot Spawn.
As it's a child of the player ship
our Shot Spawn's position will
be relative to the player ship.
We want to instantiate our shots in
front of the player ship
so let's drag the Shot Spawn out along it's
Z axis until it's in front of the ship.
Let's make this a round 1.25.
If we want to test the position
we can drag an instance of our Bolt prefab
in to the scene as a child of Shot Spawn.
Make sure the instance's transform is at origin.
This is a local value, so it will be
at origin relative to the Shot Spawn's transform.
This is where the Shot Spawn's position and
rotation will put our instances.
That's great, that feels good to me.
Now, let's make sure we delete our
test instance, we don't want to have a
shot in our scene when we start the game.
Let's return to our player controller script.
Now we need to write a few variables to hold
references to our object and transform.
Write public GameObject shot
and public GameObject shotSpawn.
Hmmm.
There may be a better way to handle Shot Spawn.
If we reference the game object to get the
position and rotation we need
we would have to write shotSpawn.transform.position
and the same for rotation.
On the other hand our variable
could use the type of transform
instead of game object.
We will still drag a reference using the game
object in the Inspector
but Unity is smart enough to find
and use the transform component on that
game object if we declare the
variable's type as transform.
So what do we want to instantiate?
Our shot.
And where do we want to instantiate it?
At the Shot Spawn position
with the Shot Spawn rotation applied.
If we left the code like this and tested it
we would create a stream of shots.
One new shot every frame.
For this game let's fire a shot
only when the player holds down a fire button.
And we will limit the fire rate as well
to a value we can set in the editor.
We do this with Input.GetButton.
Let's look up Input.GetButton in the documentation.
Conveniently the code snippet in
the documentation is all about
firing a weapon and limiting the fire rate.
Let's step through this code one line at a time.
The example starts with a game object reference,
like our Shot reference,
followed by a float value to set the fireRate,
or how long we must wait between shots.
Lastly there is a nextFire value
which is used to track when in the game
we can fire our next shot.
Let's look at the code in Update.
We only execute the instantiate code
and fire a shot if
Input.GetButton is true
and the time in the game is greater
than our nextFire value.
The Fire1 used in the Input.GetButton code
is a value preset in the input manager,
and the time in the game is represented by
Time.time.
For more information on the input manager
or the time class please see the lessons
linked below.
What is the key to this code is that
as soon as the If statement returns true
for both the Input.GetButton
and Time.time
the nextFire rate is updated,
which prevents us from firing again.
All of the code in Update will be
executed every frame.
On the very first frame Time.time
will be greater than 0
so we could fire as soon as we touch the fire button.
But let's say we don't touch the button until
1 second in to the game.
On every frame before that 1 second mark
Time.time will never be tested
against nextFire as Input.GetButton Fire1
Fire1 will be false
and this statement is tested from left to right.
When we do touch the fire button
Input.GetButton Fire1 will be true
and Time.time at 1 second
will be greater than the nextFire value of 0.
So we fire our first shot.
However, in the same frame
we increase the value of nextFire
to Time.time plus fireRate.
or 1 second plus 0.5.
NextFire is now 1.5.
If we keep our finger on the fire button
in the next few frames Input.GetButton
will be true but Time.time
won't be greater than nextFire.
We won't be able to shoot another shot
until more than 1.5 seconds in to the game.
So let's copy the sample code
from the documentation and paste it in to our script.
There is 1 typo in this C# code
snippet that we need to correct.
We only need as GameObject once in our code.
What is this as GameObject code for?
We need to remember that we are simply
instantiating a basic object with our code.
Unity does not know what type of
object this is.
We could have defined this object in a
number of different types.
To access and use this object
we need to tell Unity what type of
object it is.
So what we are saying with this line of code is
please, instantiate this basic object
as a game object.
When we instantiate an object we can take
a reference to that game object.
The instantiate function will return
or give us a reference to the object
we are instantiating.
We take that reference here with our
game object variable at the beginning of the line.
This gives us a connection to the new object
as a game object,
otherwise the new object just gets dropped
in to our scene along with all of the other
objects that we have.
Without a reference to the new object
we cannot easily find and pick this
object out of all of the others in the scene.
If we don't have a connection or a reference
to a specific object we cannot perform actions
or do things with this object.
If we take the reference to the new object
when we instantiate it we now have
access to that new object.
Now in our case we are simply
firing our shots in to the scene.
We don't need to do anything
with these shots once we have fired them.
They can take care of themselves.
We don't need a reference to the shots we fire
and we can get rid of the reference
and simply instantiate the object.
When we do we must also get rid of the
as GameObject as well.
Now let's update the sample code we've
pasted in to our script.
We want to instantiate our shot
at the Shot Spawn position
with the Shot Spawn rotation.
Next we need to update our variables
to work with this code.
We need a public float for our fireRate
and a private float for our nextFire.
Now let's save this script and return to Unity.
Click on the player game object so we can inspect it.
We need to populate the references we have
created in our Player Controller script.
Open the Prefabs folder and drag the
Bolt prefab on to Shot.
Next grab the Shot Spawn game object
from the Hierarchy and drag it on to the
Shot Spawn reference on the
player controller component.
Note that Unity was able to reference
the transform component from the
Shot Spawn game object.
Lastly we need to set our fireRate.
4 times a second sounds good and fast,
so let's use 0.25.
Now let's save and play.
And we're shooting our shots.
And as we move, because the Shot Spawn
is a child of our player ship,
we always shoot from the front of the ship,
no matter where we are in the game.
Our player can now shoot shots.
We have created a problem however
we are filling our scene with shot
game object clones, all flying off to infinity
on the Z axis.
In the next assignment we will create a boundary
to clean up any game objects
that leave the game area.