So let's set up our play field.
The play field for our game will be very simple.
We will place walls around the edges
to keep our player game object from falling off
and we will create and place a set of collectable
objects for our player to pick up.
First let's create a new game object
and rename it Walls.
This will be an organising parent game object
for our Wall objects.
Reset this game object to origin.
Now we will build our walls.
Let's start by creating a new cube
to be our first wall.
Rename this West Wall.
Now parent West Wall to our Walls game object.
Let's focus our Scene view camera
to our Wall object.
We can do this by typing the F key
while the cursor is over the Scene view
or by selecting Edit - Frame Selected.
We need to change the size of the cube to fit
one side of our play area.
Change the cube's transform scale of X, Y and Z to
.5 for thin, 2 for tall and 20.5 for long.
Now we can simply push the wall in to place
using the Translate tool
or we could enter a value in to the transform component.
In this case we can set the transform's
position X value to -10.
This places the wall neatly to the edge of our play area.
To create the next wall we could
start with another new cube,
but then we'd have to rescale this
new cube before we placed it.
Our current West Wall is already the perfect size.
So let's duplicate the West Wall game object.
Let's rename it East Wall.
To place the wall simply remove the negative sign
and it pops in to place on the east side of our game area.
Now let's duplicate the east wall
and call it North Wall.
Reset the X position so the north wall
is in the centre of the play area.
We now have two choices.
We can rotate the wall by 90 degrees.
or, as this is a cuboid,
we can rescale the wall to 20.5 in the X and 0.5 in the Z.
Now it's scaled correctly for it's orientation
as the north wall.
We can drag the wall in to place or
we can simply use the value of 10
in the transform's position Z field to place it.
Duplicate North Wall and call it South Wall,
and -10 in the Z axis pops it in to place.
Enter play mode and test.
Fantastic, the walls work fine.
Remember to test early and test often,
don't wait to test.
Let's highlight the player game object.
and set the editor to local mode and try again.
Note how in local mode we can see the transform rotate.
Let's exit play mode.
Next let's create our collectable objects
Create a new cube
and rename it PickUp.
Reset the PickUp's transform to origin.
Focus the scene view camera on the PickUp object.
The player game object is in the way.
Let's select the player game object
and deselect the checkbox
in front of the Name field.
This is the game object's active checkbox.
Deselecting it will deactivate the game object in the scene.
This will give us a clear working space for
our new PickUp object.
The cube is buried in the plane, just like in our
player's sphere was when we started this project.
The cube is also a regular shape,
1 by 1 by 1.
so let's lift it up by half a unit
and we know it's resting on the plane.
This cube will be our pickup object.
To be effective it must attract the attention
of the player.
So let's make the cube more attractive.
We will start by making it smaller
This will also give it the effect of floating
above the play area.
Both will help identify this object as special.
Not enough however. Let's tilt it over.
(45, 45, 45)  in each
of the axis of the transform's rotation.
Better but not sexy enough.
One thing I feel certainly attracts the attention of a player
and that is movement. So let's rotate the cube.
To do this we need a script.
With the PickUp object selected use the Add Component
button in the Inspector.
Create a new script called Rotator
Click Create and Add to confirm.
Organise the script by placing it in the Scripts folder
and open it for editing.
We want the cube to spin and
we want to do it with this script.
Let's remove the sample code we don't need.
We will not be using forces, so we can use update
rather than fixed update.
We have already set the transform rotation
in the transform component to
(45, 45, 45) for the X, Y and Z axis.
But these values don't change by themselves.
We want to change these values every frame
To make the cube spin we don't want to
set the transform rotation
but we want to rotate the transform.
Next type transform inside update.
Select it and hold down the control key on the pc or
the command key on the mac and type single quote.
This brings up the transform page in the documentation.
There are two main ways to effect the transform.
These are Translate and Rotate.
Translate moves the game object by it's transform.
Rotate rotates the game object by it's transform.
We will use Rotate.
So let's click on the link
and this brings up the page for Transform.Rotate.
Even though the content of the code is nearly
identical between Unity's Javascript and C#
we are using C# for this project
so let's change the language to C#.
Note again the two signatures and the
two possible overrides
One using a vector3 and the other using
three float values for X, Y and Z.
Both overrides have the optional parameter Space,
which we will leave at default for this lesson.
Again we will choose the most simple
form that only uses the vector3 for direction.
Let's return to our code.
After transform, and make sure transform is
written to begin with a lowercase t,
write .Rotate(new Vector3(15, 30, 45).
Now this action also needs to be smooth
and frame rate independent
so we need to multiply the vector3 value
by Time.deltaTime.
Save this script and return to Unity.
Test by entering play mode
and our PickUp object rotates.
Let's exit play mode.
Okay, we have the start of a working pickup object.
Next we want to place these around the game area
but before we do this we need to do
one important step.
We need to make our PickUp object in to a prefab.
So remember a prefab is an asset
that contains a template or blueprint
of a game object or game object family.
We create a prefab from an existing game
object or game object family
and once created we can use this prefab
in any scene in our current project.
With the prefab of our PickUp object
we will be able to make changes to a single
instance in our scene, or to the
prefab asset itself and all of the PickUp
objects in our game will be updated
with those changes.
So, first let's create a folder
to hold our prefabs.
We want this folder on our root or top
level of our project,
so select the Assets folder
and then choose Create Folder.
Rename this folder Prefabs.
Now drag the PickUp game object from our hierarchy
and place it in to our Prefabs folder.
When we drag an item from our hierarchy
in to our Project view we create a
new prefab asset containing a template
or blueprint of our game object or game object family.
Before we spread our collectables around the game area
we should create a new game object to
hold our PickUps and to help organise our hierarchy.
Let's create a new game object
and call it PickUps.
Check to make sure this parent game object
is at origin and drag our PickUp game object in to it.
Now we want to spread a number of these PickUp
objects around the play area.
First, make sure we have the PickUp
game object selected, not the parent.
Now let's move in to a top-down view
by clicking on the gizmo in the upper right
of our scene view.
Let's back out a little so we can see
the entire game area.
Grab the PickUp game object and it doesn't move
in the scene the way we want it to.
Note how the cube is moving in relation to it's
gizmo, which is tilted over.
What we are seeing is the game object
moving in local mode.
We really want to move the PickUp game object
aligned with the ground.
Change the editor to Global mode.
Now see how the orientation of the gizmo changes?
And now we can drag our game object around
relative to the world's global axis.
So let's lay down a few of these in the game area.
Take our first PickUp object and place it
in to the game area some place convenient.
I'm going to place mine at the top.
With the game object selected, duplicate it.
This can be done either by selecting Edit - Duplicate
or by using the hot key combination,
this is command-D on the mac
or control-D on the pc.
Now we place the second instance of the prefab.
Using the hot keys we will create a few more,
placing them around the play area.
Note that I'm moving parallel to the ground
or the X/Z plane by selecting the
X/Z plane at the centre of the gizmo.
Okay, that's 12.
Let's hit play and test.
Excellent.
These PickUp prefabs are working great.
In the next assignment we will learn how
to pick them up and count them.