The next thing we're going to jump in to is
the new UI system
and the first thing that we're going to do
is to click the 2D mode,
so in Unity 4.3 we introduced some
2D features and they're also useful
for the GUI.
So in the scene view there is a little
box here called 2D, so if you enable
that you will see that the scene view switches
to a completely flat representation
and that the gizmo in the upper right disappears.
It looks like this.
What we're going to do is create a canvas.
So the way that the new UI system works
is that everything is based off of a canvas.
So if you go to Game Object
you can go to UI and
create a Canvas.
Game Object - UI - Canvas from the top menu.
And we will rename this object
from Canvas to HUD Canvas
HUD Canvas.
Just to give you a little bit of background information
the UI system is based around
the concept of a rect transform.
So rect, short for rectangle, has a number of ways of
displaying a rectangle on the screen
and every child object, every UI element is
based off of the parent object's rect transform.
So in the case of a canvas
you'll see that in a particular mode
such as Screen Space Overlay
the rect transform's values are being
driven by the game view.
So the first thing that I'm going to do is
to select my HUD Canvas in the hierarchy
and I'm going to frame-select it
so if you hover over the scene view and press F
you will see an outline of this canvas.
so that's driven by the game view.
You can see if i drag the game view
the actual shape of that is changing.
That HUD Canvas is going to have all
of our child elements attached to it
and it's going to stay to the scale of the screen
so if you're working for different resolutions it's
going to still stay full screen.
It's driven by this canvas component.
Canvas has 3 modes
Screen Space Overlay,
which is just filling the entire screen.
Screen Space Camera,
which can have UI perspective
and World Space, which is for things that
are intrinsically within the 3D scene.
So for example you might have a speech bubble
popping up from a 3D character.
We're going to stick with Screen Space Overlay
so we don't need to worry about that.
Pixel Perfect can be used to make
sure that all of your graphic elements are
pixel perfect, but we don't need it for what we're doing here.
Graphic Raycaster we don't need to concern
ourselves with at all.
What we do want to do is to add
a component, before we do anything else,
which is a canvas group.
So what a canvas group does is allows UI elements
to have an alpha and it allows you to
toggle whether they are interactables.
So for our entire UI we don't actually
want interaction, so we don't want to put in
buttons or anything like that.
We're going to be putting in elements that would
be interactable but we can cancel them out
by on the canvas group removing that.
Also, because we use a raycast from screen space
to the quad in order to control the character
we don't want this canvas, which is going to be
effectively rendered in front of everything to
block that raycast.
On your canvas group, interactable, and block raycast
should be unchecked.
Real quick too, obviously the canvas is very big
and I just wanted to clarify it's so big because
it maps 1 pixel per unit, world unit
so that we get the highest level of fidelity in our graphics.
So if you have a graphic that is
512 pixels by 512 pixels
it's going to be drawn 512 units by 512 units.
And if you recall the capsule collider on our character
is 0.6 units wide
so 512 units is very very big.
So that's why you're seeing the canvas display
huge in here and then the level looking tiny
down in the corner, it's nothing to worry about whatsoever.
One trick that I don't want you guys to do
right now because it can lead to confusion
is that you can use layers to disable this
so all new UI elements are automatically put on
the UI layer and what you can do is
just choose Nothing and then UI
to only show the UI.
But we don't want to do that, we're just going to work it
it out as it is like that.
Okay, so the first thing we want to do is get
a HUD element in to this so we're going
to create an empty child.
There's another way of doing this, so I want to
basically give you an example of each way
of doing certain things.
We can select HUD Canvas and
from the top go Game Object and Add things.
We can go to the Create menu here, which now has
Create Empty and Empty Child as of 4.6.
But we can also right click on a game object
we want to create an empty child for.
So I'm going to right click and go to Create Empty Child.
And I'm going to rename this game object
HealthUI
Capital H, capital UI.
Now the advantage of adding a child directly
to this rather than making it separately
and adding it is that because we selected
that HUD Canvas first Unity
knows that we're trying to add another UI element
so instead of the standard transform component
that it adds to any new game object
it's adding a rect transform.
And you can see that you have a slightly different
looking component than you're used to.
Just to draw your attention to something else
to do with UI.
This is our new empty game object, this square in the middle.
We also have up at the top a brand new
tool, the fifth one there,
which is our Rect tool.
And you can use that to scale
things, you can use it rotate,
and you'll also notice that when you drag these things around
we have snapping
and we have these mysterious looking
triangles in the centre.
Those are our anchor points and
they're a very powerful way to
position your different UI elements
and we're going to show off how you use
some of those throughout the day.
The first thing we want to do is to
setup our Health UI in the
lower left of the screen.
There's a button which may not immediately
appear to be a button, on the rect transform.
It's called the Anchor Presets button.
And what it does is give you all these
presets and a couple of different modes
using Alt and Shift
in order to be able to lay things out.
So the rect transform's position is based
off a number of different factors and when you're in
different modes and have your position
in different places the actual
properties that you're getting, the position,
X, Y, X, the width and height,
will be different depending on how things are anchored
i.e. where those particular anchors are positioned.
So when they're all positioned together
so for example if I move this
and move my anchor to the top right
then my position is relative to
where those anchors are.
So as I drag my canvas in
you can see that that stays with the righthand edge.
So it's all based around this thing
but we're going to use some of the presets for this
to make it a little simpler.
What I want you to do is with the rect
transform button open,
hopefully you can see this menu,
we're going to, first off we're going to hold Alt
because Alt is also going to set the position
whilst moving the anchors for us
and we're also going to hold Shift.
And then we're going to click on the
lower left preset.
So you can see they've got titles here.
We've got Bottom and Left.
We're going to click there with Alt and Shift.
So you see if I hold Alt it moves the box.
If I hold Shift it highlights the blue
circle, which is our pivot.
And we click there.
If you have trouble remembering that it also says it
right at the top, Shift sets the pivot,
Alt sets the position.
So then what you should see is that
in you scene view that
you have something in the lower left,
it looks like this.
Then I'm going to go ahead and set the
width to 75
and I'm going to set the height to 60.
So the next thing I'm going to do is add those
child elements, this heart icon and the slider.
I'm going to again want to add something
directly as a child, so I'm going to right click
HealthUI this time, go to UI
and choose Image.
So UI Image is exactly what it sounds like.
It's any way to get a texture or sprite
as we call it in imported form
in to your UI layout.
Once we've added this rename it
from Image to Heart.
Then in the rect transform
we are going to set the X
and Y positions, if they're not already, to 0,
and I'm going to set my width and height
to 30.
What you should see is a white
square in the lower left of your screens.
You should have your
HealthUI parent object and you should have your
Heart, which is a white square right now.
So when you add an image in the new system
until you give it a source image it has
a white background, so it falls back to using
it's colour property.
So that's just a really handy way to see
where the outline of the thing's going to be and if
you didn't want to see it at all you can always turn down
the alpha value, the opacity of the image.
But we do have an image for it, so we are going to,
on the image component,
use the circle select to look in to our Assets
and choose Heart.
Click the circle select to the right of Source Image
and choose Heart from the assets.
I'm sure you all are noticing
that the heart and the white box and everything are actually
appearing in the lower left hand corner
in your game view,
so it's very easy to set things up because
you can see what it will look like in the final project.
The next thing we're going to do is add in
a slider for our UI.
So we have the heart and next to it we want to have
the amount of health displayed to the user.
I'm going to reselect my HealthUI
because I want to create a child of that.
I'm going to right click,
do the same again, UI
and this time we're going to choose Slider.
And we're going to rename this first of all
to HealthSlider.
F2 on PC, Return on Mac.
HealthSlider, capital H and S.
Then I'm going to set the X position
in the rect transform to 95
ensuring that Y and Z are 0.
So what this is effectively is a slider,
so you can use this for a number of different things,
if you have settings in a game,
you might want people to drag a slider and set something.
We're using it slightly differently, we're using it in
a non-interactable manner.
And basically we don't need to worry about the handle.
So what I want you guys to do
is to open up HealthSlider to see the
child object's that are standard within a slider.
You'll see that we have Fill Area and Handle Slide Area.
The Fill Area is in charge of the background
and the fill itself.
So the main space that you've got to fill
and what's going to be behind it.
We don't want the Handle Slide Area at all
so we're going to remove that from the hierarchy.
Leaving the Fill Area select Handle Slide Area
and to delete something, if you're on a PC, delete key,
on Mac Command-Backspace
will remove it from the hierarchy.
You should then lose the handle in the game view
and scene view and just be left with the actual
slider space itself.
So we want to setup what this actually does.
The first thing we're going to do is look at our
slider component.
So the slider component is basically all of the different
rules about what it's going to do.
It has an interactable checkbox, we know that we don't
want to actually have any interaction here
but because we've placed this under the canvas
which itself isn't interactable
we don't need to worry about the sub-assets
having interactable checkboxes.
We don't need to go through and check all of those,
the canvas being the parent is handling
all of that for us.
Because it is something that
you can interact with as standard we have a transition.
We don't want any of that either so we're going to
select Transition - None.
Then we want the Max value of this
to be equal to the Starting Health effectively,
so I'm going to set the max value to 100.
Then I'm going to change the value also to 100.
If you look at the game view when I adjusted
the slider you can see that that is
the value that we're getting.
So when I set that to 100 I know that
I can write some scripting that addresses this
slider and decreases that each time we
get hurt by an enemy.
Then what we're going to do is to have
some kind of visual feedback
when you do actually get hurt.
Because that slider in the lower left is kind of small
we want to have the screen flash
like it would in a real game
every time you get hurt.
So we can do that using a UI image as well,
So what we're going to do is to go back
to our HealthUI.
Reselect HealthUI.
Right click, this time I'm going to add
another UI image.
We're going to rename this DamageImage.
And because it's a brand new image
that's just kind of sat on the lower left right now
we want this to be over the entire screen
so the entire screen can kind of flash red
each time you get hurt.
So there's a very quick way with the anchor presets
yet again to stretch this over the entire screen.
So here's what I want you guys to do.
Is to select DamageImage, drag it up
and drop it on to HUDCanvas,
which will make it a child of HUDCanvas instead.
Then we can collapse HealthUI.
Once you have made it a child of HUDCanvas
you can then go ahead and select
and then Alt-click on the lower right anchor preset
as I'm showing you right now.
Alt-click there, and you should have then
white covering your entire canvas.
And then the final thing we need to do is
set the alpha to 0 for this.
So we're going to worry about the colour in our
scripting later so don't worry about that now.
But to set the alpha to 0 we just click
the colour block and then drag the
A for alpha down to 0.
Obviously if you have done that please do
save your scene, very important