So far we have a game
where we can shoot a singular enemy
and you can be killed by
that very same enemy.
But currently
there is no way to score points.
So we want to add more to our UI
and we want to add the ability to
score points and represent that inside
our UI as well.
Okay, so, what I want you guys to do
is to take a look back at your hierarchy
and we are going to look at the HUD Canvas.
So the HUD Canvas is our
UI canvas, as you remember earlier we placed
in the Health UI which gives us the slider for our health
and the little heart icon
as well as the damage image.
But this time we are going to create a score text.
So what I'm going to do very quickly is just a the top
of the scene view click the 2D button
to switch back to 2D mode and I'm just
going to zoom right out
or what I can do is double click my HUD Canvas
to frame it and then zoom back in.
What I'm doing is selecting my
rect tool because whenever I work on
UI stuff I want that 5th tool,.
Show us the 2D button really quick while you're zoomed in.
There it is, 2D button.
Once we're in 2D mode we can then
go ahead and create some more UI
so this time we're going to make a
child object of the HUD Canvas.
Therefore I'm going to right click it
go to UI and Text.
So these UI things are basically a
collection of ready-made objects that
you can start working with.
All of the things that are in the UI system,
much like the rest of Unity,
are actually components, so what we're really doing
is creating a new game object
with a text component attached to it.
By default when you make a new text component
you made something that is default Arial text
and it is in grey so that it will
work neutrally on light or dark backgrounds.
So we're going to rename this
The first thing we're going to do is call Text
ScoreText, so capital S and T.
So rename Text to ScoreText.
Then what I'm going to do is to
re-anchor this to the top centre of the screen.
So if you remember we learnt about
rect transform's anchor presets.
And the way that we're going to do that is just
to set the anchor rather than all of it
to the top centre.
So it's this preset here.
We don't need to Alt, we don't need to Shift,
we just need to click that singularly.
And what that does is moves our anchors
to the top, so you can see our
little flower pattern thing is now
sat at the top.
And from there we can then adjust
the positions as appropriate.
You'll now noticed that because I've moved those anchors
the Y position is -220, so the centre of the game view
is -220 pixels or units from the top.
So now I can say the Y position is going to be -55
and I'll make sure that my X is also on 0.
That moves the text in relation to the anchor.
Yeah, so if I set that to 0
you can see that the pivot is 0.5, 0.5, in the centre.
But if I drag this down
you can see that I'm moving it a - value.
So I'll put that around -55.
The next thing we're going to do is setup the width,
I'll set that to 300.
And I'm going to set the heigh to 50.
And I'll set the color to white.
so in the text component you have all the controls
for how the text displays
and I'm going to drag in the color picker
so that my color for the text is white.
Then because we don't want it to just be Arial
and very small we're going to set the font.
And we're going to use the circle select and
choose LuckiestGuy, so that's a font
that we've included in this.
If you're not used to doing any kind of UI
work in Unity, because Unity is authoring another game
or application effectively
you need to include that font within your project.
So we have the truetype file for LuckiestGuy within that.
So we have the licence for it and we have the font itself.
That means that when we export it will have
the font and use it, it doesn't work like
word processors or Photoshop, it won't
just be able to pick from your library, you
have to create a copy of the truetype within your project.
So our score text has that font
and we're going to set the font size to 50.
And we're going to use the alignment under paragraph
to centre and middle.
So centre and middle and font size to 50.
And you should see that we have new text written in there.
Obviously we don't want it to say new text,
we want to see what our actual score will look like.
So in the Text field I'm going to type
in Score: 0.
That's the default that it's going to look like
when we start the game.
Also important to note that we don't have to
set the text to say Score: 0.
Our script is actually going to
write what it is that text should be
however it's really hard to tell what
this is going to look like when we're playing our
game without putting some value in there.
So you might say later 'why did we set that text
when the script is already doing it?'.
The reason is so that we can visually see
'okay, that looks pretty good'
now let's go ahead and apply our scripts and do the rest.
So it's just a placeholder.
Now that we've done this I'm going to save my scene.
So File - Save.
And the next thing I'm going to do is put a
slight drop shadow, so there are some
effects that come with the UI system and
we can add them as a separate component.
We can keep the ScoreText selected,
go to Add Component and just type the word Shadow
and it will immediately find that component
and you can hit Return.
That will just give you a slight drop shadow.
I'm going to make it a bit more obvious
by changing the Effect Distance to 2, -2 in the X and Y axis.
It's also important to keep that
Use Graphic Alpha checked,
otherwise if you change the alpha
of the text the shadow won't also change.
What you'll notice about this is if I change the
alpha of the text itself the shadow
underneath is also fading out.
Whereas if it's not checked
we can fade this and then the shadow
will get left behind which is not desirable.
And then we need something to set
the score, something to be managing
the score, updating the text component's
text value with Score 10, Score 20,
whatever happens in the game.
And the way that we're going to do this is
by adding a Manager script.
So what I'd like you to do is look in
the Scripts - Managers folder
and you will find out Score Manager.
We're going to drag and drop this on to the
ScoreText game object
Then once you've applied it you should see
it at the bottom of the list of components
right underneath the shadow
and we can double click to open that up.
So at the start we again have our public variables.
You'll notice there's a new keyword there
Static.
So a static variable doesn't belong to the instance
of the class it belongs to the class itself.
So let me explain.
Whenever we're dragging on EnemyHealth
or PlayerHealth or PlayerMovement on to an object
we're creating an instance of that class
and applying it to the game object,
so they are all instances of a class.
And so all of the variables,
they're instance variables,
each enemy has it's own health,
each player has it's own speed, etcetera.
Static variables do not belong to an instance,
they belong to the class itself.
So what that means is,
in order to reference the score there
we don't need to go ScoreManager variable
GetComponent ScoreManager then use it, we just say
ScoreManager type . score.
So we don't need to create a variable to use it
we're just going to use it through the type itself.
So it only effectively exists in one place
we're not going to address a bunch of instances where
this exists, we're changing it in 1 place.
We could still have multiple
instance of ScoreManager,
we could drag multiple ones on to
a game object, on to different game objects, doesn't matter.
We're not going to, because that would break everything.
But if we did all of them would share the same score.
because it belongs to the type
not to the instance.
So the next thing is we need a reference to our Text component.
In awake we're going to setup that reference
to the text component.
Then we need to reset the score
because if we die we want
the game to reset, so,
we need to set the score back to 0.
And in our update function
what we're doing there, the text.text is
we're changing the text property
of the text component.
Okay, so the text component that we have
that string that we said Score: 0,
that was the Score text,
that was the text property of the component.
So what we're doing is we're setting that
to a completely new string, we're not changing that,
we're just setting it completely afresh.
We're changing it to Score:
and then that number will be the score.
So very simply that's our ScoreManager and
if you happen to save it it'll ask you to convert
the line endings, it's no big deal.
Okay, we'll need to continue scoring points
and I'm going to select my
Zombunny in the hierarchy
and locate the EnemyHealth script.
And we're going to open the EnemyHealth script.
and have a look down at the very bottom
at the StartSinging function.
James mentioned the public static
integer score earlier,
he promised you very kindly that you could
indeed say the name of
the class, ScoreManager.score,
so without saying GetComponent
or create an instance of the script, assign to this part of the script
we can very simply just say ScoreManager.score.
So we're going to re-enable that by deleting
the 2 // comments.
And what we're doing there is adding to it
the value of ScoreValue.
So scoreValue within this particular script is
a public variable that we can change.
This enemy has a value of 10 that when you kill it you get 10 points.
This way we can apply this
EnemyHealth script to different enemies
and have different score values.
So if you wanted to make the
killing the elephant worth a lot then you could
change that value, you don't need to go in to the
script and change it, it's a public value
so it appears in the inspector.
I just want to make a quick point about static variables.
So you know it's a lot easier to do it with static there,
we didn't have to create an instance variable,
we didn't have to assign it in awake
and then use it, we just used it just like that.
So why don't we use it for everything like that?
That would be so much easier?
It's because we have multiple enemies
and if we wanted multiple players then
we'd have more of those as well.
So if we wanted to change the health
of one player all of the player's health would change.
So we can't do it most of the time.
It's just very specific circumstances
where you'd only have one score
so we can make that static
to make it easier for ourselves.
So we're going to save this, it's going to ask you
to convert line endings, just choose Convert.
This project was made on PC and then
moved between PC and Mac so the files
get confused but it's no big deal.
So we should now go ahead and try it out.
So if you save your scene and press play
at the top of the interface.
There we go, 10 points for a Zombunny.
A very important point to make right now about prefabs
is that they are incredibly useful when you want to
spawn more than one object.
So some people might use if for rockets in a game
and you might use it for enemy spawning in a game.
You can use it for really anything you want to
But we want to use that for our enemies,
there's going to be 3 types of enemy,
and you guys have gone and created that first enemy.
What we don't want is just the enemy to be
sat next to the player when the game starts.
So what we need to do is to save him as a prefab.
So everybody make sure you've stopped play,
so play is no longer on, it should be black at the top.
No more blue buttons.
What we're going to do is to select our
Prefabs folder in the project
and then grab the Zombunny in the hierarchy
and drag and drop it in to the project panel
either in the empty space or drop it on
to the Prefabs folder.
Both of those will create the same effect,
you will get a Zombunny prefab,
which looks like this.
And you will have all of the same settings
that you had on the version that's in the scene.
So that version in the scene now belongs
to that prefab parent.
And even if we delete the version in
the scene, in the hierarchy,
then the version in the project is saved,
and that's very crucial.
Everybody check that you've got your Zombunny
in the project, it's very important.
Then in the hierarchy we want to get rid of it,
so I'm going to select it there and
on Mac Command Backspace,
on PC just the delete key.
Remove it from the scene.
And then save your scene.
Switch off 2D mode and double click the
player to zoom back in to the action
so you can see the player.
Okay, so that is the end of phase 8.