Phase number 10 of 10.
We are going to create our game over state.
We are able to shoot enemies
and enemies are able to attack us
but we currently want to show the player when
the game has ended, apart from having you fall over.
So we're going to do that by
creating a bunch of other UI elements.
The first thing I'm going to do is click
on the 2D mode of the scene view
and then I'm going to double click
my HUD Canvas to frame selected as before.
Remember that that is shortcut F if you wanted to do that
instead you can click on any object and
F to frame it, I'm just zooming in to fill my screen.
And I'm going to right click that HUD canvas
and go to UI
and Image.
We're going to create an image that
stretches over the entire HUD Canvas,
the entire screen,
and we are going to fade it out.
Rename this from Image to ScreenFader.
ScreenFader, capital S and F.
Then in the rect transform
anchor presets click the button
and we're going to Alt-click
the lower right preset,
which is stretch in both dimensions.
That will stretch it over the entirety
of the canvas, and currently because
it is white it will just block everything out.
Then what we're going to do is in our Image script
I'm going to click on the color block
and I'm going to pick a shade of light blue,
something like this.
So we're not going to pick a shade of black,
we want to see our drop shadow on our score
and our game over, I'm going to pick a light blue.
Then we need to add our game over message.
So yet again reselect the HUD Canvas,
right click, UI Text.
As before it's going to create it
right in the centre of that.
We're going to rename thisGameOverText.
Capital G, O and T.
Then what we're going to do is make sure that it's
centred perfectly, so we're going to Alt-click
the centre preset, it should be centred anyway
but we're just making sure.
Then I'm going to change my width to 300
and a height of 50.
Then we're going to write in an actual message.
In the Text component we're going to say
Game Over.
Then we're going to say the font
is also our existing font, Luckiest Guy.
So circle select to pick the font.
And the font size, we're going to go with 50.
The alignments are going to be
centre and middle, under Paragraph.
And I'm going to scroll down and choose
white from the color picker, just like before.
And as before we need a drop shadow
so we're going to Add Component, so I'll type in
S-H-A, press Return to add the Shadow script.
Yet again I'm going to put in 2
and -2 just to accentuate the effect a little bit.
Then, very importantly we need to reorder
how these are arranged.
This is a really important thing to learn about the new UI system.
What you may have noticed as of Unity 4.5
and now in Unity 4.6
the hierarchy doesn't show in A to Z order.
You'll notice that things that are H is below a Z.
The reason for that is the UI
system needs to use the hierarchy
to order it's render order.
The way that this works, if you're used to Photoshop,
you have to think backwards.
The lower most child object
is rendered in front of everything else.
So currently we have
DamageImage at the bottom followed by
HealthUI rendered on top of that,
followed by ScoreText, ScreenFader then GameOverText.
However, we don't want it in that order.
We want our HealthUI to be at the bottom
so that when we fade in this blue screen
it obscures or renders in front of that HealthUI.
You don't need to know that you had no health
left when you died because that's pretty obvious,
that's why you died.
So we're going to drag and drop these to reorder.
You need to be careful with this and
just watch me do it first because it can be a bit clunky.
What I want you to do is just watch for a second.
What I'm going to do is move my healthUI
to above, so I don't want to
accidentally drop on to something else, like this,
I want to drop it so that it has the line
and the small circle and drop it above.
I'll slowly get these in to the right order.
With the ScreenFader, that needs to be the
third thing, so I'll drag that between these two
so the line shows up.
And then GameOverText, and ScoreText at the end.
The HealthUI will render first,
and the DamageImage is next.
That's intermittently happening so it doesn't matter too much.
The ScreenFader needs to obscure both
of those by fading in and we'll finish
the game with GameOverText and ScoreText
still showing on top of that blue screen.
So we've sorted that render order.
Just to remind you of the render order,
this is what it is;
Health UI first, then DamageImage,
ScreenFader, GameOverText,
going own the list so that the render order
ends with ScoreText.
The ScreenFader hierarchy by default needs to be
transparent, we don't want to start the game
with this blue obscuring everything.
I'm just going to save my scene.
And then with my ScreenFader
reselected in the hierarchy I'm going to
click on the color block
and you'll see sliders at the bottom
RGB, Red, Green, Blue
and A for Alpha.
So that's how you do transparent things,
you drag the Alpha to 0.
Then the same thing for the GameOverText.
Select GameOverText and in
the Color for the text component, open the block,
set the Alpha to 0.
Drag the slider down to 0.
So at the start of the game these are
there and we're going to use animation in just a second
to animate those in, make them look cool,
and we're going to create a state machine for
when the game ends.
Because we previously used
pre-animated FPX files
they came with an animator component
already attached to them.
We just needed to create the controller,
the state machine, to apply to it.
But you can use the animator with anything.
A lot of people get confused because
when we added the new animation system
it has a nickname, which is MeshAnim.
And a lot of people think that that is only
useable for character animation.
It's not true at all, you can animate
anything you want to, it's just a
state machine you can apply animation clips to.
So we're going to do exactly that with our UI right now.
Even the term animation is a bit misleading because
it makes you think that some form of motion is involved
and in fact animation in this case
can literally be the changing of anything,
positional information such as movement but also
colors, alphas, values, turning things on and off.
Literally anything you want.
So you can animate any public property of
any component on any game object in Unity.
We're going to do that with the UI
right now to give you an example of that.
Because when we start adding
animation Unity's going to automatically
assign the animator, I.E. the holder for state machine.
We need to select the right object, so we're going to choose
the HUD Canvas as the one we're going to
start adding animation to.
That way when we add one clip
we'll be able to address any property of
any of the child objects.
That's really important.
With the HUD Canvas selected
I want you to go to Window
Animation.
Window - Animation, not the animator,
the actual timeline, it should look like this.
And I'm going to drag this tab and
dock it by the game view,
because when you're animating you're mostly going to look
at the scene view and you don't really need to worry
about the game view so I'm going to dock that in the same place.
Then if I don't already have a
clip made as soon as I add a curve,
adding curves basically means add
property that I want to animate of
anything that's attached to the game object
currently selected.
I click Add Curve and you need to
decide 'whoa, you don't have an animation yet'.
So it pops up a Create New Animation box.
Because we've made that animation folder before
we started I'm going to select that as the
place to put it
and I'm going to name my new clip
GameOverClip.
Like that. Press Save.
So now you'll see that the
animation window is in Record Mode,
the Record Mode button is highlighted
and it's asking us which property
we'd like to animate.
It's worth noting that it is in fact
in record mode so anything you do in the scene view
or the inspector is going to get recorded.
And you need to be careful exactly the things you touch.
A really quick and easy way to know if you're in record mode
is you see the player icons at the top are red?
That means you are in record mode.
Which means anything you're doing right now is being recorded.
If you change stuff it's going to think you intended
for that to be part of the animation.
There's a couple of different ways to work with this window.
We're going to work in a very specific way,
but there's a more freestyle way where you can
move the playhead along, change a property
and then it's going to get recorded straight in to your animation.
We'll do a little bit of that and we'll do
a bit of filling it in manually.
Like I said adding curve is choosing
a property that you want to animate.
The list here shows me first of all
the components attached to the game object we are animating.
So there's a rect transform, there's a canvas,
there's the graphic raycast of the canvas group,
and now it's added also an animator component because
we're going to drive this with a state machine
Unity knows that's the way it needs to work so it's added it for us.
It also very helpfully created
an animator controller asset for it
and assigned it for us as well.
So now we also get
the child objects, so all of these things that are attached
to HUD Canvas are also animatable.
So what we're going to do is add
a number of properties that we want to animate.
The first one we want to animate is the GameOverText.
We want to make that fade in.
So if you expand GameOverText
and then expand the text component
and click the + icon for color,
you can see Color here,
click the + icon and you will get
some keyframes added in at 0 and at 1 second.
And you also get
the properties of that particular thing.
So next I'm going to add another curve.
I'm going to go to GameOverText Rect Transform
and Scale.
Add a property for that.
Then ScreenFader - Image - Color,
so these are all things we want to animate.
Remember we're animating in the alpha of the ScreenFader.
We're going to animate the fading of the
word Game Over on the text.
And we're also going to scale it,
we're going to make it bounce when it comes in,
so we're going to use Scale for that.
Finally ScoreText, we're just going to shrink
down a little bit when the game is over,
we're going to add one more curve,
ScoreText - Rect Transform - Scale.
And the last thing I'm going to do
is to select the top most keyframe of
the end keyframes.
So what you can see is there's an empty row
in your list of curves.
Now what that does is it allows you to
grab all of them that are in line.
So I can click on my top keyframe, here,
I can drag this back to frame 30 and let go.
That will shorten the entire animation.
So I'm grabbing this top one and it's pulling
all of the end keyframes for my animation
to frame 30.
So now we're going to actually start animating.
When you move your mouse over
this timeline here where I'm moving my mouse now,
you can drag around and you'll see the red line
and that's the playhead moving around.
I'm going to move to frame 20.
You can see here that the number that you're
currently on is represented.
So if I want to move to frame 20 I can drag
or I can type in here frame 20.
And then I want to create a keyframe
for the GameOverText Scale.
So I'm going to drag this divider so that I can see
the end of that property.
So the line between the list of curves
and the timeline itself can be dragged
to expand it.
GameOverText Rect Transform Scale is the first one.
I select the property so it's highlighted in blue,
and I press K to make a new keyframe,
or I can use this button here,
to add a keyframe as well.
You can also just double click in that row.
Okay, so, once I've done that
I can move to frame 0
and expand this.
And what you'll see is that I've got 1, 1, 1.
So when we start off the scale is all at 1.
But we want it to increase
from 0 scale and bounce up
and then shrink back down.
So drag the playhead back to 0.
Then I'm going to enter in 0, 0, 0,
in the Scale property, so if you expand
GameOverText Rect Transform Scale
you can click on those boxes and type in 0
and hit return.
What you'll notice if you then drag
the playhead is that that rect transform is increasing.
We haven't animated the alpha yet but you can
see the rect of the box is popping up
as I drag over those.
What I want you to notice as well is that
we can also address this
using the inspector.
So the GameOverText Rect Transform Scale,
with that selected I could also use the inspector
so when we're in record mode anything
that's setup for animation, anything we've
added as a curve in the list
is highlighted in red.
So you can see that change as I drag in the inspector.
The next thing we're going to do is go to that
frame 20 where we've added that new keyframe.
And because we're in record mode I can
go to the inspector and type 1.2 for all axis.
1.2 for the scale of all of those.
So where it's red and says 1,
replace that with 1.2.
What that's doing, if I drag now,
is it's popping up and then bouncing back down.
So at frame 20 it's a scale of 1.2
and then we know that it's a scale of 1 at the end.
Move the playhead to frame 20,
set the Scale to 1.2,
and then you should see that it's popping up.
Then to finish this off we're moving
our playhead to frame 30.
Again, please make sure you are on that frame,
so frame 30 is represented in this box.
And then we need to just set a couple of other properties.
So GameOverText - Text Colour.
We need the Alpha to be 1.
So I can expand that
and set the Alpha to 1 so I know that it's going to
increase and become fully visible by frame 30.
Then I'm going to close it back down
and with the ScreenFader I want
that to fade up to 1 as well
so I'm going to set the Color.A property to 1,
so the color alpha to 1.
As soon as I do it I see that the blue appears,
so that's correct.
And finally ScoreText
at the end should be a scale of 0.8
So I'm going to set those in, 0.8.
Basically we're just shrinking that down
so it makes Game Over more prominent.
We don't want them to be the same size, we just scale one down
as the GameOverText bounces up.
If you've done those correctly, as you scrub over
it should be doing something like this.
ScoreText is going down, the blue is fading up,
Game Over is bouncing in and becoming more visible.
Whilst HealthUI is hiding
or disappearing behind the ScreenFader.
What we should have is our clip
and what you'll notices is that if we press play
in the animation view it's constantly looping.
We don't want that to happen.
But before we address that what we're going to
do is to move all of our keyframes to
further on in the timeline, because we don't want
this to happen as soon as the player dies
because we won't get to see the PlayerDeath animation
or the enemies changing to Idle or anything like that.
So you can zoom in the animation view.
Use that if this next part proves difficult
you can use the scroll wheel,
if you're on a Mac you can use the 2 finger zoom.
But what I'm going to do
is to drag a box over all of my keyframes.
Then drag all of them so that
the first keyframe is on
1 second 30 frames, or 90 frames in total.
So move it like that, that way it's going to stop playing,
you'll see the other animations in the game
and then this GameOver sequence is going to pop in.
And finally disable record mode.
So switch off that record button.
Like I said, animation clips will loop.
So the default in Unity is for looping animation.
With something like this you don't want it to loop.
And the way that you address that is a
little bit hidden away, it's not ideal
but it's attached to the clip.
We don't want this to loop so what I'd like
you to do is to go to the Animation folder
in the Assets.
And select the GameOverClip that we just made.
So that clip that we just made,
the default at the top there is Loop Time.
Uncheck Loop Time at the top
of the inspector.
Then reselect the HUD Canvas
and you'll notice that Unity has added
like I mentioned before, the animator component
and it's created a HUD Canvas
Animator Controller.
It names it after the game object
that you started animating basically,
that's why it's the same name.
So I can double click that asset to open it
in the animator window of the state machine.
And that's exactly what we need to do.
So double click HUD Canvas,
the animator controller no the game object,
to open it in the animator window.
So by default it puts it in as a new state
and it puts that clip in to that state
as the default one to play and it's just going to loop it.
We've stopped it looping by unchecking Loop Time
but we also don't want it to play straight away.
So we're going to right click
Create State - Empty.
So we'll have a new grey state.
This state doesn't have any animation clips
assigned to it so it effectively does nothing at all.
Here's the problem that we're solving.
As soon as I press play
it's game over. You want people to have a bit more
of a game-based experienced.
So what we'll do is to solve that
by stopping this being played by the
animator straight away.
We've made a new empty state
and we don't have any motion,
so usually when you see a state it has
an animation clip in the motion field.
We don't want that there.
If we really wanted to we could rename it
Empty but we don't need to at all.
But we do want that to be the default
so we're going to right click on our new state
or our empty state, and choose Set As Default.
Then we're going to create a transition
Make Transition to GameOverClip State.
And we're going to select that transition
and you'll see that there's a condition called
Exit Time, but we don't want that.
We want to have an actual trigger
to make this happen.
In our parameters we're going to
create a new trigger
and we're going to name this
parameter GameOver.
Capital G and O.
Remember are being addressed
by a script so it's very important that you get
that naming correct, capital G, capital O.
We need to then set this condition
so make sure the transition is highlighted in blue
like this
and set the condition to GameOver.
So as soon as that trigger is called from a script
it will fire us in to that state.
Then finally
we're going to select our HUD Canvas
in the hierarchy and we're going
go to the Scripts - Managers folder
and we're going to drag and drop GameOverManager
on to HUD Canvas .
So in Scripts - Managers folder in the project find
GameOverManager, drop it on to HUD Canvas.
Then we're going to double click this to open it.
As always we're going to start with our
public variables a the top of the script.
We first need a reference to the player's health
obviously the game ends when the player
has run out of health, we need to know when that is.
Next we have a public float
which is the restartDelay, so that's how long it's going
to take once the player has died
before we restart.
Next we have our private variables,
We're got an animator reference,
obviously because we need to set the
animator's trigger parameter.
And a timer for that restartDelay.
So in our awake function
we're going to setup the reference as we have done before
using getComponent.
And then in update
we're going to check if the player has
run out of health, if he's got less than
or equal to 0 health.
So if he has he's dead.
So we're going to set the animator trigger parameter
to GameOver.
We'll set that and it'll trigger that animation.
We're then going to start the restart timer
and we're going to start counting up that timer.
Once that exceeds the restart delay,
so when the restart timer is`
increased enough that it is greater than 5 seconds then
we're going to call application.loadLevel.
So that's just going to reload
the scene because we've parsed in the loaded level.
So usually you can write in a string, you might
say level 01
if you add it to the build settings
but if you're reloading the same scene you can use shortcuts
called LoadedLevel which is the one that's there.
It's a very simple script, just a way to
count up to a particular point
if you've run out of health whilst also
triggering the animation of GameOver
to appear on the screen.
Going back to Unity, we are very finally
going to select our HUD Canvas
and you'll notice that the GameOver Manager
needs to know about PlayerHealth.
So we need to assign the player
to that public property PlayerHealth.
With my HUD Canvas selected I'm going to drag
Player and drop it on to PlayerHealth
so it's got a reference to that, it can find out
our health and therefore when we have died.
Select the background music
and do Play On Awake.
Finally save your scene,
pat yourselves on the back and press play
to shoot some zombie toys.
It'll probably sound like this.
I'm going to turn that down a bit.