The next thing we're going to do is look in to
player health, so obviously we just created a slider
to represent the health,
we now want to actually implement that.
So we have this HealthUI
and the next component to this game
that we want to have is we want to
have the player have health
that is able to be taken away and is able to
also interact with our UI that we just created.
We also want to have the enemy have
the ability to attack the player and thus
take that health away.
And then from there we're going to reverse the roles,
we're going to give the enemy some health and give the player
the ability to take that health away.
What we're going to do to start is we're going to go
to the Scripts folder and we're going to
locate the Player folder and
we should find a script called PlayerHealth.
So we're going to take that and we're going to click
and drag that on to the Player game object
in our hierarchy.
So we will drop there and if we click on the player,
we scroll down and we should see
Player Health Script as a component.
Also we are currently still in this
view where we're really zoomed out and we're
focused on the canvas and all that stuff
so why don't we take a second, we'll come out of 2D
view here again by clicking on the 2D button
right there, bringing us out of that 2D mode
and then if we want to get to the player quickly
we can just double click on the player's name in the hierarchy
it'll zoom us right in there.
It just brings us back to where we were previously
We now have the PlayerHealth script on the player
so we're going to open it up and take a look at it
before we do be sure to save your scene.
And let's go ahead and pop this open.
Alright, player health.
So we start off with our PlayerHealth with a whole
bunch of variables so let's just step through and
see what each of these are.
So the first variable here is our startingHealth,
which is a public integer which dictates
how much health the player has
when the level first starts.
Next we have an integer for currentHealth
which is how much health a player will have
after they've been damaged or just at any given point in the game.
We have this healthSlider which
is a slider game object
which is the reference to that slider UI element
that we created earlier.
Now a good note right here, we're accessing Slider,
which is the new UI.
In order to access this we need to
include using UnityEngine.uI.
If you don't have that line of code at the top
using UnityEngine.uI
you're not going to be able to use text, images, sliders
any of the new UI components.
So just keep in mind you have to have that.
After the slider we then have a
public Image damageImage,
which is again a reference to that damage image
item we created.
We have an audio which is our death clip.
So unlike our hurt clip the death clip
is going to be what's called a one-shot audio
where we basically are saying we're not going to play
the hurt sound any more, this is the sound the player makes
when the player loses the game.
We have a public float flashSpeed which is how
quickly the damaged image
flashes up on the screen.
And then we have flashColour which we have
set to (1f, 0f, 0f, 0.1f) which means
completely red and a tenth
of the way completely opaque.
So it's mostly transparent and red.
Next we have some private variables, the first
is animator anim which again a reference
to our animator components.
We have a reference to our audio sources which
we call payerAudio.
We have a reference to the playerMovement scripts
So this is the first time we've seen this.
We've created a reference to another script
that we've already written.
We all remember writing PlayerMovement earlier today
so now we are actually getting a reference to that
script that is on the Player
so that we can prevent the player from
running around once the player is dead.
We have to have a reference to it to do that so
you're seeing some script interactivity there.
We have 2 boolean values, one is isDead,
which will determine whether or not the player is dead.
And the other is damaged, which will allow us
to know whether or not the player has taken damage.
The awake function here is going to be fairly similar
to what we've seen before, we're starting
by getting a reference component to
our animator, we're then getting a
reference to our audio source
playerAudio = GetComponent
This is slightly new, so here we're doing
playerMovement = GetComponent
And you'll see to get the component of the script
we've created we just use the name of that script.
Script is called PlayerMovement, I want to reference to it
so I GetComponent .
Again we have some comments in our code.
We'll revisit this script and re-enable that later.
And then we're going to say our
currentHealth is equal to our startingHealth
You'll recall awake gets called right
at the beginning when the game first starts up
so we're just going to set out currentHealth to it's max
value right there.
Update method, our update method's really simple.
Update is simply concerning itself with
whether or not we are flashing that
red damaged image, right.
And so basically what this function is saying
is 'hey, if we are damaged,
if damage has been taken, what we are going to do is
we are going to set this image
to our flashColour',
which you'll recall is red with a
10% opacity, so that's going to happen
immediately, it's going to flash this red.
Otherwise, if we're not damaged,
what we're concerned with is fading
the damaged image away, so it flashes red
and then we're going to fade it back to transparent.
And we do that again using Lerp.
Before we used Vector3.Lerp
with the player's movement, so now  what we're doing is
we're doing a Color.Lerp,
which is the exact same concept,
we're moving from one to another,
but instead of vector3s we're doing color.
So we're doing Color.Lerp and we're
parsing in the current color
of our damaged image and we're
parsing the color that we would like,
which is completely clear, completely invisible,
and then we have our flashSpeed
times Time.DeltaTime.
Very much like the smoothing that we had on
the camera as it would follow the player around.
Here we're just smoothing from the
color that it is all the way to transparent.
And then finally at the end of every update cycle
we're setting damaged equal to false.
What that basically means is the moment we
take damage we're then going to set damage back
to false after showing that damaged image.
In the next bit here what we have is a
called TakeDamage.
Now this function is also unique because it is a
public function, as such, what this means is
other scripts and other components can
call this function.
Take damage as a special function in the script
in that it's not called in this script.
Other stuff calls this function,
so when the enemies attack the player they
call the TakeDamage function and so
again that script interactivity is important.
It has to be public or else this isn't going to work.
The one parameter or argument for this function is
int amount, which is how much damage the player has taken.
Next what we're going to do is we want to ensure
the player flashes that red image.
So we do that by saying damaged equals true.
We detract the amount of damage from our current health.
We do that using a little shorthand here
by saying currentHealth -= amount;
What that little shorthand means is we're going to say
take the current health, remove the amount of damage
and then put that back in to current health,
so basically it just reduces by that amount.
We are then going to take our current health and
parse it in to the value of our slider.
And so we see the slider slowly
shrink as the player takes more damage.
Next we're going to play our audio and if we
recall we setup an audio source on
the player in Unity
and we gave it that Player Hurt audio.
So basically every time the player takes damage they're
going to play that hurt audio.
Finally we're going to say 'the player's hurt,
is the player dead?'.
What we're going to do is say
if the current health is now below or
equal to 0, and they're not already dead,
that's what that and not isDead
make them dead, alright, because there's no sense in
making them dead if they're already dead.
If that happens we're going to call a new function called Death.
Death is a function that is in this script.
It's not built in to Unity or anything like that.
It's actually the very next function we're going to look at.
Basically if the health drops below 0
we're going to call this Death function,
and here's what the Death function does.
The first thing the Death function does is sets
isDead equal to true, saying 'yeah, okay, player is dead'.
Next we've got some disabled code, we'll come back to that.
Next we say anim.SetTrigger ("Die");
remember when we did the Animator Controller
in the animator window and we had that second
parameter which was Die which was a trigger?
This is where we play that animation
so we say SetTrigger Die and the character
plays their death animation.
We then set the audio clip of
the audio source to this Death clip
and then we play that sound, the sound the player makes
when they lose the game.
And then finally here's where we access
that script, the Player Movement script
we added as a component.
We say playerMovement.enabled = false;
which basically means no more movement.
That script component on the object gets
disabled, stops reading our inputs,
player stops moving.
And so this is that script
in it's entirety so let's go ahead and
close this down here and now we're going to
return to the Unity editor.
And again I reiterate, make sure if you
click on the player in the hierarchy
that you see the playerHeath component
at the very bottom, which will let you know that you
put that script on to the right game object.
Now that we are
back here and we have this PlayerHeath script component
on the player game object what we're
going to do is we are going to start
filling in some of these values.
So we could see Starting Health is 100, that's fine,
it's what we want.
Current Health is 0, again that doesn't matter
it'll be set in the awake function.
But here we have this Health Slider property.
And it's currently empty.
This is where we establish that link between
the UI that we created and the
script that we've just added.
So if we look in the hierarchy
we see the HUDCanvas, which we expand
and then the healthUI, which we expand,
and right here we have our HealthSlider.
So if we were to take this health slider and
click and drag and drop it in to the
Health Slider property that will link
the healthSliderUI component
with this Player Health script.
So now we can update the health via the slider.
Next we have this Damage Image,
so again I'm going to come up and grab my
Damage Image from the HUD and I'm going to click and drag
down in to the Damage Image property in the script.
And then finally I have this Death Clip,
where it currently says None I'm going to click the circle select
here and I'm going to look for
Player Death and I'm going to double click
and we'll see that that gets added there.
So the next thing I want to do now,
the player has health and the health is interfaced
with our UI system, so as the player loses
health the UI system reacts, and all that's done.
Now what we want to do is we want to give the
enemies the ability to actually attack the player
and thus we can see that this all works and
see the interactivity of our game objects.
We want to look in the Scripts folder
and we want to locate the Enemy scripts folder
and we're going to locate the EnemyAttack script.
What we want to do is click
and drag that on to the Zombunny.
Again when we select the Zombunny afterwards
we should see,
we should see EnemyAttack
at the bottom there.
Let's go ahead and open up EnemyAttack.
EnemyAttack, a lot of this stuff is going to be
very familiar to you by now,
but again we're going to start with a few public variables.
The first public variable we're interested in is a public float
timeBetweenAttacks,
which is 0.5.
It basically is the amount of time
between each of the attacks
And then we also have a public integer, which is the attackDamage.
So how much damage has each of these
attacks done to the player.
Then we have our private variables, and again
these are very similar, we have an
Animator variable named anim which is going to
store our reference to our animator component.
We have a GameObject parameter which
is going to be the player, so again the
enemy will be able to attack the player
but it needs to have some reference to that player.
We have a reference to the PlayerHealth script.
This is new, we have the enemy
referencing a script that we have created
that is on a different game object.
So the player has a PlayerHealth script
and the enemy has a reference to it
so that the enemy can then damage the player.
We have a bit of code that is commented out
and then we have a boolean value playerInRange.
This will be set to true whenever the player gets
close enough for the enemy to attack/
It'll be set back to false when the player
gets too far away.
And then finally we have float timer,
and timer is a variable that we're going to use to keep
everything in sync, to make sure that the enemy is not
not too fast, not too slow.
In our awake function, again we're going to be
setting up a lot of our stuff so
we're doing GameObject.FindGameObjectWithTag ("player");
Which again is going to locate the player for us
and store that reference locally.
We do this in the awake method and then we store it
so that we don't have to do it every frame
or every time we need it.
This is a fairly inefficient call
so we really want to limit the number of time
we do that, so by doing it once in the awake function
and storing it we're greatly improving
the performance of our games and projects.
Then we use that player object that we just found
and we say player.GetComponent
thus pulling the PlayerHealth script off
off that player, and again, storing a reference to it.
Now with that reference we have the ability to
call that public function takeDamage we saw previously.
And then finally we do GetComponent
to setup a reference to our animator component.
Now remember how we created the
sphere collider on the enemy that was a trigger
and I talked about how triggers are
not used for in-scene effects
and Will was talking about how we use these
for detecting collisions and stuff behind the scenes?
If we have a trigger on an object and
another object comes in collision with that
it doesn't react physically, because it's a trigger.
Instead it calls a function
and if we have a function in a script
that function runs.
The function's called OnTriggerEnter
and it gets called whenever anything goes
in to a trigger.
So here we have void OnTriggerEnter
and then inside parenthesis we have (Collider other).
Other is whatever it is that
collider with this collider.
If I'm the enemy and something collided with me chances
are Other is the player.
And so now I know where that is.
So the very next line is
me making sure that it's the player
because we don't want to be able to attack a sofa
we want to only attack the player and
as such we want to ensure
what it is we are attacking, so we're going to say
if(other.gameObject == player)
and that double equals is an equality operator, it says
'are these the same thing?'.
So if what we collided with is the player,
cool, okay, then we can attack it.
If that's true then we set playerInRange to true.
Now there's an inverse version of that
function called OnTriggerExit.
It tells us that something was in the trigger
and it has now gone away.
Alright, that's just the complete opposite.
So again what we're going to say is
was the thing that left the trigger the player?
If it was the player is no longer
in range, so we set that to false.
So we just used the trigger to say 'hey, they're close enough'
'no, they're not close enough any more'.
'Hey they're close enough, no they're not close enough any more'.
This isn't actually the attacking part
this is just how we determine whether we're close enough.
The actual attacking happens in the update.
In the update method the first thing we
do is we determine how much time has occurred.
We start accumulating this time
inside the variable Timer.
So every time update runs Timer gets a little bit bigger and
a little bit bigger and it represents how much time has passed.
Then we're going to say
if the timer is greater than
the time between attacks, so it's been long enough
between attacks and the player is close enough,
we're going to attack the player.
And we can see that we call the function Attack.
Then finally we'll look at Attack here in a second.
Then finally we say
if the player's health is
equal to 0, that means the player died,
right, our attack killed it and the player died
so we're going to do anim.SetTrigger ("PlayerDead");
which as we recall will transition us from the
moving state to the idle state.
Player is dead so now we just get to sit around and go
'well that was fun, now what?'.
And so that's how we stop chasing the player around.
So if the timer is greater than the time between attacks
and the player is in range then we call this aAttack function
and this is what the Attack function looks like.
The first thing we do is we reset Timer.
We're now attacking so Timer is set back to 0.
And then we're going to say if the player is alive
playerHealth.currentHealth is greater than 0,
let's take some of that away.
So we say playerHealth.takeDamage
and we parse in however much damage this enemy does.
And so then the player is going to manage
the rest of that and if that happens to kill them
the rest of the update will run and we'll
transition in to the idle state.
And so that is our enemy attack
and once we've taken a look at that
be sure to save our scene to wrap up
what we've just done here.
Why not test this? Let's pop back over to Unity.
Will, go ahead and get eaten!
Oh, and he's taken damage
and we see the health slider being reduced in size,
we see the screen flashing slightly,
and man, that Zombunny is relentless!
I don't think he wants to give you hugs.
The damage image there is quite faint.
But we can play around with that with the
Flash Color public variable on PlayerHealth
on the player.
So if we wanted to make that more apparent
we could crank it up a little bit and it would flash
a bit more harshly, like that.
Again he achieved this just now by increasing
the alpha of the color on the Player Health script.
Obviously the higher the alpha the stronger the effect
and so on and so forth.